<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A discourse of the forbearance or the penalties which a due reformation requires by H. Thorndike ...</title>
            <author>Thorndike, Herbert, 1598-1672.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1670</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 228 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 94 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A62452</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing T1044</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R1719</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12129183</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12129183</idno>
            <idno type="VID">54672</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A62452)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 54672)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 900:3)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A discourse of the forbearance or the penalties which a due reformation requires by H. Thorndike ...</title>
                  <author>Thorndike, Herbert, 1598-1672.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 179, [2] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by J.M. for James Collins ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1670.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
                  <note>Errata: p. [6]</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church renewal.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:54672:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:54672:1"/>
            <p>A <hi>DISCO<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>RSE</hi> OF THE FORBEARANCE OR THE PENALTIES Which a Due REFORMATION REQUIRES.</p>
            <p>BY <hi>H. THORNDIKE,</hi> One of the Prebends of <hi>Weſtminſter</hi> Church.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>J. M.</hi> for <hi>James Collins,</hi> at the <hi>Kings-Head</hi> in <hi>Weſtminſter-Hall,</hi> 1670.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:54672:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:54672:2"/>
            <head>THE PREFACE.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>ARiſtotle</hi> and Experience teacheth us, that no <hi>Poſitive Law</hi> can provide for all the Caſes, that may ariſe upon the Terms of it. Religion in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, in General, is a Moral Vertue; But the true Religion, that bringeth Salvation, is a <hi>Poſitive</hi> Conſtitution of Gods Grace, requiring the Condition of Chriſtianity, to qualifie for the Promiſe of life everlaſting. But upon ſeveral Terms, heretofore, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Law of Nature and <hi>Moſes,</hi> and now, under the Chriſtian Faith. The Church of Chriſt, in all Ages, hath been conſtrained, to provide new Decrees, and ſeek new Laws, for the quenching of new Hereſies and Schiſms. They that ever hoped to do that, by an Act of <hi>Compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſion,</hi> which the Act of <hi>Uniformity</hi> hath not done, would have proved them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves <hi>deceitful Workers;</hi> They would have made many Breaches, by ſtopping of One. That which I am able to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pound,
<pb facs="tcp:54672:3"/> I confeſs, is rather poſſible than probable. For, were it ſo far advanced, as to be inacted for a Law of the Kingdom; I ſhould never believe, that it would take effect; unleſs the Faith and the Laws of the Catholick Church might be received, to give Bounds to all emergent Diſputes. No more then I can believe, that the Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation will ever prevail, after one <hi>Breach</hi> in <hi>Germany,</hi> after another ſince in the <hi>United Provinces,</hi> and theſe laſt here amongſt us; unleſs we unite our ſelves upon the ſame Principle. Whether I have ſaid enough to prove it well grounded, or not, I muſt refer that to Judgment. But he that excuſes me not, in ſuch an innocent <hi>Propoſition</hi> as this; How would he have Almighty God to excuſe me, if, having attained this <hi>Reſolution,</hi> I ſhould not declare the Conſequence of it, in our preſent Caſe? Eſpecially, conſidering the Duty, which the Law of the Land, juſtly and neceſſarily impoſes upon all of my Order; to Reduce <hi>Recuſants</hi> to Church. For, there are now <hi>two ſorts of Recu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſants:</hi> And thoſe that are bound to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce them, muſt do it upon ſuch Reaſons, that by reducing the one ſort, they drive not the other ſort from Church. Let
<pb facs="tcp:54672:3"/> them that have more skill then I ſhew, how it can be done, without imploying my Principle. I, that am reſolved, it can by no other means be done, muſt declare my Reſolution, though I were to ſuffer for it; Which, from a <hi>Chriſtian Kingdom,</hi> I cannot do. One thing I have adventured, upon my own Head; Granting, that the Government of the Church was <hi>Regular,</hi> till after the ſixth General Council: And ſo, that the the Acts of the Church before that time, are effects of it. But that is not to ſay, that the <hi>Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption</hi> of the Church, which we <hi>Proteſt</hi> againſt, and <hi>Reform,</hi> began not till that time. Religion began to be corrupted ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lier in ſome, and later in other <hi>Points.</hi> But this Corruption had not the force of <hi>Law,</hi> till after that time: And eſpecially, till the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſurpation of the See of <hi>Rome.</hi> It is enough, that there is difference <hi>Viſible,</hi> in any Point, between that which was <hi>from the beginning,</hi> according to the Scriptures, and that which was, when the Reformation was attempted. That which can be made out hereof, will ſerve to cramp both ſorts of Recuſants: That which cannot, ſhould be no cauſe of difference. He that reduces the <hi>ſenſe of the Scripture, within the
<pb facs="tcp:54672:4" rendition="simple:additions"/> Faith and the Laws of the whole Church,</hi> warrants the Penalties of Recuſants. Let the Laws do their <hi>Office,</hi> and make it a <hi>Diſgrace,</hi> to be out of the Church; And then we may expect, to ſee the Bleſſing of God, up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on his own Ordinance. But without reſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring Diſcipline, without Canons and Laws to reſtore it, without the Office of the Synods, in providing thoſe Canons, let no man think, that temporal Penalties will ſerve to do the buſineſs. For, though there can be no reaſon ſufficient, for violating the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity of the Church; yet, if the diſſatisfaction that hath cauſed it, reſolve into a defect of the Laws, it can no more be ended, without redreſſing the Laws, then a Diſeaſe can be cured, without taking away the Cauſe of it.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>Errata.</head>
            <p>PAg. 10. lin. 13. r. Propheſies ſent, ſince the Ground o Salvation was declared, is—p. 17. l. 5. the Church, read <hi>this Church,</hi> p. 20. l. 27. the Article of this Church, r. <hi>the Law of this Kingdom,</hi> p. 22. l. 3. Chriſtians, r. <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian,</hi> p. 25. l. 27. decay, r. <hi>decays,</hi> p. 36. l. 1. or to be believed to, r. <hi>to be believed or to,</hi> p. 42. l. 29. Laws, r. <hi>Law.</hi> p. 63. l. 20. the beſt, r. <hi>their beſt,</hi> p. 99. l. 28. Churches, r. <hi>Church,</hi> p. 109. l. 28. making, r. <hi>and making,</hi> p. 113. l. 5. Chriſts, r. <hi>Chriſt,</hi> p. 121. l. 12. which, r. <hi>of whom,</hi> p. 125. l. 21. to come to, r. <hi>come to,</hi> p. 151. l. 17. Idolaters, r. <hi>Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latry,</hi> p, 153. l. 18. Invocations, r. <hi>Invocation,</hi> p. 263. l. 16. theſe, r. <hi>thoſe.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="discourse">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:54672:4"/>
            <head>OF THE FORBEARANCE OR PENALTIES Which a due Reformation requires.</head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. I. The Caſe, in which forbearance is pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended for weak Conſciences.</head>
               <p>IT is a long time, that the <hi>forbear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance</hi> due to tender Conſciences hath been alledged, for the means to reſtore Unity in this Church. And certainly, were the Caſe ſtated, in which S. <hi>Paul</hi> preſcribed it to the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> that ſo it might be drawn into Conſequence in our Caſe; the Scripture muſt needs produce that which would be of advantage for Peace, without prejudice to Truth. But, when
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:54672:5"/> the bare Phraſe of Scripture is toſſed up and down, in the diſcourſe of them that care not to underſtand, either the Reaſon upon which it is grounded, or the Effect to which it ſorteth; no marvel to ſee the decay of Religion proceed from the abuſe of the Scripture. We need not the He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſies of the Primitive Times; even the abominable Villanies of the <hi>Gnoſticks;</hi> to tell us, what irreligious pretenſes may be ſet forth in Scripture Phraſe. Our own Fanaticks would furniſh ſport enough, with the fooleries which they pretend, as from Gods Spirit, becauſe they can deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver their non-ſenſe in the Phraſe of Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture; could ſuch irreligious madneſs move any thing, but the compaſſion and lamentation of Chriſtians. It is enough for my purpoſe, that, unleſs the Precept of the Apoſtle be limited to that conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence, which the reaſon of the Caſe will produce; the two-edged Sword of the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Scripture may prove an edge tool, to cut their ſhins with, who take upon them, and have not the skill to handle it. For the ſtate of the Caſe, to which S. <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeaks, I will ſay no more at preſent, but this; That he preſcribeth only to the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> at that time, when the
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:54672:5"/> care was, not to looſe the Jews, by winning the Gentiles to be Chriſtians. There could then be no queſtion, of eſtabliſhing a Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tional Church, by the Law of a Kingdom; which Church, and which Kingdom ſhall; by that Law, reform that which it proteſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth to have been decayed, and depraved, in the Faith and Laws of the then preſent Church. We have a Reformation eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed by certain Laws of the Kingdom; which, all men know, how great a part of the Kingdom declineth, becauſe the See of <hi>Rome</hi> diſclaimeth it. And therefore the queſtion is, what that Law ſhould be, that may oblige Recuſants, to the Reformati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on which we profeſs. For, diviſion in Religion can never ſo deprave mens ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, as to puniſh them for refuſing that, which they are not obliged to embrace. And yet, who would have the Kingdom to eſtabliſh that Reformation, which they would not have it inact by competent Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nalties? Now, ſuch is our Caſe, that, ſince the afflictions, which this Nation hath been viſited with, have revived the humor of departing into Conventicles, Independents and Fanaticks decline Communion with this Church, as much as Recuſants; And, if we will ſpeak properly, to be underſtood
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:54672:6"/> according to the Laws, we muſt diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh them, by the addition of <hi>Popiſh</hi> or <hi>Fanatick</hi> Recuſants. Whereupon the queſtion ariſes, what Penalties are compe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent to the one &amp; to the other; whether the ſame or diverſe. For, as there can be no Law, if there can be no Penalties to enact it with; So, there can be no Penalty, unleſs the Legiſlative Power be Judge of the Cauſe, why the Parties decline the Law; and may ſecure them in Conſcience, that they ought not to decline it. Can any Chriſtian Power puniſh the diſobeying of that Law, concerning which, it cannot ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure the Conſciences of them that obey? But there is a further difficulty in our Caſe, in regard of the Preſbyterians; Who, whatſoever they may do, or may have done, ſince the time of diſorder, have al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways pretended to the ſervice of the Church; ſo far from diſclaiming Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion with it. For, grant they do uſurp the liberty of Conventicles, to hold their People at the more diſtance, from being reduced to Law; their pretenſe is not, to be obnoxious to the Law, for violating it, but to make the Law obnoxious to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, by reforming it. Suppoſe we them then, comprehended with the Clergy,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:54672:6"/> (whoſe Authority is included in the preſent Laws) in the ſame Priviledge, of mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtring in and to the Church; Our Caſe is not ſtated, till we conſider that, which all Pulpits ring of, that <hi>no Religion</hi> ſtands to be the Religion of the Kingdom. The Caſe was like to come to this, when <hi>Crom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well</hi> firſt uſurped. For then it began to appear, that this would be the fruit of his Courſe, in maintaining all Parties in the Religions, which the licentiouſneſs of the War had allowed them to exerciſe. The Laws having recovered poſſeſſion, and the diſpute remaining, by what Penalties to be exerciſed, whether any or none, whether thoſe that are, or what others; I need not ſay, that there is any Profeſſion of Atheiſm; (which could never be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed among the very Gentiles) This I ſay, that, whoſoever favours it, will ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarily ſhelter himſelf under the Law, profeſſing that which it maintaineth. And therefore, that it is to come into the ſtate of our Caſe, in which, Forbearance is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded for tender Conſciences; how it is to be limited; That thoſe who have No Religion, if any ſuch ſhould be, may not have the Benefit of it. So, the queſtion now in hand is of the ſame conſequence, as
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:54672:7"/> if it were demanded, upon what terms the Reformation of the Church is to be ſtated. For whatſoever comes to debate, the que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion will always be, how far we ought to depart from the Church of <hi>Rome.</hi> The other part of the queſtion; What Penal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties the Reformation, duly ſtated, may or is to be inacted with; will depend upon this, for the greater part of it. For, what can render the ſubject of this Kingdom lia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to Penalty, for not obeying the Law which our Reformation is eſtabliſhed with; but, that he is firſt bound in conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to embrace the Reformation, and to do the duty of a Chriſtian according to it? Only what Penalties, and how great, or or how grievous, it is to be, or may be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>acted with; This will further require the reaſon, which makes it the duty of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian States, to joyn in Reforming the Church.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:54672:7"/>
               <head>CHAP. II. That a private Perſon may be obliged to declare in it.</head>
               <p>THis is that which obliges a private perſon, as I am, to declare his Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, when ſo great a concernment of his Conſcience is at ſtake. For, who could ever think the Reformation could ſtand, were not the Clergy obliged, as the Law obliges them, every one in his place, to reduce Recuſants to the Church? Or, how ſhould they either do this, or ſtand obliged to do it, if the Reaſon, upon which the Reformation, and the Law by which it is ſtated proceeds, inable them not to convince them, that they are bound in Conſcience to embrace it? Theſe hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred years hath the diſpute been on foot. Very nigh ſo long it is, ſince the Bull of <hi>Pius</hi> V. acquited the Subjects of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, of their Allegiance to Q. <hi>Elizabeth.</hi> The Government being then jealous of that Party; thoſe that had appeared before in the <hi>Troubles of Francford,</hi> to challenge a ſhare in the Government of the Church,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:54672:8"/> thought this the time to ſet their preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions on foot. It is to be ſeen, by <hi>Camdens</hi> Annals, that, when the Recuſants firſt for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bore coming to Church, about that time, did this Party begin to be known, by the name of <hi>Puritans.</hi> Ever ſince that time, did theſe embers lye raked up in deceitful aſhes, ſtill moſt appearing, when the State was moſt ſolicitous; till at length <hi>the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty appeared in Arms</hi> againſt the late King; and, prevailing in thoſe Arms, became divided into thoſe ſeveral Parties, which remain united in the Plea for <hi>tender Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences.</hi> For, the Laws recovering by His Majeſties return, the ſame embers, which it was then thought fit to rake up again, in the ſame deceitful aſhes, upon the firſt rub, have flamed out again, to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand Law, to juſtifie that which they <hi>uſurp,</hi> by way of <hi>Fact,</hi> againſt Law; Both pleading, that their Conſciences cannot be ſubject to any Law in the Caſe; and that Chriſtianity hath not wherewith to clear up thoſe doubts, againſt which if they proceed, they are damned. It muſt therefore needs be ſaid, that the preſent Laws have been juſtified, beyond all con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradiction, that may pretend, any thing to be commanded by the Laws, which Gods
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:54672:8"/> Law forbids; So that, the demand of new Laws ſeems to be a demand, that the <hi>Concluſion</hi> be contradictory to that which is inferred by the <hi>Premiſes.</hi> And, what ſhould <hi>Weakneſs</hi> demand of <hi>Reaſon,</hi> that is to give Law, but inconſequence? Only, let not inconſequence in Reaſon draw miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chief upon us in effect. We have hither<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to anſwered the demand; <hi>Where was your Church before Luther?</hi> That it was where it is; The <hi>ſame Church Reformed,</hi> which was decayed and depraved afore. Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther can we ever anſwer otherwiſe, till we renounce our Creed, and deny that <hi>One Holy Catholick Church,</hi> which, we muſt be ſaved by believing, and by continuing in the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity</hi> of it. Depart we once from theſe <hi>terms of our Reformation,</hi> what ſhall we plead, with a good Conſcience, to bring Recuſants to Church? It will be ſaid, that the Pope is Antichriſt, and the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> all I Idolaters: that there can be no queſtion, of <hi>abandoning Idolatry and Antichriſt.</hi> But is there no queſtion of holding the true Faith, of continuing a true Church, parting with Idolatry and Antichriſt? Were Papiſts Idolaters, and the Pope Antichriſt a thouſand times, the Reaſon, and the Rule of Reforming the
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:54672:9" rendition="simple:additions"/> Church would be where it is; and will require, that it be ſo Reformed, as to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue a Member of one <hi>Catholick Church,</hi> as it was unreformed; ſaving the Unity, which cannot be held, without the conſent of thoſe that will not be reformed. Not that I grant the pretenſe of Idolatry and Antichriſt; Or, that I intend to diſpute againſt it at preſent, being a queſtion too large to be voided, by ſo ſhort a Diſcourſe as this. But that, to ground our Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation, and Salvation, upon the interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of Propheſies, is a thing without the compaſs of Reaſon to do; And alſo a departure from that <hi>Plea,</hi> upon which our Reformation is hitherto ſtated. Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving therefore placed my buſineſs, and ſpent my time, in conſidering the Contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſies, which the Reformation hath occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſioned; Becauſe the Diſputes we have among our ſelves concern nothing, but how far we are to depart from the Church of <hi>Rome;</hi> I thought my ſelf tyed in Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, to publiſh the Reſolution I had attained, both under the danger, that might be expected, from the late Uſurpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and at His Majeſties happy return. So that, the publiſhing of my <hi>Opinion in the Caſe</hi> at this time in diſpute, is but a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claration
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:54672:9"/> of the conſequences, that have enſued, becauſe <hi>a palliative cure</hi> hath not ſerved the turn. If they that break Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty in the Church, have liberty to plead for their their <hi>Conventicles,</hi> which they <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſurp</hi> againſt <hi>Law;</hi> why ſhould not my Opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on expect a favourable Audience? Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſting before God, that, how advanta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious ſoever I think it, to the Salvation of Souls, yet I do not deſire that it ſhould take place, but by the <hi>free Act</hi> of this Church and Kingdom.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. III. That the Rule of Reformation is the Catholick Church.</head>
               <p>IN the firſt place, therefore, I hold my ſelf bound in Conſcience, upon this occaſion, freely to declare to <hi>my Superi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ours;</hi> That there is no Power in this Church and Kingdom, to reform it ſelf in matter of Religion, but only by that Form, and to that Form, which may ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear to have been held by the <hi>whole Primi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Church,</hi> before the Corruption came in, which we pretend to Reform. And
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:54672:10"/> the reaſon hereof is unanſwerable; being immediately grounded upon the <hi>Article of our Creed,</hi> whereby we profeſs to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve <hi>one Catholick and Apoſtolick Church.</hi> For, if there be ſuch a thing in the world, then muſt there be one <hi>Catholick Faith,</hi> the Profeſſion whereof is the <hi>condition of Communion</hi> with it; And one and the ſame Laws, the violating whereof is the forfeiture of the ſame. And here I crave leave, to call all <hi>Canons,</hi> all <hi>Cuſtoms</hi> of the Church, whether concerning the <hi>Rites</hi> of Gods Service, or other Obſervations; whether delivered in writing, or received by <hi>ſilent <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe and Practice;</hi> by one and the ſame general name, of <hi>Laws of the Church;</hi> Only, that I may be the better under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood. Being therefore well aſſured, that the Church cannot be <hi>Catholick,</hi> but it needs muſt be <hi>Viſible;</hi> Becauſe it can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be Catholick, till it may be Viſibly diſtinguiſhed, from Heretick and Schiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matick both; I muſt alſo infer, that it can never be Viſible, till it become Catholick. That is the only way, to juſtifie that which hath been always pretended; that this Church is the ſame, that it was before <hi>Luthers</hi> time. For, as the Church had never been Catholick, had it been confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:54672:10"/> to one Nation, as the Synagogue was; So I do believe, that it had never been called <hi>Catholick,</hi> had there not been He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſies and Schiſms, before it was ſo called. It had been <hi>One Church of all Nations,</hi> by virtue of the Converſion of the Gentiles. When Hereſies ſprung up, as Tares among the Corn, then was it called <hi>Catholick,</hi> for diſtinctions ſake. It was viſible, that the true Faith was ſpread all over; Hereſies and Schiſms prevailed but here and there, where they were raiſed. So, if an Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick or Schiſmatick were aſked the way to the <hi>Catholick Church,</hi> he durſt not have ſhewed the way to his own, ſaith S. <hi>Auſtin.</hi> Nor is it a queſtion to be aſked a Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an, why the true Church ſhould be <hi>Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick;</hi> The anſwer being ſo obvious, that it was <hi>Apoſiolick.</hi> Say why the Faith preached by the Apoſtles prevailed, why the Communion ſetled by their Authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty; (whereas Hereſies and Schiſms were known but here and there) and you have ſaid, why the True Church was Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholick. We that profeſs the Reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion are agreed, that this proviſion of Gods goodneſs is no <hi>Promiſe</hi> of God, againſt mans malice; That corruption may become Catholick, for the preſent
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:54672:11"/> Age, though not from the Apoſtles. This is the common ground of Reforming the Church; If the meaſure and bounds which it limiteth were alſo common, all our diviſions were at an end. Nor can any <hi>private Spirit,</hi> expounding the Scripture without theſe bounds, derogate from it. It is a ſufficient prejudice, againſt any In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpretation of Scripture, that it ſtandeth not with the Faith, and with the Laws of the Primitive Church. S. <hi>Paul</hi> challeng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the <hi>prophets at Corinth,</hi> to ſhew them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves <hi>Spiritual</hi> men, by ſubmitting to his Orders; Having ſaid, that <hi>the Spirits of the Prophets are ſubject to the Prophets:</hi> and inferring, that <hi>all their Spirits are to be ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject to his,</hi> being an Apoſtle, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> XIV. 32, 36, 37. The ſame is the Caſe to the Worlds end; the promiſe of our Lord, <hi>Behold, I am with you to the worlds end;</hi> being made to the <hi>Apoſtles,</hi> and to all that ſhould be Chriſts <hi>Diſciples,</hi> and learn <hi>of the Apoſtles, to do all that he hath command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed,</hi> Mat. XXVIII. 19, 20. For, who can think he continueth in the Doctrine of the Apoſtles, departing from their <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority,</hi> in any thing ſubject to their Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority? Or what is not ſubject to their Authority, excepting that which our
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:54672:11"/> Lord had commanded, before he gave them their Authority? His own Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands being the condition of Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; Their Authority, the means provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, to inable us to attain it, by obſerving and learning his Commands. So, as it is <hi>Hereſie,</hi> to depart from the Faith which they preached; ſo is it <hi>Schiſm,</hi> to depart from the Authority which they left in the Church, till the Worlds end. Were not the Catholick Church a Warrant to parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular Churches, they could not Reform themſelves, without the conſent of the Whole. But, ſeeing abuſes are and were <hi>Viſible</hi> at the Reformation, it is neceſſary to grant, that particular Churches (and ſecular Powers, by whoſe Laws they ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt) may reſtore that which may appear to have been decayed; But it is alſo neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary to ſay, that Reformation is the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoring of that which was, not the intro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducing of that which was not.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:54672:12"/>
               <head>CHAP. IV. That the Church is no further Viſible, then it is Catholick.</head>
               <p>ANd thus ſhall the <hi>Church</hi> become <hi>Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible,</hi> according to the Will and Ordinance of God; which, being in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cay by the malice of man, though <hi>not In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſible,</hi> yet muſt needs become <hi>hard to be ſeen,</hi> at leaſt to the purpoſe of Gods good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs. For, by the diſcourſe premiſed it appears, why it pleaſed God to provide, that the true Church ſhould be Catholick. That is to ſay, that when it was ſo eaſie to diſcern the True Church, from all that pretended, being indeed Hereticks or Schiſmaticks; the ſimpleſt were left with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out excuſe, if they made a wrong choice. Which if it be true, how can it be in the Power of any Church, or of the ſecular Powers that maintain it, being bound to continue a Member of the whole Church, to introduce that for Reformation, which cannot appear to be reſtored, but may ſeem to be innovated? Which, how ſhould it be done, without owning that
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:54672:12" rendition="simple:additions"/> ground of Reformation, which I have de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered; and by conſequence, thoſe bounds, which the ſaid ground inferreth? And I do very well believe, that none of thoſe, who decline Conformity with the Church, would have the Face to deny this, had they to do with the now <hi>Miſſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naries</hi> of the Church of <hi>Rome.</hi> For it would not ſerve their turn, in anſwer to them, to plead, that the Pope is Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt, and the Papiſts Idolaters; having Reaſon to challenge, that God hath found<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed a Viſible Church. It would be abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutely neceſſary to plead; though the goodneſs of God hath <hi>inſtituted</hi> a Viſible Church, yet, that, by the malice of man, it might be, and is <hi>become Inviſible,</hi> for the difficulty of finding Salvation by it; though <hi>abſolutely Viſible,</hi> becauſe Salvation might always be had in it. It is eaſie for him, that would anſwer them with a good Conſcience, for Truth and not for Victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, to maintain the Church to be Viſible, ſo far as the <hi>Faith</hi> and <hi>the Laws</hi> thereof con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue Viſible. But that, ſo far as the Faith and Laws thereof may be diſguiſed, from that which was from the beginning, ſo far it may and is to be ſaid, that the Church, which by Gods Ordinance is and ought to
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:54672:13"/> be Viſible, by humane diſorder is become Inviſible. Which being ſaid, it follows immediately, that, as all eſtates in the Church are obliged, in their ſeveral qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities, to do their utmoſt, that the Church may be Viſible; (the Salvation of all Chriſtians requiring them to Reſort to the Communion of the Church, which they believe to be Catholick) ſo, there is no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther way to make it Viſible, but to reſtore the Faith and the Laws of the Church, that from the beginning made it Viſible. And therefore, no Chriſtian Church or State can have Power, to Reform the Church any otherwiſe, then, by reſtoring that Faith, and thoſe Laws, which the Church may appear to have had from the beginning. It would be <hi>Sacriledge,</hi> and <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſurpation</hi> upon the Faith, which God hath built his Church upon; and upon the Laws, which either the Apoſtles have de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered to the Church, or inabled the Church to deliver to poſterity; to intro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce any thing elſe for the Reformation of the Church. Which ſeeing it muſt needs bind over the Church and Kingdom, to the wrath of God; as either deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctive, or at leaſt prejudicial to the Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the People; muſt needs bind over
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:54672:13"/> him that hath this opinion, to the ſame, if, upon ſo juſt an occaſion, he ſhould for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bear to publiſh and to plead it as he may, without offenſe. And therefore, I take leave to blame all thoſe, who declare, in behalf of this Church, that it departeth, and <hi>ſeparateth</hi> it ſelf from the Church of <hi>Rome.</hi> For, ſeeing it hath been granted, in and by this Church, ever ſince the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation, that there is and always was Salvation to be had in the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> as a true Church, though corrupt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; I am very confident, that no Church can ſeparate from the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> but they muſt make themſelves thereby <hi>Schiſmaticks before God;</hi> though, before the Church, they cannot be condemned for ſuch, becauſe the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> (the Authority whereof muſt needs be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gredient into the Sentence) cannot oblige any Body, to ſtand to the <hi>Authority,</hi> which it ſo abuſeth. For, if God have tied <hi>all Churches to Communion with all Churches,</hi> how ſhould it not be <hi>Schiſm,</hi> to profeſs Separation from a true Church? And it is every whit as eaſie to ſay, that we in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend only to Reform our ſelves: and that the Separation hath come to paſs, by the rigour of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> Excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municating
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:54672:14" rendition="simple:additions"/> thoſe that Reform themſelves without her leave.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. V. How far this Rule is owned by this Church.</head>
               <p>HEre, it will perhaps be demanded, whether or no, the Law of this Land make this the Rule of the Reformation which we Profeſs. And my Anſwer is, that <hi>in effect,</hi> and <hi>by conſequence</hi> it doth. For, by maintaining the <hi>three Creeds</hi> to be part of the Service, wherewith we glorifie God, by Profeſſing the Catholick Faith; and by maintaining the <hi>four Councils,</hi> whereby, both the Faith, and the then Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nons of the whole Church are eſtabliſhed; it doth in effect maintain the <hi>Primitive Church,</hi> not only till that time, but beyond it. For, ſeeing it is evident, that the fifth and ſixth Councils are but appendances of the Fourth; (tending only to maintain and inforce the decree of it) how can it be doubted, that the Article of this Church; receiving all Councils, that have decreed according to the <hi>Word of God;</hi> receiveth
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:54672:14"/> and inacteth thoſe, which tend only to inforce the Fourth; which it own<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, for decreeing that Faith which the <hi>Word of God</hi> teacheth? Beſides the pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers for the proſperity of the <hi>Catholick Church;</hi> whereby we prove our ſelves no Schiſmaticks, to the See of <hi>Rome,</hi> when we repay the <hi>Curſes</hi> of it with our prayers. Beſides that <hi>Injunction</hi> of <hi>Edward</hi> the VI, which obligeth all Preachers, to expound the Scripture, according to the <hi>Conſent of the Ancient Fathers.</hi> Which, as no man can ſay, why it ſhould not be in force; So, had it been in force, we need not have come to the queſtion now on foot. And indeed, it is, in effect, that which I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand. For it will be found, that the <hi>Conſent of the Fathers</hi> is not to be had, but in the common <hi>Faith,</hi> and in thoſe <hi>Laws,</hi> which the <hi>whole Church</hi> either enjoyned, or allowed particular Churches. So that, to expound the Scriptures according to the <hi>Conſent of the Fathers,</hi> is to expound them within thoſe bounds; and to trouble the heads of Chriſtian people with no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, that is without the ſame; As if their Salvation could be concerned, all being ſafe within thoſe bounds. Here I muſt take notice, that the reaſon, why the
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:54672:15"/> Church <hi>Catholick,</hi> is to be held, may be miſkenned; if it be extended to all that is called <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> and not limited to that, which, maintaining the <hi>Faith,</hi> violateth not the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity</hi> of the Primitive Church. If the profeſſion of <hi>Chriſt</hi> and <hi>Chriſtianity</hi> were enough, to make men members of the Catholick Church, why ſhould not <hi>Socinians</hi> and <hi>Anabaptiſts</hi> belong to the Church <hi>diſperſed over the face of the whole earth?</hi> Again, the <hi>Eaſtern Chriſtians,</hi> that are thought to come from <hi>Neſtorius;</hi> the <hi>Southern Chriſtians</hi> under <hi>Preſter John,</hi> that maintain the memory of <hi>Dioſcorus,</hi> and condemn the fourth Council of <hi>Chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedon,</hi> cannot be admitted to be <hi>Catholicks,</hi> by any man that owneth the four Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cils. But, in regard it appeareth not, that they owne the <hi>Hereſies</hi> of <hi>Neſtorius</hi> and <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyches,</hi> though they owne the memory of their <hi>perſons;</hi> and in regard there is cauſe enough to preſume, that they would, with all their hearts, be <hi>reunited</hi> to the Church, did not the See of <hi>Rome</hi> refuſe all terms of Re-union, that include not the <hi>infinite power</hi> which it challengeth; they cannot be included within the Catholick Church without reſerving a liberty to exclude them, whenſoever, in point of Faith, it
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:54672:15"/> ſhall appear, that they owne the <hi>Hereſies</hi> of <hi>Neſtorius</hi> and <hi>Eutyches.</hi> As for the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nons of the Church, it was never neceſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, to the maintenance of Communion, that the ſame <hi>Cuſtoms</hi> ſhould be held in all parts of the Church; It was only neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, that <hi>ſeveral Cuſtoms</hi> ſhould be held by the <hi>ſame Authority.</hi> Which is to ſay; That the ſame Authority inſtituted ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Cuſtoms, which they thought to be for the beſt, in ſeveral times, and in ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral places. For ſo, they might be chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged by the ſame Authority, and yet Unity remain. Whereas, <hi>queſtioning the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority;</hi> by queſtioning whether the Acts of it be <hi>agreeable to Gods Law</hi> or not; how ſhould Unity be maintained? This is the Reaſon of that which I ſaid even now; that the <hi>Fathers</hi> do not agree in any thing, but in the Faith and the Laws of the Church. For it is manifeſt, that they could not have agreed in the Laws of the Church, if any had excepted againſt any thing, uſed in any part of the Church, as if Gods Law had been infringed by it. Seeing therefore it is manifeſt, that there are certain Canons and Cuſtoms, known to have been the <hi>Canons and Cuſtoms of the Primitive Church,</hi> owned by this Church; it
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:54672:16"/> followeth of neceſſity, that nothing can be diſowned by this Church, as <hi>contrary to Gods Law,</hi> which holdeth by the Primi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Church. So, it is not my intent to ſay, that the Canons and Cuſtoms of the Primitive Church ought to be in force: And, that there is no other means to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtore Unity in the Church. But, that no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing can <hi>cauſe a Breach</hi> in the Church, that hath Authority from the Primitive Church. And that nothing can have Authority in the preſent Church, that in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fringeth the Authority of the Primitive Church; as if Gods Law were deſtroyed by any Act of it. Further, there are two points in the <hi>Title</hi> and <hi>Cauſe</hi> of the late War; <hi>Epiſcopacy and Sacriledge;</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, the Cauſe of the Crown hath been ſo united to the Cauſe, both of <hi>this</hi> and of <hi>the Catholick Church,</hi> that I may well ſay, that, to diſowne the ſame Cauſe in other points, alike Primitive and Catholick, would be to deny the <hi>Concluſion</hi> admitting the <hi>Premiſes;</hi> Or to keep <hi>divers weights and meaſures</hi> in the ſame Budget. The Plea for <hi>Epiſcopacy,</hi> and for <hi>Conſecrate Goods,</hi> hath made out ſo much evidence for it ſelf, that it hath helped to recover the Laws of the Kingdom. And ſhall
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:54672:16"/> not the Laws of the Kingdom, ſo recover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, maintain the ſame Plea, in all other things? For, the Viſible Unity of the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholick Church, as it never ſubſiſted, but <hi>in the conſent of Biſhops,</hi> ſo was it never maintained, but <hi>out of Conſecrate Goods.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. VI. What Errours have followed, becauſe it is not ſo <hi>expreſly.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>BUt I do freely acknowledge, that, though this Church hath many <hi>Obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gations,</hi> to owne this Principle, for their Rule; yet, it is not <hi>formally</hi> and <hi>expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly</hi> inacted, by thoſe Laws of the Land, whereby Religion, and the Rights of the Church are eſtabliſhed. For I do further claim, that the want of inacting and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forcing it, and driving it home to the true Conſequence, in every point, is the Cauſe and Sourſe, not only of the diſorders, which divers pitiful plaiſters have been tendred to cure; But of all diſorders, imperfections, and decays of Religion, which have ſucceeded upon the Reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; having been made without limiting
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:54672:17"/> thoſe bounds. And, that the preſent diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>orders in Religion are the <hi>Symptoms</hi> of a common diſeaſe, which all men are of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended with, but cannot be cured, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out recourſe to the Unity of the Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Church, and the terms of it; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in that health of Chriſtianity conſiſteth, which all diviſion impeacheth. I do therefore freely acknowledge, that I find two poſitions, to be the ſourſe of all thoſe <hi>Excentrical Opinions</hi> in Religion, which cauſed that <hi>Confuſion,</hi> upon the iſſue of the War, that helped to make way for his Majeſties happy Return. The firſt is, that there is <hi>no Condition for the Covenant of Grace;</hi> That there is no <hi>Contract</hi> in it, but a meer <hi>Promiſe.</hi> The ſecond is, that there is no ſuch thing as a <hi>Viſible Church,</hi> inſtituted by God; But, that men are firſt <hi>Children of God by Faith,</hi> then members of a Church, of free choice. Of theſe Poſitions, the one neceſſarily dependeth upon the other. For, the Faith of the whole Church from the beginning re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires <hi>Baptiſm</hi> to Salvation. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, <hi>includeth it in that Faith,</hi> which a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone juſtifieth. And by conſequence requires, that <hi>juſtifying Faith</hi> cannot be underſtood, without that <hi>Profeſſion of
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:54672:17"/> 
                     <hi>Faith,</hi> which a man maketh at his Baptiſm. And this will neceſſarily infer a Church, therefore <hi>Viſible, becauſe Catholick.</hi> For it is agreed upon by the whole Church, that <hi>Baptiſm in Hereſie or Schiſm,</hi> (That is, when a man gives up himſelf to the Communion of Hereticks or Schiſmaticks, by recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving Baptiſm from them) though it may be true Baptiſm, and not to be repeated, being given in the form of the Church; yet is not available to Salvation; making him acceſſory to Hereſie or Schiſm, that is ſo Baptized. Now, it is not my intent to ſay, that theſe two Poſitions were <hi>ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſly and formally</hi> profeſſed, by Compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies diſtinguiſhing themſelves from o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, by Eccleſiaſtical Communion in the Profeſſion; Which is the true ſignifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of an <hi>Hereſie, in the eye of the Church.</hi> But the Poſitions I maintain to be Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies, in ſo much that, if there were ſuch Companies, they muſt of neceſſity be taken for Hereſies, in the account of the Church. And my Reaſon is clear. For it is ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledged by the whole Church, clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly delivered by our Lord in the Goſpel, that the taking up of his Croſs is a neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary condition to Salvation. Now, ſince our Lord gave Commiſſion to his Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles,
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:54672:18"/> to <hi>Baptize all Nations in the Name of the Father, Son and Holy Ghoſt;</hi> it is evident, that ever ſince, we take up Chriſts Croſs, when we undertake at our Baptiſm, to lay down our lives, rather then <hi>deny the Faith</hi> of Chriſt, or <hi>tranſgreſs</hi> his Commandments.</hi> And ſince this Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe is not available, unleſs it be depoſited with the true Church; it cannot be avail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, to him that continueth not in the true Church, that may exact the Promiſe depoſited with it. If any man aſk, whom I can charge with theſe Poſitions, which, I cannot ſhew to have been <hi>Profeſſed by Viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Bodies;</hi> I diſcharge my ſelf upon a number of <hi>Pamphlets,</hi> of the time of that Confuſion, which was called the <hi>Bleſſed Reformation;</hi> wherein <hi>free Grace</hi> was made to be the <hi>pardon of ſin before it is done; Juſtification</hi> to be the <hi>Revelation of predeſtination to Glory,</hi> and <hi>no ſin to be ſeen in Gods Elect.</hi> One particularly; which I have cauſe to believe was printed by <hi>Cromwells</hi> own Appointment; becauſe it anſwered a <hi>Petition of Welſh Fanaticks,</hi> which charged him to depart from his <hi>Principles;</hi> anſwers expreſly, that the Principle of Salvation is neither <hi>Faith</hi> nor <hi>good Works,</hi> but <hi>Chriſt</hi> living in the heart,
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:54672:18"/> and abiding there, whatever <hi>Principles</hi> the <hi>Godly</hi> may change. And for the Church, have we not ſeen our <hi>Indepen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent Congregations,</hi> or, do we not ſee them in <hi>New-England,</hi> refuſe Baptiſm to all, that will not take <hi>the Covenant,</hi> which they ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>point themſelves to take; and owne no other Churches, but ſuch Congregations? I ſuppoſe, no man in his right ſenſes will imagine, that there can be a Catholick Church, conſiſting in the <hi>Communion</hi> of all ſuch <hi>Congregations:</hi> Or, that there can be any Faith, to give Law to their Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion; who have the Law in their own hand, to be to morrow Socinians if they pleaſe; Or any other Sect, that allows Independent Congregations. For, the So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cinians may ſeem to have the Elderſhip of <hi>New-England,</hi> for Independent Congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions. On the other ſide, do we not ſee the <hi>Leviathan,</hi> that Monſter of a Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an, openly Profeſs, that he is bound to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce Chriſt with his mouth, if his Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raign command; Though ſtill bound to believe in him at the heart? So utterly perſwaded, that there is no ſuch thing as a Church, of Gods Ordinance; But only by the <hi>Act of Soveraign Powers,</hi> within the reſpective Dominions of each of them;
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:54672:19"/> That he had rather renounce his <hi>Baptiſm,</hi> (and ſo the Benefit of it) then owne any <hi>Creed,</hi> or any <hi>Catholick Church.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. VII. That it is for the Intereſt of the Reformation, as much as of the See of <hi>Rome.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>HAving therefore obſerved (upon due conſideration, as I hope) that all the Errours, which have had Vogue during our late Confuſions, are reducible to theſe <hi>two Poſitions,</hi> deſtructive to two Articles of our Creed, that Profeſs <hi>one Catholick Church,</hi> and <hi>one Baptiſm for remiſſion of Sins;</hi> I am ſtill led by the ſame Conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, to think my ſelf tyed in Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, freely to Profeſs; that, where theſe two Poſitions clearly renounced, and the ſenſe of thoſe two Articles duely eſtabliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and received by all Parties, that owne the ſame Creed, the Re-union of the whole Church, muſt needs follow. For, the Power of the whole Church being ſo ſtated, as to preſuppoſe the whole condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of our Salvation: and to extend only, to the determining of thoſe things, which
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:54672:19"/> may promote edification in it, without endangering the Unity of the Church; why ſhould not I think, that there is found, by the conſent of the whole Church from the beginning, ſo clear a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution of all that is diſputed, to maintain <hi>Separation,</hi> concerning the Condition of the Covenant of Grace, that it cannot be refuſed by the Parties, owning the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Faith? There is great cauſe to fear, that, notwithſtanding the miſchiefs we feel by our own <hi>Diviſions,</hi> ſome would think it ſtill a greater miſchief, that the Whole Church ſhould be re-united; Though upon juſt Terms, and ſuch, as muſt needs re-unite our ſelves. But, if the Chriſtian Religion oblige us to do men good againſt their will; He that demands nothing, but the <hi>Right <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding</hi> of two Articles in the Creed, to the Re-uniting of Chriſtendom, intends the greateſt Charity, that thoſe who love Diviſion can receive. Whether his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand be ſufficient to do his Work or no; he muſt leave it to the World to judge. For, it is to be acknowledged, that, when the Condition of our Salvation is ſetled, and all that cauſes Diviſion upon the Account of it; there remains, beſides,
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:54672:20"/> very many Diſputes, concerning <hi>Publick Orders,</hi> as well in the <hi>Offices of the Church,</hi> as in the publick <hi>Government</hi> of it; and the Intereſt, as well of the State as of the Church, in the ſame. But, let not therefore thoſe that love not Unity pretend Difficulty. For, they ſhall find ſuch <hi>Principles</hi> laid, to the determining of them all, in the <hi>Viſible Laws</hi> of that <hi>one Church,</hi> which cannot continue <hi>One,</hi> but by owning the ſame; that the due bounds of Reformation cannot eſcape them, that will not decline the thred and the grain of theſe grounds. And yet, in all this, no man declines the Scripture for the <hi>only Rule of Faith.</hi> But, he that refuſes the See of <hi>Rome</hi> for <hi>Judge in the Senſe of it;</hi> which is all that remains in queſtion; may well crave leave to decline the Judgment of any <hi>private Spirit,</hi> not confined within the bounds, which the Viſible conſent of the Church determineth. Not as if the ſenſe of the Scripture were not more and more to be diſcovered; which is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed diſcovered every day more and more. But, becauſe the true ſenſe of it will always fall within the compaſs of that, which the Church hath always re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived. I am very well perſwaded, that
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:54672:20"/> the See of <hi>Rome</hi> will never hear of any Terms of Reconcilement, ſo long as they ſee our Diviſions increaſe. But I am very well aſſured, that the <hi>Diviſions of the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation</hi> can never be <hi>Re-united,</hi> ſo as to prevent the like for the future; but upon that Ground, which, being received, will ſerve to re-unite the Whole Church. There can never be <hi>One Viſible Faith, One Viſible Church,</hi> upon any other terms. There can be no ſuch <hi>ſin</hi> as <hi>Hereſie</hi> to vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late Faith, as <hi>Schiſm</hi> to violate Charity, upon other terms. And therefore, it is out of Love to the Reformation, that I in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt upon ſuch a <hi>Principle,</hi> as may ſerve to re-unite us with the Church of <hi>Rome;</hi> Being well aſſured, that we can never be well re-united with our ſelves otherwiſe, That, not only the <hi>Reformation,</hi> but the <hi>Common Chriſtianity</hi> muſt needs be loſt, in the <hi>Diviſions,</hi> which will never have an end otherwiſe. And he that can take meaſure, how much of it is loſt in thirty years time, ſince theſe Troubles began; even among them that incloſe the Name of <hi>Saints,</hi> and <hi>the Godly</hi> to themſelves; will eaſily believe, that it hath not long to live, unleſs Diviſion be put to death. And yet the vain hopes of the Parties,
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:54672:21"/> ever ſince the Diviſion, may make it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear, that both have Reaſon enough to be reconciled. They of the See of <hi>Rome</hi> have long expected; a hundred and fifty years or thereabouts; that thoſe Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Princes, that have looked upon the Reformation as dangerous to the Peace of their Dominions, ſhould give them aſſiſtance, to reduce all that <hi>Proteſt</hi> againſt the abuſes thereof, by force of Arms, to ſubmit to their Will. Which would be, to make that Will the Law of Religion, as well to themſelves, as to thoſe that ſhould be ſo reduced. But the experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of ſo much time evidences, that the Powers of Chriſtendom have ſomething elſe to do, then to imploy the forces of their Dominions to that purpoſe: And that, if it prove for the Intereſt of ſome of them, at ſome times, it will prove not to be for the Intereſt of others, at the ſame or other times. Of which Intereſt, as they are indeed, and in <hi>Conſcience,</hi> to give account to God, and not to the See of <hi>Rome;</hi> ſo, that they will ever make the See of <hi>Rome</hi> the Judge of them, what ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance can there be? So, it is time of the day for them to hearken to Reaſon, whether they regard God, and Religion, or
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:54672:21"/> Intereſt, and themſelves. But is not our Caſe the ſame? Or, are not we tranſpor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted as far, with the conceit that they are <hi>limbs of Antichriſt</hi> and <hi>Idolaters,</hi> as they are, with the conceit, that we are <hi>Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks</hi> and <hi>Schiſmaticks?</hi> Have we not as long expected, when the <hi>Kings</hi> would joyn to ſtrip the <hi>Whore of Babylon naked,</hi> as they, when they would joyn to reduce the Hereticks by force? And is it not yet time of the day for us; whatſoever opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, thoſe that imploy their time, in ſearching the meaning of a Propheſie, may have; at leaſt to make it no <hi>Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of our Profeſſion,</hi> nor to maintain <hi>Sepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration</hi> upon the Account of it? Knowing, that were the Pope twenty times Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt, and the Papiſts Idolaters, he can ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver be Antichriſt, nor they Idolaters, for any thing, that the conſent of the Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Church either alloweth, or injoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth. So, that, whatever become of any Propheſie in Gods Word, and the ſenſe of it, the bounds of Reformation will be the very ſame; And he will be no leſs an <hi>Heretick or a Schiſmatick,</hi> that makes the Pope Antichriſt, or the Papiſts Idolaters, for doing or believing any thing, which the Church from the beginning hath in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyned
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:54672:22"/> or allowed, to be believed or to be done, then if he pretended no Propheſie to prove it. If ever any people had cauſe to reflect upon the ſad conſequences of this conceit, we are they, that ſhall find no probable reaſon, to impute the miſchiefs of the late <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſurpation</hi> to, but the hope of fulfilling this ſenſe of this Propheſie. It is a vain thing to think, that a man, who believed no God, could Act a counterfei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Religion throughout, as we have ſeen the Uſurper do. He that could hope to be ſaved, either without Faith, or with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out good Works, by having Chriſt alive at the Heart, why ſhould not he think, that all the foul way he went through was the Service of God, having intended to <hi>ſtrip the Whore of Babylon</hi> by his means? Neither <hi>Manichaeus,</hi> nor <hi>Mahomet,</hi> nor any <hi>Enthuſiaſt</hi> can be barred, of the like aim with this, if once he make his <hi>private Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit</hi> parallel to the Scripture. For, that which the ſame Authority <hi>laſt</hi> dictates, as in <hi>Wills</hi> and <hi>Teſtaments,</hi> muſt take place. I ſay not that this is the Caſe of thoſe, that interpret this Propheſie of the See of <hi>Rome.</hi> I believe they follow their Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, in expounding <hi>Scripture by Scripture.</hi> But if their Reaſon be not the Reaſon of
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:54672:22"/> 
                  <hi>Religion,</hi> the Reaſon of that <hi>Chriſtianity</hi> which we all have Intereſt in, the private Spirit that follows it may take all for Gods Service, though never ſo wicked, that is done in proſecution of it. In the mean time, Diviſion increaſing among us as it does, I think, I gratifie our ſelves, and not the See of <hi>Rome,</hi> in propoſing that truth, which reconciles the <hi>Intereſt of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation,</hi> to the <hi>Intereſt of <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity</hi> in the Church. For in <hi>Civil War;</hi> as Schiſm is nothing but a Civil War in the Church; that Party that divides is the likely to Ruine. And though the firſt hopes of the See of <hi>Rome</hi> have proved addle, yet if our Diviſions prevail, they muſt needs have freſh hopes to prevail, by our Divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. VIII. That it is the Duty of this Kingdom, and of all Chriſtian Soveraignties.</head>
               <p>ANd therefore, I muſt freely profeſs my opinion, without any manner of hope, that ever the See of <hi>Rome</hi> will abate any thing of their rigour; Though the
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:54672:23"/> Reformation ſhould content themſelves with theſe terms. For, I find, by the proceeding of former times, that it is their <hi>Maxime,</hi> to ſtand to that which they have once done: And to mark thoſe Popes to poſterity, that have abated any thing, from the rigour of their Predeceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors. For, being arrived at this Great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, by this <hi>Rigour</hi> and obſtinacy in all Pretenſes, right or wrong, they will al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways think themſelves obliged, in <hi>Reaſon of State,</hi> not to yield ſo much as the <hi>Cup in the Euchariſt;</hi> Though the Council of <hi>Trent</hi> leave it in the Popes Power to grant it. Becauſe, granting, that any thing is and hath been amiſs; who ſhall ſecure them, that nothing more ſhall be queſtioned, then is indeed amiſs; when we ſee no point in Religion remain unque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtioned, ſome time or ſome where? Not conſidering, all the While, that this Rigor is the cauſe of <hi>Diviſion,</hi> and Diviſion the cauſe of theſe Queſtions: And that, the Reaſon of Reformation being owned on both ſides, there is a <hi>Ground</hi> reſtored, for <hi>Confidence,</hi> that they who accept of it will ſtand to thoſe <hi>Bounds</hi> which it ſetleth. But, if the See of <hi>Rome</hi> can have no Power againſt the Whole Church; Much leſs
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:54672:23"/> can any other Church, or any part of the Church, or any Secular Power that pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tecteth it, make that to be Reformation, which the Whole Church alloweth not; Or ſecure their <hi>Subjects Conſciences</hi> of the <hi>Salvation</hi> they ſeek, in exerciſing their Chriſtianity according to their Laws, but by confining the Reformation which they maintain, within thoſe Bounds, which the Faith and the Laws of the Whole Church either require or allow. Now, how can the <hi>Intereſt of the Nation</hi> be ſecured, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out due ground, for hope of Gods bleſſing upon that which ſhall be done? How can there be ground to expect Gods bleſſing, till it appear, how all Subjects of this Kingdom ſhall ſtand diſcharged at the day of Judgment, following that form which the <hi>Kingdom inacteth,</hi> rather then that which the <hi>See of Rome requireth?</hi> For, there are other Chriſtian Princes and So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veraignties, that command their Subjects to obey the See of <hi>Rome;</hi> whoſe Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects muſt as well ſtand diſcharged to God, upon the ſame Plea, as the Subjects of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed Princes and States. And how ſhall the <hi>Conſciences of them that make Laws</hi> be ſecured, if they cannot ſecure the Conſciences of them for whom they
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:54672:24"/> are made? Or how can Gods bleſſing be expected, if this ſecurity cannot be <hi>evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denced?</hi> It is not yet time to aſk, how, thoſe that allow not the Reformation, up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on theſe Terms, ſhould be puniſhed; Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe there are that pretend, that no pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment can be inflicted, for diſobeying any Law of the Kingdom, by which Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion is ſetled. But it is time to ſay, that they make it a very ridiculous thing, for the Legiſlative Power to make Laws for the Kingdom, which they can inact by no Penalty. And how ſhall this difficulty be voided, but by demanding nothing, but that which Chriſtianity will require of all Chriſtians? That no Chriſtian King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom can have Power, to introduce any thing, for Reformation in the Church, but that which the <hi>Conſent of the Whole Church</hi> either injoyneth, or alloweth. Not as if the leaſt Tittle of Scripture were not enough, to warrant, that which it injoyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth to be the Reformation of the Church. But, whereas the <hi>ſenſe of the Scripture</hi> is that which remains queſtionable, not the <hi>Authority</hi> of it; that nothing can be the true ſenſe of the Scripture, which the Conſent of the Whole Church contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicteth. And therefore, that, though
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:54672:24"/> there be an appearance of truth in ſuch a ſenſe, yet, it is not for a <hi>Chriſtian Kingdom</hi> to inact it for <hi>Law,</hi> till it be duely deba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted. And, that being done, it will infal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>libly appear in all, which in moſt things appeareth already; that the Conſent of the Whole Church cannot contradict the true ſenſe of the Scripture; And that it is nothing elſe, but not knowing the one or the other, that makes it ſeem other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe. If the Scripture it ſelf is not, nor can be <hi>owned for Gods Word,</hi> but by the Conſent of Gods people, from the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, atteſting, the <hi>Motives of Faith</hi> related in the Scripture to have been infallibly done, by ſubmitting to the Faith which they inforce; Then muſt the ſame Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent be of force, to aſſure common reaſon, that the Faith, and the Laws, wherein the whole Church agrees, came from the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority ſetled by God, not by any <hi>Conſent of all Chriſtians,</hi> to fall from that which they Profeſs. And therefore, though a Kingdom may force the Subjects thereof, to <hi>call that Reformation,</hi> which they inact; yet they can never make it Reformation, in that ſenſe, which the Salvation of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians requires, if it be not within theſe bounds. It may be called Reformation,
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:54672:25"/> to ſignifie a <hi>New form,</hi> but it can never be Reformation, to ſignifie that form <hi>which ſhould be,</hi> unleſs it ſignifie the form that hath been in Gods Church. For, that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>One</hi> and the ſame, from the firſt to the ſecond Coming of Chriſt, can authorize no other form, then that which it may ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear to have had from the beginning.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. IX. That it cannot be done without the Synods of this Church.</head>
               <p>ANd therefore, it being granted on both ſides, that the Soveraign Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of Chriſtian Kingdoms and States, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding duely, obligeth the Subjects, to ſubmit to the Reformation of the Church; and cannot exact <hi>Legal Penalties</hi> of them which refuſe, upon any other Terms; I do except, in the ſecond place, that it ought to proceed in all Reformation, by and upon the Authority of this Church; That is, of the Synods. For what doth the <hi>whole Church agree in ſo Viſibly,</hi> as in this; That the Authority which God hath inſtituted in his Church ſhould give Laws
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:54672:25"/> to his Church? And how can a Chriſtian Kingdom promiſe themſelves Gods bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing, upon ſuch Acts, as they have no Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er nor Right from God to do? For, granting there is ſuch a thing as a Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Church; it is not poſſible, that any Chriſtian Kingdom, which muſt be a part of it, ſhould have Power to inact any thing <hi>Prejudicial,</hi> much leſs deſtructive to the Whole; to the Viſible Being, which is, the Viſible Communion of it. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, the Faith and the Laws of the whole being the Condition, under which the parts are to communicate; no Chriſtian Kingdom can have Power from God, to give <hi>New Laws in Religion,</hi> to the Subjects thereof, which the Church of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom warranteth not, to be according to the Laws of the whole Church. If any thing may appear to have been in force, in the Primitive Church, and, by the abuſe of ſucceeding times, to have become void; I do not deny, that the Secular Power may Reform the Church, by re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoring it, though the Church ſhould <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſe their Conſent</hi> to it. The reaſon is, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the Church would be without help, if there were no Lawful way to reſtore the decays of it; Which, we agree, have
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:54672:26"/> come to paſs; without the conſent of them that are chargeable for the decay of it. Now, the Faith and the Laws of the Catholick Church are the Birth-right of all Chriſtians; Purchaſed, by underta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king to Profeſs one Catholick Church, at their Baptiſm: And Chriſtian Powers are to protect their Chriſtian Subjects in their Birth-right. And, the Authority of the preſent Church is not ſeen, in the Faith and the Laws of the Whole Church. For, it is meer matter of Fact, what they are; The evidence whereof (praeexi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtent to the Authority of the preſent Church) cannot be underſtood to require, or to preſuppoſe it. And therefore, the Authority of the Church cannot be vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated, by reducing the Faith and the Laws of the Primitive Church into force. Nevertheleſs, in regard, that which is decayed can ſeldom be reſtored, without determining new Bounds, which the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent ſtate of the Church requires; It is manifeſtly the Office of the Church, to determine the ſame: Nor can it be done by Chriſtian Powers of this World, without aſſuming to themſelves that Authority, in which they are to maintain the Church. For, though Soveraign Power hath Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raign
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:54672:26"/> Right, <hi>in all Cauſes and over all Perſons Eccleſiaſtical,</hi> yet is it capable of no Eccleſiaſtical Power, or Right; But is to maintain thoſe that have it, by the Laws of the Church, in the uſe of it. If any thing were done at the Reformation, ſetting aſide the Synods of this Church; which, I am here neither to deny, nor to acknowledge; it muſt be juſtified upon this Account, that they refuſed the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority of the Whole Church, in autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rizing the Reformation of this Church. If any thing now may appear to be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded upon the ſame Account; let the Authority of the Synods be paſſed by, for their puniſhment, if they hinder the Reformation of the Church, by refuſing it. But that cannot appear, till it may appear; Firſt, that the matter demanded ought to have <hi>the force of Law</hi> in the Church; having been of force, and ſince decayed, by the injury of time, or cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption of men: Secondly, that it is of ſuch <hi>weight,</hi> that <hi>Religion</hi> is like to have more advantage, by reſtoring it, then the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity of the Church</hi> ſhall ſuffer, by viola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the Regular Authority of the Church. What thanks I ſhall have of my LL. the Biſhops for this, I know not; For I deny,
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:54672:27"/> that they themſelves can have any Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity in the Caſe, that ſhall not be confined within the ſame bounds. But it is not poſſible, for him that is the moſt jealous of the Rights of the Crown, in Church-mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, to ſay, what danger there can be to this Crown, in ſecuring the Conſcience of the Kingdom, by the Authority of the Church. For, the acknowledging of thoſe <hi>Bounds,</hi> which the Authority of the Church is confined to, as well in reſpect of <hi>Soveraign Power,</hi> in the Dominions whereof it ſubſiſteth, as of the <hi>reſt of the Church;</hi> leaveth no Plea for it to <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſurp,</hi> either upon the Crown, or upon the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Subjects of it. And all this I claim by <hi>S. Paul,</hi> where he commandeth all Chriſtians, to <hi>abide in that ſtate</hi> in which they are called to be Chriſtians. Which cannot otherwiſe oblige all <hi>Clergie-men,</hi> to be <hi>Subjects,</hi> upon the ſame terms, as they ſhould be, if their Soveraigns were not Chriſtians; but, that it muſt oblige all <hi>Publick Powers,</hi> to maintain the Clergy in the ſame Rights, which they had, and muſt have had over Chriſtian People, did not the Publick Powers profeſs the Faith. And therefore, though I do claim, that the Synods of the two Provinces, and
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:54672:27"/> their Decrees, ought to be confined within the bounds ſo oft ſaid; yet I do demand of <hi>All,</hi> (eſpecially of thoſe that may have made the <hi>Oath of Canonical Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience,</hi> to their Biſhops) how they can profeſs to owne Epiſcopacy; eſpecially according to their Oath; that paſs over this <hi>Right of the Synods.</hi> For, that which is done <hi>without, or againſt</hi> their Conſent, ſhall make them no Biſhops; That muſt receive Law from their Clergy, if the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular Power make their ſenſe of the Scripture Law to the Kingdom. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as I, that take the liberty to prove all this, <hi>without their Authority,</hi> can clearly Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs, that I think it a point not <hi>ſubject to Canonical Authority,</hi> which I plead for; And that otherwiſe, I ſhould think it in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſiſtent with the Oath of Canonical Obedience which I have made.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="chapter">
               <pb n="48" facs="tcp:54672:28"/>
               <head>CHAP. X. The Caſe in which S. <hi>Paul</hi> forbears the Weak.</head>
               <p>COme we now to that Scripture of S. <hi>Paul</hi> to the <hi>Romans,</hi> upon which, the whole Plea for <hi>tender Conſciences</hi> is grounded, and to <hi>ſtate the Caſe,</hi> in which he preſcribeth. And ſee, what <hi>forbearance</hi> it will inforce in our Caſe. S. <hi>Paul,</hi> having ſhewed the <hi>Romans;</hi> who, before they were converted to be Chriſtians, had been, ſome Jews, ſome Gentiles; that Righteouſneſs and Salvation comes only by Faith, or by Chriſtianity, and not by the Law, or by Judaiſm alſo; proceedeth in the fourteenth Chapter of that Epiſtle, to Order them, <hi>to forbear one another;</hi> The Jews not to cenſure the Gentiles, for not obſerving the Law; The Gentiles not to ſcorn the Jews; if, not underſtanding the freedom of Chriſtians, they lived as Jews, in all or in ſome things. It is mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt, who are the <hi>ſtrong</hi> and who are the <hi>weak,</hi> with S. <hi>Paul,</hi> in that he is one of the ſtrong, where he ſays, XV. 1. <hi>We that
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:54672:28"/> are ſtrong ought to bear the infirmities of the weak.</hi> They that underſtand, how Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs and Salvation comes only by <hi>Faith;</hi> notwithſtanding that it was to be had under the Law, as well as afore the Law; theſe are the <hi>ſtrong. One man be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieves he may eat any thing;</hi> though for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidden by the Law; <hi>but he that is weak,</hi> and ſees nothing elſe on the Table but that which the Law forbids, <hi>eats herbs. One man makes difference of a day above a day,</hi> according to the Law, <hi>another eſteems every day alike,</hi> XIV. 2, 5. Theſe two inſtances are put for all indifferent things, preſcribed or forbidden by the Law. He that underſtood the purpoſe of God in giving the Law, which he intended to make <hi>void,</hi> or rather to <hi>fulfil,</hi> in due time; So that Salvation came not <hi>by it,</hi> when it was to be had <hi>under it;</hi> He is the <hi>ſtrong</hi> with S. <hi>Paul.</hi> He that underſtood it not, and yet continued a Chriſtian, that he might come to underſtand it, <hi>the weak.</hi> Let no man marvel, that the <hi>Romans,</hi> who took S. <hi>Paul</hi> for an Apoſtle, ſhould not underſtand that which S. <hi>Paul</hi> had pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, by this whole Epiſtle. For he pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth it by the <hi>Myſtical ſenſe of the Old Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtament;</hi> Which, they who had ſubmit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:54672:29"/> to the Faith could not owne, never<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſs, until they underſtood the reaſon, why God gave the Law, with an intent to bring in the Goſpel by it. Let no man think, that they were not fit to be bapti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed, (for ſuch were they all to whom S. <hi>Paul</hi> writes) that underſtood not this, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longing to the Foundation of Faith. Baptiſm maketh all <hi>Diſciples</hi> of Chriſt, and therefore findeth them not ſo. It is neceſſary, that he who is baptized ſhould undertake all that, which, he ſhall come to learn, that Chriſt hath taught. It is not neceſſary that he ſhould know what it is; knowing that Salvation is not to be had, without doing all that, whatſoever it is, which, it ſhall appear, that Chriſt hath taught.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. XI. Compared with his Orders at <hi>Corinth,</hi> and elſewhere.</head>
               <p>BUt, ſeeing S. <hi>Paul</hi> forbiddeth the <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rinthians</hi> to <hi>ſcandalize the weak,</hi> in eating meats that had been ſacrificed to Idols; we muſt not ſtate the Caſe of the
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:54672:29"/> 
                  <hi>Romans,</hi> without conſidering, how the Caſe of the <hi>Corinthians</hi> may concern it. Here S. <hi>Paul diſtinguiſhes ſcholaſtically;</hi> that ſuch meats might be eaten, either <hi>as Gods Creatures, materially,</hi> or <hi>formally,</hi> as meats ſacrificed to Idols; which Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters feaſted upon, after their Sacrifices, in honour of their Idols; as we ſee by his words, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> X. 7. <hi>Nor be ye Idolaters, as ſome of them were; As it is written; The people ſate down to eat and drink, and roſe up to play.</hi> And Dan. V. 4. <hi>They drunk wine, and praiſed the Gods of gold and ſil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, of braſs, of iron, of wood and of ſtone.</hi> S. <hi>Paul</hi> then reſolveth, that Chriſtians may eat meats ſacrificed to Idols, as Gods creatures; and that they cannot be pollu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, by being ſacrificed to Idols, which are <hi>nothing.</hi> But that, when there may be occaſion for Chriſtians to think, that a Chriſtian eats them as Idolaters did; (as eating them <hi>in an Idol-Temple,</hi> or, <hi>being invited</hi> home <hi>by an Idolater)</hi> in ſuch Caſes, it was neceſſary to forbear, for Chriſtian Charities ſake; leaſt a weak Chriſtian, ſeeing a ſtrong Chriſtian eat them, ſhould think he eat them as Idolaters did; and, doing ſo himſelf, ſhould fall into <hi>miſpri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of Idolatry,</hi> 1 Cor. VIII. 7, 10. X. 27,
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:54672:30"/> 28. And by this example we may gather, by the way, what S. <hi>Paul</hi> means, <hi>Rom.</hi> XIV. 15, 20. <hi>Deſtroy not him with thy meat, for whom Chriſt dyed. For meat de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy not the work of God.</hi> He means, that the danger was no leſs, (if the Gentiles ſhould not forbear the Jews, but deſpiſe their weakneſs, that could not ſee them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves free of the Law) then, that they ſhould fall into diſlike with the Faith, and return to the Jews Religion again. So, the danger at <hi>Corinth</hi> was <hi>Idolatry;</hi> at <hi>Rome Apoſtaſie.</hi> S. <hi>Paul</hi> then, forbids the <hi>Corinthians,</hi> to <hi>make inquiry for con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience ſake,</hi> 1 Cor. X. 25. whether that which is ſold in the ſhambles had been ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crificed to an Idol or not. But <hi>Daniel</hi> did make inquiry <hi>for conſcience ſake,</hi> when he reſolved, <hi>not to be polluted with the Kings meat,</hi> Dan. I. 5, 8. taking all of it to be <hi>dedicated</hi> to Idols, in the <hi>firſt-fruits</hi> of it. For this, being the cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtom of the Heathen, made all their meats ſuſpicious, as dedicated to their Idols. <hi>Tobit</hi> is not <hi>Canonical Scripture;</hi> But it is as Old as the Old Teſtament in Greek. The Author of it relates, for his commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation, that he <hi>kept himſelf from eating the bread of the Gentiles, when his Brethren and
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:54672:30"/> kindred did eat of it.</hi> Tobit I. 10, 11, 12. <hi>becauſe he remembred God with all his heart.</hi> This ſignifies, that the more Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious did obſerve it, though not com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded by the Law. It ſeems they were only forbidden by the Law to go to the feaſts which they, the Gentiles, made of their Sacrifices; leſt they ſhould wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip their Gods, as they that invited them did, <hi>Exod.</hi> XXXIII. 15. and as they did with the Madianites, <hi>Numb.</hi> XXV. 2. The forbearing of Idolaters meat, was <hi>a hedge to the Law,</hi> that they might be the further off from tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſing it; But brought in under the <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets,</hi> and obſerved by the <hi>more Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous.</hi> And the Jews have reaſon, when they tell us, that, <hi>Nehemiah</hi> was diſpenſed with, <hi>for drinking the wine of the Gentiles, becauſe he was Cup-bearer to the King.</hi> Whereby it appears, that S. <hi>Paul</hi> leaves it to the Charity of every Chriſtian, to uſe his freedom ſo ſparingly, as not to offend a <hi>weak Chriſtian.</hi> But, under the Law, it became a <hi>Rule,</hi> that all the ſtrong ſhould forbear that, which might poſſibly offend the weak. And therefore, when the Apoſtles at <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> injoyn thoſe that were converted of Gentiles, to <hi>abſtain
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:54672:31"/> from meats ſacrificed to Idols;</hi> they do forbid them to eat ſuch meats, even <hi>mate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rially:</hi> And command them to make <hi>inqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry for conſcience ſake,</hi> as the Jews uſed to do, and as converted Gentiles did in the Land of Promiſe. For the Ordinance of <hi>Acts</hi> XV. 23. addreſſeth only to the Churches of <hi>Judaea,</hi> and to thoſe, which <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Barnabas,</hi> being ſent from <hi>Antio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chia,</hi> had founded in <hi>Cilicia,</hi> and the parts adjacent, <hi>Acts</hi> XIII. 2, 3, 14—XIV. 26. XV. XIV. 4. The reaſon of this diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence is manifeſt, by the words of S. <hi>Paul,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> XII. 2. <hi>Ye know ye were Gentiles, carried after theſe dumb Idols, as ye were led.</hi> Whereas <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Barnabas</hi> addreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed firſt to the Jews, and founded Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches of them, for the greateſt part. So that, the hopes of winning the Jews re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maining, the <hi>diſpenſation</hi> was to take place. But the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> conſiſted of Gentiles, as well as of Jews; whereas, in the Church of <hi>Corinth,</hi> there is no ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count at all had of the Jews. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, the forbearance required at <hi>Corinth</hi> is out of fear of <hi>Idolatry;</hi> at <hi>Rome,</hi> of <hi>Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaſie.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="chapter">
               <pb n="55" facs="tcp:54672:31"/>
               <head>CHAP. XII. The preſent Caſe of this time ſtated.</head>
               <p>HAving thus ſtated the Caſe, in which S. <hi>Paul</hi> ordereth this forbearance, let us ſtate our Caſe, in which it is deman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, by conſequence. But that cannot be done, but out of the premiſes. We muſt ſuppoſe, the Church of <hi>England,</hi> a member of the <hi>whole Church,</hi> deſires to Reform it ſelf, becauſe the reſt of the Church will not joyn in the ſame work; But deſires to continue a member of the whole Church, and not to give any cauſe of interrupting Unity, by improving Chriſtianity. I know, ſome of them that demand <hi>Toleration</hi> do not allow <hi>any ſuch thing, as a Church of England,</hi> when they are underſtood. For, how ſhould they owne any Right of Soveraign Powers, to give Law to the Church of their Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minions, that allow them no Right, to puniſh the tranſgreſſion of ſuch Laws? But the Caſe muſt be ſtated upon the Terms propoſed, nevertheleſs, as to thoſe that acknowledge National Churches;
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:54672:32"/> Excepting for thoſe that make this Plea, when we ſee time. This only, I think, would be ſaid, that the Church of <hi>England</hi> is not now to be Reformed; but, having been Reformed, is now queſtioned, as if the Reformation of it were not yet per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect; And therefore the boldneſs is ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, by a private perſon of my condition, to give an Opinion, what is moſt wanting in the Reformation of it. Becauſe it cannot be ſaid, what is unduely demand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, until it may be ſaid, what is due to be done. But it muſt be remembred, that the demand is made in behalf of thoſe, that had made a <hi>Schiſm</hi> in the Church of <hi>England,</hi> by <hi>Ordaining or being Ordained</hi> Presbyters by Presbyters, without and againſt the will of their Biſhops. In be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>half of thoſe it hath been demanded, that their Ordinations may ſtand valid and good, and the perſons inabled, by the Law of the Land, to miniſter the Offices of their Orders, and to be truſted with the Cure of Souls, by their Biſhops. And not only ſo, but it hath been further de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded, that ſome of thoſe Laws, by which Religion is ſetled in the Kingdom, be repealed, for their ſakes; That they may have no pretenſe to ſcruple the Office
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:54672:32"/> of the Miniſtry. Not that it is now ſaid, (as for this hundred years it hath been ſaid) that the Laws which they would have repealed are againſt Gods Law; And that therefore they cannot yield them obedience. But that the <hi>Miniſters,</hi> or <hi>People</hi> that will follow them, have a doubt in Conſcience, which they cannot be cleared of, that it is not <hi>Lawful</hi> for them to yield them obedience; and that they cannot do it without ſinning, and incurring damnation, by doing againſt their Conſciences. And this is alſo the Caſe, in which, thoſe that acknowledge <hi>no Church of England,</hi> no Right in Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Powers, to give Law to the Church within their own Dominions, do demand liberty to ſeparate from the Church, into their private Conventicles. Proteſting, that they cannot hold Communion with the Church ſetled by the Laws of the Land; No not though Reformed to the content of thoſe hitherto mentioned. And pretending the ſame reaſon from S. <hi>Paul,</hi> that they ſhould incur ſin and dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, doing it in that doubt, which they cannot be cleared of.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="chapter">
               <pb n="58" facs="tcp:54672:33"/>
               <head>CHAP. XIII. The Miſtake which cauſeth Weakneſs in our Caſe.</head>
               <p>THe Caſe thus ſtated, I muſt, in the firſt place, aſk both Parties, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they do think in their Conſciences, that S. <hi>Paul</hi> had not ſhewed the Jews at <hi>Rome,</hi> that were become Chriſtians, ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient reaſon, to clear them of the doubts they had, concerning their obligation to the Law of <hi>Moſes;</hi> that they were indeed free of it, and ought to be free of thoſe doubts. I ſuppoſe they will think it fit to ſay, that, though S. <hi>Paul</hi> injoyn them to <hi>forbear</hi> one another, ſo long as they did not underſtand their freedom; yet, that they might underſtand it, and were bound to underſtand it. For, is there any man ſo little a Chriſtian; now that the time of <hi>forbearance</hi> is paſt, that there is no more hope to gain the Jews, by compliance, without making our ſelves Jews; as to make a queſtion of offending a Jew, by not abating the Profeſſion of his Chriſtianity? The conſequence
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:54672:33"/> whereof is all that I demand. If S. <hi>Paul</hi> would have the Jews forborn, that the provocation, which they might meet with, might not move them to diſlike their Chriſtianity; certainly he held them to be under a light, which obliged them not to diſlike it. Otherwiſe he ſhould not have done the work which he pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tends to do by this Epiſtle; to ſhew the Law to be void, becauſe Salvation comes <hi>only by Faith.</hi> And certainly, there can be nothing more opprobrious to Chriſtia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, then that which is pleaded, for abatement in the preſent Laws; That the weak are not under a light, inabling them to ſee thoſe things to be lawful, which indeed, and to the ſtrong, may be lawful, and appear ſuch. For how could this doubt be cleared, if a weak Conſcience ſhould be pretended, when the queſtion is, whether to turn Chriſtian or not? Is it poſſible, that there ſhould be ſuch a doubt in that point, that a man, to whom the Reaſon why he ought to be a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian is <hi>ſufficiently propoſed,</hi> can be ſaid to be under a light, that convinceth him not? Which if it be true, then is there nothing in Chriſtianity, which there is not a ſufficient light, to convict that man
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:54672:34"/> of, to whoſe <hi>Office</hi> it belongs. Other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, it could not being to his <hi>Office;</hi> not being able to diſcern the <hi>Obligation</hi> of it. It is therefore a horrible reproach to Chriſtianity, to ſay, that any <hi>doubting Conſcience</hi> is not under a light, ſufficient to reſolve it. <hi>Scruples</hi> of Conſcience there may be, which may eternally have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe; and that no diſparagement to the Faith; Becauſe the Faith provides a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution, that they who have ſcruples in Conſcience, are bound in Conſcience to lay them aſide; Nay to act poſitively againſt them. But he that ſays, that, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a Chriſtian, he is not under a light ſufficient to clear him, in any <hi>doubt</hi> of Conſcience, ſays, that the Faith obligeth him to ſin; Whereas it is not the Faith, but the want of it, which, obligeth not the erring Conſcience to ſin, but intang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth him ſo, that he muſt ſin, if the <hi>obliga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of acting</hi> fall out before the errour be removed. Suppoſe the Jews convict by the Epiſtle to the <hi>Romans,</hi> that Salvation comes only by Faith, and not by the Law alſo; And you ſuppoſe them under a light, that, neither the Law, nor any Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance, then ſtanding by virtue of the Law, could oblige. But, ſuppoſe them
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:54672:34" rendition="simple:additions"/> 
                  <hi>in love with themſelves,</hi> and with their <hi>Anceſtors,</hi> and to have ſuch an Opinion of Salvation <hi>intailed upon them and their iſſue,</hi> by the Law, as to think, that they could not have it by God that gave the Law, if the Gentiles might have it as well as themſelves; and they might <hi>(very well,</hi> for conſequence of Reaſon, though <hi>very ill,</hi> for their own account) overſee the light they were under. Suppoſe we now, thoſe that make this Plea, not to believe <hi>one Catholick Church,</hi> and <hi>one Baptiſm for the remiſſion of ſins;</hi> But had rather <hi>grati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie the Socinians,</hi> and deny that any Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian can be obliged, to any thing that ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears not to his <hi>own Reaſon, out of Canoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Scripture;</hi> Then imagine he ſhould <hi>gratifie the Papiſt,</hi> if he ſhould grant, that Catholick Communion always made the Catholick Church; Suppoſe them not to believe, that the Faith which only ſaveth includeth Baptiſm in the Catholick Church; And that this Church is not <hi>Reformed,</hi> unleſs it be reſtored to the ſame form; I ſay ſuppoſing them poſſeſt with ſuch prejudices as theſe, and marvel not, to ſee them <hi>eternally doubting,</hi> whether or no, it be lawful for them, to obey the Laws, which this Church and Kingdom is
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:54672:35"/> able to make. Nay, to ſee them break out into <hi>Schiſm,</hi> as all Parties now ſeem to do, rather then obey them, when they ſhall be out of hope, to give their own Law to the Kingdom; Never fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſting, how it may appear to continue a Church, when they have given ſuch Laws to it.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="14" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. XIV. That it is not <hi>Forbearance</hi> to allow their Orders.</head>
               <p>I Suppoſe, they who make this Plea, will not grant, that they are in any er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour ſo <hi>near the Foundation,</hi> as theſe which I name. Nor do I think, that thoſe Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Jews at <hi>Rome,</hi> that doubted of tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſing the Law, when they knew that Salvation comes only by Faith, did <hi>deny the Foundation of Faith.</hi> For, as long as they lived in the Church, they were in the way to learn, and underſtand, how both were true. Neither will I ſay, that any of thoſe, who deſire <hi>Forbearance</hi> for the <hi>weak,</hi> are in any errour deſtructive to the Foundation of Faith, and the hope of Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation,
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:54672:35" rendition="simple:additions"/> till they break out into Conven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles. When that is done, I am thence<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forth bound to charge them with all the Error, which the <hi>Title of their Schiſm</hi> can ſignifie. And therefore I charge them with <hi>Hypocriſie,</hi> when they pretend to <hi>Forbearance</hi> becauſe they are <hi>weak,</hi> and yet break out into Conventieles. when they do ſo, then they can be counted no more the <hi>weak</hi> among Chriſtians, then thoſe Jews which S. <hi>Paul</hi> will have to be forborn, as the weak among Chriſtians; ſuppoſing them to have renounced the Faith afterwards, rather then continue in the Church. And therefore, the Plea of <hi>weak</hi> Conſciences cannot be allowed thoſe that ingage in Conventicles. They have cut themſelves off from it, by lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving the Church; Let them return, and then make the beſt of it. As to them, the Church is under a new Precept of S. <hi>Paul,</hi> which ſays; <hi>A man that is an He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retick, after the firſt and ſecond admoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion avoid. Knowing that ſuch a one is out of the way, and ſinneth, being condemned by himſelf,</hi> Titus III. 10, 11. Becauſe, ſaith S. <hi>Hierom,</hi> after S. <hi>Cyprian;</hi> Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as other ſinners are put out of the Church, by thoſe that manage the Keys of the
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:54672:36"/> Church; Hereticks and Schiſmaticks put themſelves out of the Church. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>Titus;</hi> that is, all <hi>Titus</hi> his flock; are to <hi>avoid</hi> them for Excommunicate per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, who do <hi>Excommunicate themſelves.</hi> As for thoſe that continue in the Church; though with a pretenſe of giving ſuch Laws to the Church, as no man knows how ſoon they may unchurch it; let them make their beſt of it. But being grounded, at leaſt upon a pretenſe of <hi>weakneſs,</hi> there can be no queſtion made, but ſome errour muſt be granted, for the <hi>ground of this weakneſs.</hi> Let themſelves, at their leiſure, aſſign what errour they will acknowledge, if they like not that which I have aſſigned. Only let them ſhew the world; that is, the Legiſlative Power of this Kingdom; what errour it is, that they have hitherto had, which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing avoided for the future, all thoſe diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culties will ceaſe, which, this Diſcourſe pretendeth, cannot be met with, but by bounding the Reformation within the Faith and the Laws of the Catholick Church. In the mean time, let me go on to ſhew, that thoſe who were Ordained in and for the late Schiſm, (compoſed by the Laws, at his Majeſties Return) by
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:54672:36"/> Preſbyters againſt their Biſhops, cannot claim by virtue of it, to be owned for Preſbyters; Or, in the terms of the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Church, to be <hi>received in their own Orders.</hi> A thing which there can no que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion be made in, by any body that under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtands, what the Church, or what a Schiſm ſignifies. And it is marvel, how, they that would be thought to allow Epiſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacy ſhould queſtion it. To acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge the <hi>Authority of giving Orders in the Biſhops,</hi> according to the Laws, by which we both maintain this Church to be Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed; and yet to allow thoſe that are made Preſbyters by thoſe Biſhops, (not to Ordain others, but to Miniſter the Office of their Order, according to the Reformation ſetled in this Church) I ſay, to allow them to Ordain others, to Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter their Office by other Laws, not only without, but againſt the conſent of the Biſhops, from whom they have their Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, is nothing elſe but to imagine, that God hath given Power to divide (that is, to deſtroy) his Church. For what is <hi>ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting up Altar againſt Altar,</hi> but to Uſurp Power to Conſecrate the Euchariſt, and give the Communion of it, in deſpite of them, whom they allow to have Power to
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:54672:37"/> do the ſame; becauſe they do it by Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity received from themſelves? In all the Records of the Church, there is but one Caſe expreſly remembred, in which it can be ſaid to have been done. That fell out in <hi>Aegypt,</hi> at the time when the Church was divided, between the Arians and the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholicks. But before that trouble, there was another diviſion on foot, about re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving back into the Church, thoſe that had fellen from the Faith, in the perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of <hi>Diocletian.</hi> For <hi>Meletius,</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Lycopolis,</hi> had proceeded to Ordain Biſhops, in as many Cities as he could, in oppoſition to thoſe Biſhops, that ſtuck to the See of <hi>Alexandria.</hi> In theſe diſtracti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, <hi>Coluthus, one of the XII Presbyters of Alexandria,</hi> became the Head of a Party by himſelf; and to propagate his Party, took upon him to make Ordinations of Preſbyters, to Miniſter to thoſe of his Sect. <hi>Aerius</hi> is the man, that maintained the Authority of Biſhops and Preſbyters to be all one. Yet do I not remember, that it is any where ſaid, that <hi>Aerius</hi> took upon him to <hi>Ordain Presbyters,</hi> being him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf one. Much leſs, that he was able to hold up a Sect, by ſuch Ordinations. <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dius</hi> was a Preſbyter, that became the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:54672:37"/> of one of thoſe Sects, that <hi>Epiphanius</hi> writes againſt. But <hi>Epiphanius</hi> ſays ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſly, that he had Biſhops that imbraced his <hi>Opinion,</hi> and propagated his Sect by Ordination. <hi>Tertullian</hi> became the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of a Sect, which continued at <hi>Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thage,</hi> till S. <hi>Auſtines</hi> time; by whom they were reduced to the Church. And truly it is to be preſumed, that the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of the Sect did propagate it, by Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinations made <hi>of his own Head.</hi> For what ſhould he ſtick at, that takes upon him to divide the Church, and to <hi>ſet up Altar againſt Altar?</hi> But I have not found it ſaid, that he did do it. Nor have I found, that any Preſbyter did ever un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertake to do it, but <hi>Coluthus.</hi> At the Council of <hi>Nicaea,</hi> to unite the <hi>Meletians</hi> to the Church, the Biſhops Ordained by him were allowed to ſucceed, when the preſent Biſhops ſhould dye; yet ſo, as to be then lawfully Ordained, though they had been Schiſmatically Ordained afore. But when the <hi>Coluthians</hi> pretended the ſame priviledge, <hi>Athanaſius</hi> pleads for himſelf, that all <hi>Coluthus</hi> his Ordinations were made void. Which is thought to have been done, by that Synod at <hi>Alexan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dria,</hi> which <hi>Hoſius</hi> was preſent at, with
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:54672:38"/> Commiſſion from <hi>Conſtantine.</hi> This is the <hi>only Example</hi> of Preſbyters Ordained by a Preſbyter, without and againſt his Biſhop. All the reſt are meer conjectures, which cannot ſtand, unleſs we ſuppoſe, the Canons of the Church were not obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, becauſe it is not recorded how they were obſerved. Whereas all rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon requires us to ſuppoſe, that they were obſerved, becauſe they might be obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved; and becauſe there followed no diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenſion, upon their not being obſerved. Such Ordinations then, being meer <hi>nulli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties,</hi> as preſumed to be done by them, that never received Authority from the Church to Ordain; do further induce <hi>Irregularity,</hi> by the Canons of the Church. And who can deny, that all reaſon and Conſcience requires it? For, who can believe his Creed, profeſſing one Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Church, and not think the Church more diſobliged <hi>by Schiſm,</hi> then by any other Crime, that renders a man <hi>uncapable</hi> to be promoted to Orders? Certainly, if Rebellion be the Crime, that is hardeſt to be reconciled to Civil truſt, then is Schiſm hardeſt to be reconciled to truſt in the Church. Nevertheleſs, becauſe Unity is to be preferred before Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline;
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:54672:38"/> and becauſe experience ſhews, that, when men are taken off from an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gagement in diviſion, they prove the more truſty, the more weary they were of their ingagement; it hath been often practiſed by the Church, to <hi>receive,</hi> not only <hi>Schiſmaticks,</hi> but even <hi>Hereticks</hi> al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo, (That is, ſuch as had received Orders of thoſe, that parted from the Church, upon an errour in Faith) <hi>in their</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpective <hi>Orders.</hi> But always upon con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition of renouncing the cauſe of their diviſion; Whereupon they were to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive the <hi>Bleſſing of the Church,</hi> by <hi>Prayer with Impoſition of Hands.</hi> The reaſon was, becauſe neither is Baptiſm in Schiſm effectual to Salvation, nor Ordination in Schiſm effectual to Grace, by the Miniſtry of any Office in Schiſm. But, being re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounced, there remains no Cauſe, why their Miniſtry ſhould not be effectual to their people; Their Baptiſm and their Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtry to their own Salvation; ſuppoſing it ſincerely renounced. Therefore the Reaſon, why they who are Ordained by Preſbyters cannot be received in their reſpective Orders, is peremptory; Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe, the <hi>Schiſm,</hi> conſiſting in Ordain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing againſt Authority, cannot be renoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced,
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:54672:39"/> unleſs the Ordination be voided. For, ſo long as the <hi>Miniſtry may be uſurp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, upon ſuch Ordination,</hi> ſo long is the Schiſm on foot. I do very well know, that the Ordinations of Arians were al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed by S. <hi>Athanaſius,</hi> in a Synod at <hi>Alexandria;</hi> who had made the Ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of <hi>Iſchyras</hi> by <hi>Coluthus</hi> void. And I remember the high acclamation, which S. <hi>Hierom</hi> applauds his Act with; That thereby, <hi>the world was ſnatched out of Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tans jaws.</hi> But I read, that the Tertulli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niaſts were received into the Church; not that they were <hi>received in their Orders.</hi> I find difficulty made by Forreign Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, of <hi>receiving the Donatiſts in their Orders;</hi> Notwithſtanding the complaints of the African Biſhops, that, without them, they had not Clergy enough to ſerve the Church. Hereby it is to be judged, how ſevere this Church was, with them that had received Ordination by Preſbyters. The Canon of the whole Church makes all <hi>Irregular;</hi> Ordainers and Ordained. Becauſe they had con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curred to bring back his Majeſty; (Which was the reſtoring of the Laws, and ſo of the Church) the forfeiture was wholly paſſed by, and nothing required
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:54672:39"/> of Ordainers, more then of the Clergy; Which is an utter <hi>Oblivion</hi> of the attempt made by thoſe Ordinations. And is not that a very great degree of <hi>Forbearance</hi> in our Caſe? S. <hi>Paul,</hi> when he injoyns <hi>Forbearance,</hi> doth he injoyn, that thoſe who did not underſtand, how men were ſaved by Faith alone, that were ſaved under the Law, ſhould be promoted to Orders, indifferently with thoſe that did profeſs it? That were indeed ſomething like that which hath been demanded, that <hi>Weakneſs</hi> ſhould intitle to the Clergy; which orderly ſuppoſes <hi>ſtrength.</hi> But does he injoyn farther, that they ſhould Miniſter without Orders? That, <hi>conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuing Lay-men,</hi> they ſhould commit the Sacrilege of Uſurping to Celebrate the Euchariſt? That, if their Ordination be void, by the Law of the Land, there ſhould be a new Law made, to make their Ordination good and valid, which was void when it was made? Then muſt he injoyn, that it be lawful for every Lay-man to celebrate the Euchariſt; Foraſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much as every Lay-man hath as much to do, to celebrate the Euchariſt, as he whoſe Ordination is void. Surely S. <hi>Paul,</hi> that commands Chriſtians to be <hi>without
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:54672:40"/> offenſe to the Jews and Gentiles, as well as to the Church,</hi> commands them alſo to be without offenſe to <hi>Papiſts.</hi> And will not we have thoſe, that would be inabled to conſecrate the Euchariſt, by ſuch a Law, to ſhew us how to ſatisfie the Papiſts, that ſuch Orders are good? At leaſt thoſe, that by their ſufferings have preſerved Ordination by Biſhops; Let them at leaſt be ſatisfied of the Validity of Ordination without Biſhops. At leaſt, let no man impoſe upon them, that they cannot yield the <hi>Forbearance,</hi> which S. <hi>Paul</hi> requires for tender Conſciences, unleſs they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive the Sacrament <hi>conſecrated by Lay-men;</hi> That is, by thoſe, whoſe Ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion they believe to be utterly void.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="15" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. XV. That the Orders of the Reformed Churches are not void, becauſe theſe are.</head>
               <p>NOw I am to look an Objection in the face, which, at a diſtance ſeems to admit of no Anſwer; but, if it be a little conſidered, will appear, to have neither Reaſon nor Religion at the bottom of it.
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:54672:40"/> It is ſaid, that hereby, we ſhall make void the Ordinations of the Reformed Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches of <hi>France,</hi> and others Reformed ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to <hi>Calvin;</hi> And ſo, make them no Churches. Here we agree, that it was neceſſary for the French, as well as for our ſelves, to Reform themſelves; That it was neceſſary for all to Reform themſelves, unto the Form of the Primi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Catholick Church, I ſay not we do agree; I ſay, that, till we do agree, there remains no hope of Unity, becauſe no Rule for Reformation, in the Church. But to the Objection; Who hath the Conſcience to think, or the Face to ſay, that if Ordinations made by Preſbyters againſt their Biſhops be void; Then, Ordinations made by Preſbyters, where they could not be had by Biſhops, are void? For, that is the <hi>difference of the Caſes.</hi> It is manifeſt, that the Biſhops of this Church, when they Ordain Preſby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, Ordain them to Miniſter their Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice, according to the Laws; That is, under their Biſhops. And can any man imagine, that hereby, they give them Power to Ordain others to Miniſter their Office, by what Laws they pleaſe themſelves? And, had the French demanded of their
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:54672:41"/> Biſhops, to Ordain them Preſbyters, that ſhould Miniſter their Office, according to the Reformation, does any man think they would have done it? So, the <hi>neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity</hi> of Reforming, which we all agree in, made the Ordinations of the Reformed Churches; The <hi>Pride and Preſumption,</hi> which cauſeth all Hereſie and Schiſm, uſurping Authority never received, made the Ordinations of our Preſbyters. And ſhall they be as valid as thoſe? All that can be queſtioned is, how it may appear, that it was not of choice, but of neceſſity, that they imbraced that way, of ſetling and propagating their Reformation, which they imbraced. And for that, we have ſufficient <hi>Preſumption,</hi> from the <hi>Albi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genſes;</hi> Who ſecretly Reforming them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, under the See of <hi>Rome,</hi> did cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly do it, by the Authority of Biſhops, who propagated their Order by Ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions. This may be proved by other te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimonies, if need be; But it is ſufficient, that the Caſe of the Bohemians is ſo well known. They, having reſolved, exactly to Reform themſelves; and having cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen the Perſons, whom they would have for their <hi>Biſhops;</hi> were at a ſtand, how to compaſs their ſucceſſion from the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles,
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:54672:41"/> by having them Ordained by Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops. In this <hi>nonplus,</hi> they underſtood, that there were in <hi>Auſtria,</hi> of the <hi>Albi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genſes,</hi> that kept ſecret Communion a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong themſelves, under their Biſhops; notwithſtanding that publickly, to avoid the Laws, they went to Maſs. To them they ſent their Biſhops elect, proteſting againſt their diſſembling; but deſiring Ordination for their Biſhops, which thus were propagated. And this may well ſeem to be the Reaſon, why, they that Reformed in the Empire, according to <hi>Luther,</hi> (in the name of whom <hi>Melancthon</hi> hath offered, to be ſubject to their own Biſhops, admitting the Reformation) ſet up ſuch a Form of Epiſcopacy, as they could, of themſelves. For, they had cauſe to think, that the Bohemians had not advantaged themſelves enough, by that Ordination, which they had been able to procure. For, it is to be noted, that they, the Bohemians, had ſent all over the World, to learn, how to get ſuch Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dination, as might authorize their Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtry, according to the Reformation which they pretended. And are not we, here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon, to preſume, that the French, by theſe degrees, finding a neceſſity of balk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:54672:42"/> the Authority of the Epiſcopacy, which they were under, did think them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, thereupon, free, to caſt themſelves into that Form, which they uſe? For, if it be ſaid; That, by this time, they had profited beyond their Predeceſſors, in diſcovering the <hi>Whore of Babylon;</hi> that they found Epiſcopacy to be the <hi>Body of Antichriſt,</hi> and therefore renounced it; It will appear, by many Reaſons, that this cannot ſerve the turn. Firſt, how can the common ſenſe of men endure to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve, that the Pope is Antichriſt, by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of that Greatneſs, which, it is certain and evident, that he hath attained, by Uſurping the Rights of his inferiour Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops? And yet, thoſe inferiour Biſhops be the Body of Antichriſt; by ſuffering thoſe Uſurpations, which they cannot help? Secondly, it is manifeſt, that they who ſhould hold this Plea could not pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend, by virtue of their Orders, received from the Biſhops of this Church, to Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dain Preſbyters; Unleſs they would ſay, that they may have their <hi>Authority from Antichriſt.</hi> This Plea, therefore, muſt remain for the <hi>Independents;</hi> to autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rize them, (that think themſelves in the State of Grace, before they are members
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:54672:42"/> of the Church) to make their their Congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions Churches, and Uſurp the <hi>Authority of Apoſtles,</hi> in Ordaining their own Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters. Laſtly, it appeareth ſufficiently, that very many learned and religious per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, of thoſe Churches, have not only approved the Epiſcopacy here ſetled; But have wiſhed the benefit of it, to themſelves. Whereby it is manifeſt, that thoſe Churches cannot owne this Reaſon; when another, ſo far from it, is owned by their principal Members. I have another Reaſon to alledge, which weighs as much with me as all theſe; And, that is, the Communion, which hath al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways been uſed, between this Church, and the Reformed Churches. For, ſhould they hold <hi>Communion</hi> with us, and yet think our Ordinations <hi>authorized by Antichriſt,</hi> how could they expect to be believed, ſo groſly contradicting them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves? And therefore, though I muſt not take upon me, either to <hi>juſtifie,</hi> or to <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn</hi> their Ordinations; Averring on one ſide, that they are not according to Rule; Seeing on the other ſide, that they are owned by my Superiors; yet I muſt acknowledge, that there are very great Reaſons to hope, and to preſume,
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:54672:43"/> that God accepteth of their Ordinations, though not made according to Rule; In conſideration of the neceſſity that drove them to it, and of the Reformation, which they were uſed to propagate. Whereas, thoſe that <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſurp the Power of the Keys,</hi> and the <hi>Conſecrating of the Eucha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſt,</hi> by virtue of Ordinations made in deſpite of thoſe Biſhops, from whom they have all the Authority, which they can challenge by their Orders; what pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenſe is there to imagine, that there can be any ſuch <hi>Crime as Schiſm,</hi> if this be not it? That God ſhould bleſs that, which is done by ſuch groſs <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſurpation,</hi> as this is? And when all this is ſaid, it remains free for me to ſay, That there is no other way to reſtore, and to preſerve <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity within the Reformation,</hi> but by eſtabliſhing and maintaining Epiſcopacy, in that Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, which it hath always had, for the determining of differences; Nor maintain that Authority, but by confining it, within the Bounds, which the Faith and the Laws of the whole Church do limit. As for the Fanaticks, which make our Orders void, becauſe the <hi>Pope is An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichriſt, and the Maſs Idolatry,</hi> whence our Biſhops received, and where they ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſed
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:54672:43"/> their Orders; I will only conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Caſe of the <hi>Donatiſts, forejudged by the whole Church.</hi> They pleaded, in point of fact, that <hi>Caecilianus</hi> was Ordained by <hi>Apoſtates.</hi> A thing which the Church was ſo clear in, that the African Biſhops offered to give up their Sees, if it were proved. But beſides, <hi>in point of Right,</hi> had it been proved, and <hi>Caecilianus</hi> owned by the Church, becauſe it did not appear, or becauſe they thought the Canons ought to be diſpenſed with, for Unities ſake; thoſe that Ordained <hi>Caecilianus</hi> ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving repented of their Apoſtacy; ſhall we imagine, that the Church was loſt, by owning thoſe that <hi>had been Apoſtates,</hi> and their Ordinations? The Donatiſts are branded for Hereticks and Schiſmaticks, maintaining all the Laws of the Church, but that of Unity. And ſhall <hi>Lay-Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians,</hi> preſuming to <hi>authorize Lay-Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians,</hi> to conſecrate the Euchariſt, and ſet up Churches, be eſteemed leſs then Hereticks and Schiſmaticks? Let thoſe that pretend to Unity find that Forbear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance, which a favourable conſtruction of their actions ſignifies. But Charity to the ſound obligeth, to take the profeſſion of Schiſmaticks in the worſt ſenſe, which
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:54672:44"/> if we do, the making of Independent Congregations Churches will be the <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nying of One Catholick</hi> Church; and the making of them Hereticks that do it.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="16" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. XVI. That changing the Laws for the <hi>Weak</hi> is not <hi>Forbearance.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>BUt if it be a thing abſurd in common ſenſe, to allow them their Orders, much more abſurd will it be, to change the Eccleſiaſtical Laws of the Land for their ſakes; Which is nothing elſe, but to purchaſe their Miniſtry, at the price of our Religion; which the Eccleſiaſtical Laws contain. Here, we muſt diſtinguiſh two queſtions; For it may be lawful for Chriſtian people, to live by thoſe Laws, which it was not lawful for Superiors, in Church and State, to make. A thing evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent to all that believe, that it was poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble for our Anceſtors, before the Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation, to be ſaved, under the abuſes of the Church of <hi>Rome.</hi> But our queſtion is, whether or no, the Laws of Superiors injoyn that, which Gods Law forbids
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:54672:44"/> Inferiors to do. Otherwiſe, it is perni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious to <hi>all Government,</hi> that Inferiors ſhould take upon them, to judge the Acts of Superiors. But if the matter of the Law be within the Power that makes it, to require an <hi>Exception</hi> for <hi>tender Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences</hi> is to ſay, that there is <hi>no Power in the World</hi> to give any Law to thoſe tender Conſciences. Was there ever any Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie, any Schiſm, any Religion pretending Chriſtianity, that did not alledge Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture for themſelves? Did ever any man alledge it, that would not be thought, to be touched at the heart with it? What is there for a Chriſtian to doubt at, where <hi>the Exception of tender Conſciences</hi> lyes not? Or how ſhall we, that agree againſt the See of <hi>Rome,</hi> but agree not in the terms and grounds of Reformation, be tryed, in the ſenſe of the Scripture? Can any man imagine, that S. <hi>Paul</hi> intended to deſtroy his own Authority, of giving Law to the Church, which he exerciſed, when he ordered the Jews and Gentiles at <hi>Rome,</hi> to <hi>forbear</hi> one another? Or is this Authority dead with the Apoſtles? What Church then can there be alive, if there be no Authority deriyed from the Apoſtles, to give Law to it? But the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:54672:45"/> is not queſtioned, ſo it <hi>provide for weak Conſciences.</hi> Epiſcopacy will be owned, if the Secular Power will force it, to take them for their Preſbyters, whoſe Miniſtry they cannot give account to God of; Being both authorized and exerciſed by Laws made, without and againſt their Authority. This, no Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianity can juſtifie. Chriſtianity main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains the Eſtates of the World, in all the Right they had, when they became Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians; And cannot juſtifie it ſelf to the World otherwiſe. How ſhould the World receive it upon other terms? But if the World ſtand upon the ſame terms, having received Chriſtianity, as afore; then muſt Chriſtianity, and the Church, continue in the ſame Rights, which it had before the World received it. No exception to be allowed, but as afore; If it appear, that the Faith and Laws of the Primitive Church be decayed. Not if it ſeem to <hi>private Spirits,</hi> that the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture is not fulfilled. In the mean time, is it for the honour of the Religion we pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs, that <hi>Weakneſs,</hi> (which at the beſt is <hi>negative ignorance,</hi> in truth, perhaps, <hi>wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful ignorance)</hi> ſhould give Law to it? Is it reaſon, that they, who have failed to
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:54672:45"/> deſtroy both Church and Kingdom, ſhould give Law to both? As if a Child ſhould govern the Houſe, becauſe he will be framfold, and diſquieted, otherwiſe. Surely it is that, which the Emperor ſaid to his Niece; <hi>Put as tibi injuriam fieri niſi imperas?</hi> But is that the way to have Peace in Religion? When Inferiors ſhall be made to <hi>tread upon the necks</hi> of their Superiors, they will be ſo modeſt for the future, as to ſtay there. They will be content, to have their Doctrine regulated by them, as the Law of the Kingdom re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires. Or, they will think fit, that the Biſhops be content with their Revenues, and leave them to <hi>Preach what they pleaſe.</hi> Surely, they that can carry the diſpute of a hundred years; wherein the Biſhops had ſo viſibly the better, that Club-law was found requiſite to get the advantage; will not lay down the Cudgels here. So, they that agree, in conforming to the Laws, differing every day, in that which the Law determines not, the <hi>Recuſants</hi> on both ſides may make hay in the heat of our Contentions; and profit more by ſuch a Law, then by the War which de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed this Church. But eſpecially the <hi>Atheiſts,</hi> who have profited ſo well under
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:54672:46"/> theſe Contentions, as to make that viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, which was but foreſeen under the Uſurper; That no Religion would in time ſtand to be the Religion of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom; They, having the Priviledge of the Laws, and not liable to any Infamy, when the differences maintained make Religion contemptible, ſhall have cauſe to thank all that ſhall have done their work, by ſolliciting ſuch Laws.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="17" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. XVII. Of the Opinion of Regeneration by Baptiſm.</head>
               <p>ONe point I muſt not paſs over in ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence, which hath been named for a point to be changed; That all paſſages, ſeeming to determine <hi>the Opinion of Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptiſmal Regeneration,</hi> be altered in the Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turgy and Rubricks of it. For, this point is an inſtance, how eaſily, the ſubſtance of Faith, neceſſary to Salvation, may be queſtioned, or abated, or renounced, by a Clauſe of ſuch an Act. I grant it is clearly S. <hi>Pauls Opinion, S. Peters Opinion, our Lord Chriſts Opinion,</hi> the Opinion of Gods whole Church. Be it the Opinion of
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:54672:46"/> thoſe, whoſe Opinion is our Faith. But he that would have it no more then Opinion, muſt teach us a new Faith. No <hi>Remiſſion of Sins</hi> but by Baptiſm; En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tring us into the <hi>Covenant</hi> of Grace, which the Vow of Baptiſm inacteth. Entring us into the <hi>Church,</hi> into which the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Baptiſm introduceth. Abate the Covenant, which the Sacrament of Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptiſm inacteth, and how ſhall a Chriſtian be regenerate? Abate the mention of it in the Service, and where will be the Faith, which this Church, with the Whole Church, hitherto profeſſeth? Shew me any Chriſtian, that ever que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtioned it, till it was queſtioned, what was to be Reformed in the Church, and let it be abated. Could <hi>Pelagius</hi> have queſtioned it, his Hereſie had not ſo eaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly been quelled. He that travelled all the Church, from <hi>Britain</hi> to <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> had he found <hi>any Church, any received Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor of any Church,</hi> that durſt maintain Salvation due by the Covenant of Grace, to any man that dyes unbaptized, he had made the Church more work then he did. No Baptiſm, no Original ſin; no Cure for Original ſin but Baptiſm; no Salvation without the Cure. They that think to
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:54672:47"/> confute Anabaptiſts, abating this point of Faith, no marvel if they make Anaba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptiſts; when they make men think, that the Church hath no better Reaſon to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fute them with, then they will uſe. Some perhaps, that are not ſo well taught as they ſhould be, may think it unagreeable with Chriſtianity, that Salvation ſhould depend upon a <hi>Bodily act,</hi> as the waſhing of Baptiſm; and that <hi>in the Power,</hi> not of him that is Baptized, but <hi>of the Church,</hi> or of him that is to miniſter in behalf of the Church. But S. <hi>Peter</hi> hath anſwered this Objection, by diſtinguiſhing two things in Baptiſm, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> III. 21. the one, the <hi>waſhing of the Body,</hi> which ſaves not; The other, the Anſwer that is made out <hi>of a good Conſcience,</hi> to the <hi>Examination</hi> ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered him that is Baptized; whether he will undertake Chriſtianity or not; And this <hi>ſaves,</hi> if S. <hi>Peter</hi> ſay true. And what account can any Chriſtian give himſelf, to ground the hope of his Salvation upon, but <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Chriſtianity; which the Goſpel tendreth, which Baptiſm inacteth? Or what can be neceſſary to Salvation, if the ground of the hope thereof be not? This is that one ground, which over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throweth both thoſe Hereſies, in which,
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:54672:47"/> I ſaid, all the erroneous Doctrines, of that Confuſion which we have ſeen, do re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolve. The Profeſſion, which we make at our Baptiſm, is the Condition on our part, upon which, the Promiſe of the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant of Grace becomes due on Gods part. The Profeſſion ſo made, nothing can defeat the hope of a Chriſtian, but the tranſgreſſing of it; Being tranſgreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, nothing can repair this hope, but the reſtoring of it. All Arts to diſguiſe this Faith, all over the Scripture, ſignifie no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, but the hope of Salvation, without living the life of Chriſtians. I will hope, whatſoever <hi>Fanaticks</hi> or <hi>Atheiſts</hi> would have, that there was never any intent to demand, ſo great <hi>an Apoſtaſie from the Faith</hi> to be inacted, by a Law of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom. I will hope much more, that, had it been demanded, it would have been rejected, with that indignation, which ſo great Apoſtaſie deſerveth. But I am glad, and give God hearty thanks, that I have lived to the day, when I may and do teſtifie to my Country, and to the Church of God in it, that he who ſhould demand of them, to renounce this point, muſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand of them to unchurch themſelves, and to be, for the future, that which the
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:54672:48"/> See of <hi>Rome</hi> would have us to be.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="18" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. XVIII. Conference for Satisfaction is <hi>Forbearance.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>BUt is there then no effect of S. <hi>Pauls</hi> precept, in our Caſe? Can we break the Unity of the Church, without bread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Charity of Chriſtians? Or can particular Chriſtians be tyed <hi>to forbear one another,</hi> and Chriſtian Powers not be tied, to cauſe both to do the ſame? Here is indeed the <hi>Hinge,</hi> upon which the truth turns; and reſolves all queſtions, and clears all difficulties, which muſt and will intangle the World in confuſion, upon the account of Chriſtianity, till it be owned. Chriſtian Powers may conſtrain their Subjects, that profeſs Chriſtianity, to be Chriſtians; and puniſh them if they be not. But they muſt protect them for their Subjects, though they be not. The rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of this hath not been declared, by the Reformation; though they have juſt cauſe to complain, and do, as they have cauſe, complain of the See of <hi>Rome,</hi> for authorizing <hi>capital Penalties</hi> upon Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks.
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:54672:48"/> Under that name they comprize alſo <hi>Schiſmaticks;</hi> And Schiſmaticks, in their language, (as alſo in the language of all that claim the Authority of the Church) ſignifies all that maintain Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion apart; though the <hi>Cauſe make the Crime</hi> before God. But if S. <hi>Paul</hi> have Reaſon, when he commands every Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian to <hi>continue in the Eſtate in which he was called</hi> to be a Chriſtian, then can no mans Life or Eſtate become forfeit, for not being a Chriſtian; And much leſs, for not being <hi>Orthodox,</hi> but an <hi>Heretick.</hi> If the Life or Eſtates of Subjects ſhould Eſchete to the Soveraign, for not being Chriſtians, that <hi>temporal Dominion</hi> of So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veraigns muſt be <hi>founded upon the Grace</hi> they have to be Chriſtians. All ſuch Right S. <hi>Paul</hi> diſclaims, and diſcharges. But ſhall Soveraign Power, that is Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian, be therefore diſabled, to give Law to Subjects profeſſing Chriſtianity? That is our Caſe; the whole Kingdom pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſing Chriſtianity, though the <hi>Whole</hi> cannot ſo properly be ſaid to profeſs the Reformation. For, the Reformation ſetled by Law, we ſee, is refuſed, as well by thoſe that ſeparate from it, for a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation of their own, as by thoſe that
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:54672:49"/> adhere to the See of <hi>Rome.</hi> Shall the Soveraign then loſe the Right, that all Chriſtian Soveraigns have, of giving Law to their Subjects, in point of Religion, becauſe he is a Chriſtian? Or ſhall the Subject, by being a Chriſtian, ſtand obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged to the Laws of his Soveraign, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manding him to ſtand to the Chriſtianity which he profeſſeth? Suppoſe the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianity commanded to be <hi>Viſible,</hi> before Chriſtian Powers command it, and you inable their Laws to oblige their Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects. Not ſuppoſing it, you cannot ſay, how the Laws of Soveraign Powers ſhould oblige Chriſtian Subjects; ſeeing the Papacy, as well as the Reformation, maintained by Chriſtian Soveraigns. For, by the ſame Reaſon, for which, the Subjects of thoſe Powers that maintain the Reformation are tied to their Laws; by the ſame Reaſon, ſhould the Subjects of thoſe that maintain the Papacy be ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liged to obey the Laws, by which they maintain it. There can be no Reaſon for a difference, if that which they main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain be not <hi>Viſible,</hi> before the Law main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain it. I ſuppoſe it will not be though a good Plea, at the day of Judgment, for a Subject to ſay; that he was either <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant</hi>
                  <pb n="91" facs="tcp:54672:49"/> or <hi>Papiſt,</hi> becauſe his Soveraign was ſo. Now, Chriſtianity can be Viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, by no other means, but, becauſe it is the Viſible Profeſſion of the Viſible Church. If it <hi>become Inviſible,</hi> by diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rences betwixt Parties, it muſt be in So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veraign Powers, to bring the Parties to tryal; Provided, that there be no tryal, but by the Viſible Church. This is the <hi>Forbearance</hi> that may be <hi>extended by Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtors,</hi> and may be <hi>required by the Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raign,</hi> in our Caſe. For, the preſent diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenſion ſhews, that the Reformation was well begun, indeed, but not perfected. Does not the World know, that there was an Act in force, for nominating Commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaries, to <hi>Reform the Eccleſiaſtical Laws</hi> of the Kingdom? I am not to ſay, why this Act took no effect. I think I have ſaid it, when I have obſerved <hi>the riſe of the Puritan Party,</hi> and the ſeeds of the late War, ſowed in the beginning of <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſancy.</hi> But I am to ſay, it could not have taken good effect, without taking in the Principle which I maintain. What could be more juſt, and diſcreet, then to appoint Commiſſaries, in equal num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, of <hi>Biſhops, Divines, Civil and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Lawyers?</hi> But what could have had
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:54672:50"/> force, but that which had been done, to reſtore and maintain the Faith, and Laws of the Primitive Church? There are ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry great Reaſons, why, thoſe that deſire to ſerve the Church ſhould be ſatisfied, in all that this <hi>Exception</hi> will allow. There can be no Reaſon, why more ſhould be allowed. To bring them into diſpute with their <hi>Paſtors,</hi> is to put the <hi>Authority of the Church</hi> to compromiſe. To com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>promiſe any Law of the Kingdom, to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pute of Divines, upon this Principle, is no more, then to oblige, either Popiſh or Fanatick Recuſants, either to ſtand to the Reſult, or to ſuffer <hi>Penalties competent to their diſobedience;</hi> and the hazard which the <hi>Publick Peace</hi> runneth, when the <hi>Peace of Religion</hi> is diſturbed. If that which hath been pretended be all that is intend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; That ſome ſmall things are ſcrupled; Let the Legiſlative Power be ſatisfied, that the preſervation of Religion, and of the Authority of the Church; in which the preſervation of Religion conſiſteth; is only ſought. The Intereſt of the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, to give and to receive mutual ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction, is ſo great, that if there can be ever hope of Peace, by diſpute, this is the time, and ours the Caſe, wherein to hope for it.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="19" type="chapter">
               <pb n="93" facs="tcp:54672:50"/>
               <head>CHAP. XIX. Probability of recovering the Presbyterians.</head>
               <p>FOr, I cannot have ſo hard an opinion of men, whoſe zeal, for the advance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of <hi>Diſcipline</hi> in the Church, I have always eſteemed; as to think them re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved, to ruine the <hi>Common Chriſtianity,</hi> without hope of doing their own buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs; ſeeing this to be the unavoidable conſequence, of holding up the diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence on foot; rather then taking up, with ſo much of their own Pretenſions, as the State of the Catholick Church will allow. Let them conſider, in the firſt place, the <hi>Recuſancy of the Fanaticks</hi> as well as thoſe of the Church of <hi>Rome;</hi> What hope their Principles can give them, either to make their Recuſancy pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhable by the Law of the Land, or to reduce them, by convicting them of that ſenſe of the Scripture, which they only allow themſelves to convict them with? I ſet aſide, for the preſent, thoſe Prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies of <hi>Daniel</hi> and the <hi>Revelation,</hi> by which, they pretend the Pope to be Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt,
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:54672:51"/> and the Papiſts Idolaters. For, I muſt argue in due place, that the Recu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſancy of the Papiſt cannot be puniſhable by Law, upon this Account. But how will they, either reduce the <hi>Recuſancy of the Papiſt,</hi> by thoſe puniſhments, which the Recuſancy of the Fanaticks muſt ſuffer; or give the Kingdom, God, and the World, a Reaſon for the <hi>why not?</hi> which the beſt of them is here challenged to undertake. Then, let them conſider the wantonneſs of theſe times, and the wits of them, that think it good ſport, to call in queſtion the foundation of Chriſtiani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, upon the belief of <hi>Original ſin,</hi> by in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troducing the <hi>praeexiſtence of Souls;</hi> That think it but ſport, to make ready their ſtudies in Divinity, for the Pulpit, by <hi>Epiſcopius his Works;</hi> denying Original ſin both name and thing, and making <hi>the Faith of the Holy Trinity</hi> unneceſſary to Salvation. Or rather by the Works of the Socinians, collected and united toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in <hi>Holland,</hi> on purpoſe to prepare us, for the ſame Apoſtaſie to Socinianiſm, which they are in ſo much danger of there. Let them conſider, what hope they have, to <hi>make the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſities good Presbyterians,</hi> that have ſowed the ſeeds
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:54672:51"/> of this danger in them, by the diſſatisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction they had of their Doctrine, when they were in Poſſeſſion there. Then let them tell me, what we ſhall ſay to the Papiſts, to perſwade them, to come to Church; when as they ſhall ſay, that they cannot be ſecured, that their <hi>Curate is no Socinian, or Origeniſt.</hi> For, the Armi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nian Congregations in <hi>Holland</hi> having ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted the Socinians into their Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion; and the Canon of the Church ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king all <hi>Socinians,</hi> in the eye of the Church, that <hi>Communicate with Socini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans;</hi> how ſhall they be ſecured againſt thoſe, that take their Doctrine from the Socinians; Or from them, who commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicate with Socinians? Beſides, let them but remember the time, when they had the Ball at their Foot; an Ordinance of Parliament for ſetting up their Preſbyte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries; And how much they gained upon the People, (whom they had diſordered out of all Eccleſiaſtical Government) when they came to be at what they would be at. I think they will be at ſo great deſpair, of reducing the World to their intent, (having nothing in the Law of the Land to favour it) that they will think, that they have cauſe to thank God, of a
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:54672:52"/> good opportunity, to bring them off from an ingagement, in which they are like to gain ſo little, by hazarding the common Chriſtianity. As for the Clergy of this Church, I ſuppoſe there is none of them ſo little a Chriſtian, as to repute it a loſs to the <hi>Party,</hi> to ſee their Adverſaries capable of that truſt in the Church, and thoſe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards of it, which they have ſuffered for themſelves. For, if the neceſſity of the Kingdom hath required an <hi>Act of Obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vion,</hi> much more muſt the <hi>neceſſity of Religion;</hi> which cannot be attained, without a cordial conſpiring, of thoſe that are to manage it; inforce a <hi>mixture of Intereſt.</hi> And that being conſidered, let any man tell me, how that can be made, but by a <hi>Third,</hi> in which all are alike Intereſſed; That is, by owning the Faith and the Laws of the Catholick Church, whereby the Papiſt is either re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced, or left puniſhable as the Fanatick.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="20" type="chapter">
               <pb n="97" facs="tcp:54672:52"/>
               <head>CHAP. XX. The Cure, by repairing the Revenue of the Church.</head>
               <p>BUt all this is but a Cure for the <hi>Sym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptom.</hi> Should ſuch a <hi>Conference</hi> take effect, the <hi>Cauſe</hi> of the diſeaſe would re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main intire. For, the Cauſe of our Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſions is not theſe differences; which are too inconſiderable, to produce ſo in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comparable a miſchief, as that of Schiſm. It riſes, and is fomented, by thoſe Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſts, which the <hi>imperfection of two Laws</hi> of <hi>Henry</hi> VIII. hath created. So that, the Reformation is no way obliged to anſwer for them; Only, if it refuſe not to mend them, now that time hath diſcovered the miſchiefs which they have produced. I call them two Laws, not as if they were compriſed in <hi>two Acts of Parliament;</hi> but becauſe they concern, one of them the <hi>indowment,</hi> the other, the <hi>Rights of the Church.</hi> We all know, that, when the Monaſteries were given to the Crown, the indowment of thoſe Churches, which had been impropriated to thoſe Monaſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries,
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:54672:53"/> was transferred, by the Crown, into thoſe hands, that could not Officiate the Cure of Pariſhes; as the <hi>Monaſteries,</hi> by ſome of their <hi>Members,</hi> or by their <hi>Vicars,</hi> had done. And, though the Right of the Crown (which could be no more then the Monaſteries had) could not abate the <hi>Original Right of the Biſhop,</hi> in ſetling a <hi>reaſonable portion</hi> upon the Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carages; yet, in the hands of thoſe that claim under the Crown, it hath appeared ſo ſtrong, that ſuch Vicarages are gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally impoveriſhed; But where the Cure lay upon the Covent, there, there now remains no indowment, <hi>no Proviſion for the Cure of Souls;</hi> Which falls out moſt in Cities, and places that were moſt fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quented with Monaſteries, as well as with People. What the conſequence hereof hath been, it is plain enough; Even a ſort of <hi>Mungrel Clergie of Lecturers;</hi> Who, being Authorized by the <hi>Biſhops Orders and Licenſe,</hi> but <hi>payed by the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple,</hi> to ſupply the Office of Preaching, which the Benefices of the Church were not able to maintain; Like a Pack of Dogs, that are ruled by the Huntſman that ſeeds them, and ſets them a work, not by the Maſter that provides for them;
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:54672:53"/> No marvel that they owne not the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops, for <hi>Judge of their Preaching,</hi> whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther according to the Law or not. He that ſees not, that this was the ſourſe of the late War, of him is the Proverb, that ſays; <hi>No man ſo blind as he that will not ſee.</hi> And the worſt is, that ſo great a part of the <hi>Gentry,</hi> as have ſhared with the Crown, in the ſpoils of the Monaſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, think it their <hi>Intereſt,</hi> to hold up that <hi>Party,</hi> which, they think, would juſtifie their Title in point of Conſcience; Whereas it is found by experience, that thoſe very Preachers, that would Reform the Church by force of the People, would queſtion their Tenure, as ſoon as they ſaw themſelves in condition to do it. Now, I intend not here to diſpute, that, founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions to intents of falſe Religion; as for redeeming Souls out of Purgatory; are <hi>ipſo facto</hi> forfeit to the true. God him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf hath recommended this Courſe to the Church, in the Caſe of the <hi>Cenſers</hi> of <hi>Core, Dathan,</hi> and <hi>Abiram;</hi> which he challenges for his own, to the uſe of the Altar, though conſecrated to the uſe of their Schiſm. But the Chriſtian Emperors of the Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitive Churches, inacting thoſe Penalties upon the Conventicles of Hereticks and
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:54672:54"/> Schiſmaticks, which we read, in the laſt Book of <hi>Theodoſius</hi> his <hi>Code,</hi> the fifth Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle <hi>de Haereticis;</hi> have confiſcated the pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces where they met in nine Laws, and forfeited them to the Church, in five. Whereby it appears, that the Primitive Church, living under thoſe Laws, did not think, that goods, ſo conſecrated, do, of neceſſity, <hi>eſchete</hi> to the Church. My preſent purpoſe obliges me only to ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, that the <hi>Tithes;</hi> which, all the world ſaw, that they had been conſecra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to God, for maintaining the <hi>Cures of the Pariſhes;</hi> Theſe, if there be any ſuch thing as a Church, could not be alienated from it, <hi>without Sacriledge.</hi> But I ſay not, therefore, that they can never be held <hi>bona ſide;</hi> Which is that which makes the jealouſie incurable, in thoſe that find their Eſtates conſiſt much of them. And, yet, I undertake not to warrant, generally, the holding of them; Only think, that, in ſome particulars, it may be warrantable. For, when they are come into ſuch hands, that the ſupport of Eſtates depends neceſſarily upon them; and that, by <hi>mean contracts, and originally ſuch,</hi> as had in them no <hi>ill Faith;</hi> I ſay not I can warrant them, I think they may be
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:54672:54"/> warrantable. Now, I know there may be an <hi>Act of Oblivion</hi> done by the <hi>Church,</hi> as well as by the Kingdom. And the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> knew it well enough, when they reconciled this Kingdom, under Q. <hi>Mary,</hi> without reſtoring theſe Poſſeſſions. By the ſame Reaſon, for which Hereticks and Schiſmaticks were always <hi>diſpenſed with for Canonical Penalties;</hi> (leaving the <hi>Pardon to God,</hi> that the Unity of the Church might be recovered) By the ſame, may the Church leave all to their own Conſciences; not warranting their pardon from God, neither yet refuſing them the <hi>Communion,</hi> as unpardonable. But alas, what would this Act do in our Caſe, did the whole Clergy underſtand themſelves tyed in Conſcience, by it, not ſo much as to mention, much leſs to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach any ſuch Tenure? So long as the miſchief once done remains unprovided for, by the Law, which gives the Title and Poſſeſſion; the contradiction be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the <hi>Canonical and Popular Intereſts</hi> can never ceaſe. But if the Kingdom conſider, that it was an Act of Parliament that did the wrong, they muſt neceſſarily find, that <hi>nothing but an Act of Parliament</hi> can repair it. And if the People conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der,
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:54672:55"/> that a Parliament may tranſgreſs the truſt which they repoſe in them; (which of neceſſity may come to paſs, unleſs we make the <hi>Parliament infallible, and the Pope not)</hi> they will eaſily find, that a Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament cannot repair the wrong that a former Parliament hath done, but upon the Charge of the people. For Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>goods, under Chriſtianity, ceaſe not to be the <hi>Goods of the People,</hi> though the <hi>Church</hi> be <hi>truſted</hi> with managing them, being founded by God for that purpoſe. And he that admits of the neceſſity of all this, will find it no conſiderable Charge for the whole Kingdom, to furniſh contribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, neceſſary for the founding and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowing of Churches, requiſite for the <hi>Reſort and Cures</hi> of all Aſſemblies, requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſite for a Reformation regulated by the Primitive Church. And if this be one Cauſe of our Diviſions, and that the Kingdom cannot be counted a Chriſtian Kingdom, till it take a courſe in it; let no man marvel to ſee the Judgments of God, in our Diviſions, when he ſees the <hi>Sin of the Kingdom</hi> continue. And if this were conſidered, the diſcourſes that walk up and down in all Aſſemblies, of relieving the Publick Charge, by ſeizing
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:54672:55"/> the pitiful remainder of the Church-Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venue, would appear to be, as they are, the productions of <hi>Atheiſm,</hi> not of pity to the peoples purſes.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="21" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. XXI. By limiting and reſtoring Eccleſiaſtical Diſcipline.</head>
               <p>THe other Law, concerning the Right of the Church, in the Supre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macy of the Crown, <hi>over all Perſons, and in all Cauſes, as well Fccleſiaſtical as Civil,</hi> may ſeem to extinguiſh the Right of the Church, over the ſame Perſons, and in the ſame Cauſes: Which could not be called <hi>Eccleſiaſtical,</hi> if there were no ſuch thing as a Church, (as one of the Articles of our Creed profeſſes) indowed by God, with a Right in and over the ſame. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, I do not attribute the cauſe of our diviſions to it, as unjuſt, but as <hi>indefinite,</hi> and unlimited. And I inſtance in the Tenure of our <hi>Eccleſiaſtical Courts;</hi> Which, by a branch of this Law, are de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared to be <hi>the Kings Courts,</hi> and the Judges of them <hi>the Kings Judges.</hi> A thing
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:54672:56"/> neceſſarily following, upon the <hi>Reſumpti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> of the Rights of the Crown, uſurped by the See of <hi>Rome,</hi> into the Crown. But which hath turned ſo great diſſatisfaction, in the eſtabliſhment of Religion by the Law of this Land; becauſe the Right of the Church, in that part of their Juriſdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, which neceſſarily ariſeth from the Founding of the Church, by our Lord Chriſt, hath not been reſerved to the Church, by <hi>expreſs Proviſion of Law.</hi> Thereupon followed another Law, which gave the Judges of theſe Courts <hi>the Priviledge of being Married:</hi> At ſuch time, as the Law of the Land allowed not the Clergy to Marry. And by conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence, made them no Clergy-men, whom the Law owned for the <hi>Kings Judges</hi> of theſe Courts; Exempting them thereby, from <hi>the Canonical Obedience,</hi> which they of Clergy owe their Biſhops; And leaving their Miniſtring of the Laws, in their reſpective Juriſdiction, to their own diſcretion, as well againſt, as without the conſent of their Biſhops. It is true, they ſubſiſt by <hi>Patents</hi> granted by their Biſhops, and other <hi>Eccleſiaſtical Dignities,</hi> indowed with Juriſdictions. But, the Law having declared them <hi>the Kings
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:54672:56"/> Judges,</hi> I refer it to Judgment, whether it were any marvel, that the Biſhops, and other Dignities with Juriſdiction, ſhould diſcharge themſelves of their Juriſdiction, upon ſuch Judges, as the Law had quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied, rather then croſs the Law, in taking them upon their own charge; Part whereof, in miniſtring the <hi>Power of the Keys,</hi> and in <hi>correcting the inferior Clergie,</hi> is eſſential, and neceſſary to the Office, which Ordination makes the Clergy (Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops, and Preſbyters) capable of. For it is reſolved upon, by the Sages of our Laws, that, ſuch a Patent being granted for <hi>term of life,</hi> the Patentee is inabled to exerciſe the whole Juriſdiction, without and againſt the conſent of him that grants it; and ſhall be maintained againſt him, in ſo doing, by the Law of the Land. I am neither to blame, nor to excuſe them, that have not done their utmoſt, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deem the Office, which we are conſecra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to a capacity of managing, out of that Poſſeſſion, which the Law of the Land thus ingageth. For, it is granted, and it is to be granted, that <hi>the Church cannot pardon ſin;</hi> As if it could pardon him that is not qualified for pardon: Or keep him from pardon that is. But the Church par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dons
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:54672:57"/> ſin, by bringing him to be <hi>qualified for pardon that is not:</hi> And declaring him <hi>pardoned that is.</hi> If we were Fana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks, and believed no <hi>Condition</hi> of par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don, but only, to imagine that we are pardoned; There would be no Church, <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> Keys of the Church to manage. If we believed, as ſome underſtand the Council of <hi>Trent;</hi> That ſin is pardoned, by <hi>ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitting it to the Keys of the Church:</hi> And that the mortification of the fleſh ſerves only to redeem the <hi>temporal Penalty,</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maining due when the ſin is pardoned; A Lay Judge, having knowledge, might manage the Keys of the Church, as well as a Prieſt. But, becauſe a notorious ſinner becomes qualified for pardon, when the Concupiſcence is mortified, which his ſin gratifies: And, becauſe he <hi>undergoes his Mortification,</hi> becauſe he cannot have the Communion otherwiſe; Therefore are they only, that conſecrate the Eucha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſt, to judge, whether he be qualified or not, and to give or refuſe him that which they conſecrate. And, <hi>Commutation of Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance,</hi> when it ſuppoſes not, the inward contrition of the heart performed, by outward mortification of the fleſh, is but the betraying of that Soul to damnation,
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:54672:57"/> whom it admits to Communion, not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing qualified for it. True it is, nothing hinders him, that is diſcharged of Excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munication, to become qualified by his own private endeavours. But, God would never have founded his Church, upon the Power of the Keys, if the Office thereof were only, not to hinder, and not alſo to procure, notorious ſinners, to be fit for Communion with the Church. And, that to procure, muſt be the Office of thoſe, who, by the Foundation of the Church, are to judge, who is fit and who not. If therefore the Law of the Land provide not, that that Office of the Church may be in force, to that effect, for which the Power of the Keys is given them that conſecrate the Euchariſt; Is it any marvel, that the Judgment and Ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance of God ſhould lye ſo heavy upon the Land, profeſſing Reformation, and not inabling that which it profeſſeth to take place? My preſent buſineſs there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore is now to ſay; That the Intereſts which cauſe our Diviſions are ſo far im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putable to theſe Laws, as, without the Reforming of the Laws, they cannot be cured. Two of theſe Intereſts I name, contradictory the one to the other, in their
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:54672:58"/> Pretenſes. For, what doth the World complain of, but of the abuſe of Excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munication; daily imployed, to inforce the contentious Juriſdiction of theſe Courts; Never imployed, to the corre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of ſin, and recalling of ſinners; Which, being the Office of thoſe that receove the <hi>Power of the Keys</hi> by Ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, cannot be exerciſed by the Laity, without Sacriledge. Now, granting, that the Uſurpation of the See of <hi>Rome,</hi> or the Indulgence of Chriſtian Princes and States have procured, or granted to the Clergy, a larger Juriſdiction then their Office required; It would have been no Inconvenience, that the whole Juriſdiction ſhould be inforced, by Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communication, ſignifying impriſonment by the Law of the Land; If a difference had been made, between the <hi>proper Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſdiction of the Church,</hi> and the <hi>Acceſſory.</hi> For, in this part of it, it is an oppreſſion to Chriſtian Subjects, that they ſhould be barred the <hi>Communion,</hi> for maintaining themſelves and their Right, by Law, in matters of any Right of this World; Though the Clergy were Judges, by the Law of the Land. But it would be no oppreſſion to them, that the Juriſdiction
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:54672:58"/> of the Kings Courts ſhould be inforced by impriſonment; which Excommunication might ſignifie, by the Law of the Land, without ſignifying <hi>a Bar to the Communion of the Euchariſt;</hi> if theſe were duely di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinguiſhed. In the mean time, the whole indowment of the Church, in a manner, being <hi>irrecoverable</hi> by theſe Courts, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Excommunication; the ſcandal of theſe Juriſdictions becomes a Popular Plea, to ſtrip the Clergy of their mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance; Tyths being no farther paid, then it pleaſe Frantick Fanaticks, or contenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous neighbours, to do right of good will; Knowing that, Excommunication being odious, Impriſonment is not like eaſily to follow upon it. I ſaid, that there is ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Intereſt on foot, upon a Pretenſe contradictory to this. And I mean that, which vulgar <hi>Profeſſors of the Laws of the Land</hi> ſet up to themſelves, out of theſe ſcandals; To reduce the whole Juriſdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of Eccleſiaſtical Courts under the Juriſdiction of the Laws of the Land, and thoſe Courts that miniſter the ſame. This Intereſt eſpouſeth the Opinion, which voids the Article of our Creed that pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſes <hi>One Catholick Church;</hi> making Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communication, and Eccleſiaſtical Juriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction,
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:54672:59"/> founded by our Lord Chriſt, a meer Impoſture; declareth it uncapable of any Sacriledge, to be committed in the uſing of it. In the mean time, the Clergy, whoſe Intereſt is no ways con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned, in the <hi>Scandals, which the Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſtical Courts</hi> may give; Further, then as they are hindred, by the ſaid Courts, to cure their Scandals, by the due Uſe of their own Office; do ſuffer, not only the Scandals which are done under colour of their Patents; But even the affronts of the Eccleſiaſtical Courts themſelves; Receiving Appeals, from the Cenſure of their Biſhops upon the Clergy. For, a few examples, ſerving the Biſhops, not to imploy that Juriſdiction, which is ſo ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſily affronted, it muſt be acknowledged, that the debauches of the Clergy are come to that height, that, till they be Reformed, Reformation is not duely pretended againſt the See of <hi>Rome.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="22" type="chapter">
               <pb n="111" facs="tcp:54672:59"/>
               <head>CHAP. XXII. The ground of the proper Intereſt of the Church.</head>
               <p>BUt perhaps there be thoſe, that are perſwaded by the <hi>Leviathan,</hi> that a Church is nothing elſe but <hi>a Chriſtian Common-wealth.</hi> And that the Civil Power thereof, which is Soveraign, hath full Right to injoyn whatſoever it pleaſe, for the Chriſtian Religion; exacting what Penalties it pleaſe of Recuſants. There be others beſides the Leviathan, that have maintained ſome branches of the ſame Opinion; but he is the only man, that hath looked the whole Queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in the Face, with this Anſwer. I will but relate the Iſſue, which his own Reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution hath driven him to, and leave him to Judgment. For, having objected to himſelf, in his Latine Book <hi>de Cive,</hi> that which is obvious to all Underſtandings; That then, a Chriſtian may be juſtly pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed, for his Chriſtianity; He anſwers, that it is no inconvenience, that he ſhould; Becauſe, by ſuffering, he pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſes
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:54672:60"/> an abundant reward. I know not whether any man told him, or whether himſelf took notice, that this was the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer of <hi>Julian</hi> the Apoſtate, making him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf ſport with the complaints of the Chriſtians; That they were beholding to him for the Kingdom of Heaven, which they gained by ſuffering his Perſecutions; But, that it was not for the credit of his doctrine, to bring Chriſtian Princes into the predicament of <hi>Julian</hi> the Apoſtate. And therefore, upon ſecond thoughts, his Leviathan anſwers; That a Subject is bound to obey all that his Soveraign commands in Religion, whether he be Chriſtian or not: Inſomuch that, if he command him to renounce Chriſt, he is bound to do it with his mouth, and ſhall be ſaved, believing in him with his heart, nevertheleſs. This anſwer ſhews the neceſſary iſſue of this Opinion; That he who holds it, if he be as bad as his word, is as neceſſarily an Apoſtate, as <hi>Julian</hi> the Apoſtate. The hope of Salvation, and the Right of Communion with the Church, lyes not only in the heart, which <hi>believes to righteouſneſs,</hi> but in the mouth, which <hi>profeſſeth to Salvation.</hi> The Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion, which is made at our Baptiſm, is a
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:54672:60"/> Condition, without which it cannot be had. It is the taking up of Chriſts Croſs, which the Goſpel requireth. He that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clares himſelf free, in any Caſe whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, to renounce Chriſts, though he hath not done it, hath declared himſelf free of the Bond, which he entred into at his Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptiſm; And as he is no more a Chriſtian to God, no more ſhould he be to the Church. If further he ſay; As the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions firſt maintained, and afterwards recanted, by his late Diſciple at <hi>Cam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bridge,</hi> do import; That there is no dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference between good and bad, before Civil Power that is Soveraign inact it; Then muſt it be ſaid further, that he is properly an Atheiſt. For, if God govern not the World, if he reward not the good, if he puniſh not the bad, though man do not, (pardon me God and all good Chriſtians, if I repeat Blaſphemy, that it may never more be repeated) then is he not God. Particularly, if Civil Power can oblige a man to ſay or ſwear, that which he means not, there remains not that Ground for Civil Society, which the Heathen themſelves (whom nevertheleſs S. <hi>Paul</hi> truly calls <hi>Atheiſts)</hi> maintained. For, what Ground for Civil truſt, if
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:54672:61"/> there be no Law, before Civil truſt, to puniſh the falſifying of it? Let him that conſiders this Conſequence, (neceſſary upon all Opinions, that diſtinguiſh not the matter of Eccleſiaſtical Law, conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent to the State and Conſtitution of the Church, from the Force it hath, to be a Law of the Kingdom, by the Act of the Kingdom) I ſay, let him anſwer in Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, whether thoſe Laws, by which the Rights of the Crown, Uſurped by the See of <hi>Rome,</hi> are Reſumed into it, did proceed upon this Opinion or not. For my part, I remember very well a ſolemn Proteſtation, which one of them makes, that the intent was not, to innovate any thing in Religion, by vindicating the Rights of the Crown. And therefore do infer, that none of them can be under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood, to extinguiſh the Rights of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, concurrent with the Rights of the Crown, in Church-matters, which it doth not diſtinguiſh; Knowing how difficult it is, to diſtinguiſh between them; As not knowing, that ever the ground, upon which they are to be diſtinguiſhed, was delivered till now. But there is an Act of the V. of Q. <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> by which, that abatement in the ſenſe of the <hi>Supremacy
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:54672:61"/> of the Crown in Church-matters,</hi> which had been declared by her <hi>Injunctions,</hi> from the beginning of her Raign, to prevent miſconſtructions, was made a Law of the Land. This Act, becauſe it undertaketh not to limit the <hi>Supremacy,</hi> by diſtinguiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Intereſt of the Crown from the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt of the Church, (for the difficulty of ſatisfying all Conſciences) gives the Subject leave, to declare the ſenſe, in which he takes that Oath; reſerving to himſelf, that which Religion requires a Chriſtian to reſerve, for the Church. Which was not the ſenſe of them that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved no <hi>Catholick Church,</hi> no Viſible Right of it. And, by vertue of this De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claration, it is, that my ſelf have under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taken to declare that limitation, which the <hi>Catholick Church</hi> requireth. For, how many Prelates and Divines of this Church, (King <hi>James</hi> of excellent Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory in particular) have done the ſame? But it is no other, then that which the Canons of K. <hi>James</hi> declare; when they deſcribe this <hi>Supremacy</hi> to be the ſame, which <hi>the Godly Kings of Gods Ancient People,</hi> which <hi>the Roman Emperors of the Primitive times</hi> (before that corruption came in, which we <hi>Proteſt</hi> againſt) did
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:54672:62"/> exerciſe. Here have you the due bounds of this Supremacy, ſetled by Law, upon the true ground of it. For it is manifeſt, that it cannot be derived from the Rights of the Kings of Gods Ancient People alone; Becauſe there could be no <hi>Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Church,</hi> before the calling of the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles. But, the Empire, imbracing the Faith, when the Church was ſetled upon that Faith, and thoſe Laws, that are now as Viſible, as the Laws of <hi>England,</hi> from which preſent Titles are derived, can be Viſible; muſt needs have that Right, from which the Right of all preſent So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veraignties muſt be derived; Becauſe the <hi>Church,</hi> (whoſe Intereſt concurreth with the Intereſt of them all, in the ſame matters) is always <hi>One</hi> and the ſame, and ought ſo to be, from the firſt to the ſecond Coming of Chriſt. And that anſwers any difficulty, that may be objected, when any Law of any Roman Emperor, or other Chriſtian Prince or State, ſeems to <hi>infringe the Canons</hi> of the Church. For, the Protection of the Crown being of ſuch advantage as it is, both for the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larging, and maintaining of Chriſtianity; It is enough, that the Church can conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue <hi>One</hi> and the ſame <hi>Viſible Church,</hi> by
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:54672:62"/> one and the ſame Viſible Laws; Though the force and effect of them be hindred now and then, here and there, by ſome Acts of Secular Power, which, in ſome regards, may advance the Church as much, as they hinder it in others. It was neceſſary for the Crown, under <hi>Henry</hi> the VIII, to vindicate the Supremacy from the pretenſe of the Popes Secular Power; which had been on foot divers Ages afore. And therefore, not to have to do with him, that pretended to aſſoil the <hi>Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects</hi> of Princes, whom he ſhould excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municate, of their <hi>Allegiance,</hi> till they might owne him, upon terms, conſiſtent with the Protection they owe their Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple. And it was ſtill more neceſſary, under <hi>Edward</hi> the VI. when the Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation was inacted; which, they knew well enough, that the Pope would not en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure. But, when the Right of the Crown in Church-matters is declared by Law, to be the ſame, which <hi>the Kings of Gods Ancient People,</hi> and the <hi>firſt Chriſtian Emperors</hi> did exerciſe, the ground of that Intereſt, and the bounds of that Intereſt, which the Church muſt challenge, if it will continue a Church, are declared to be the ſame, which the Faith and the Laws
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:54672:63"/> of the Whole Church from the beginning do allow.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="23" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. XXIII. Of reſtoring and reforming the Juriſdicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the Crown, and of the Church, in Eccleſiaſtical Cauſes.</head>
               <p>ANd this makes the Reformation of our Eccleſiaſtical Laws as eaſie, as it is viſibly the cure of all diſtempers in Religion among us. It is in brief this; That the Juriſdiction, which may by this means appear to the Kingdom, to be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veſted in the Church by Gods Law, be, by a Law of the Kingdom, reſtored to the Clergy; To the <hi>Biſhops</hi> in chief, then, to the <hi>Chapters of their Cathedrals,</hi> and to their <hi>Archdeacons;</hi> (And to theſe, not without the Aſſiſtance of the <hi>Principal Clergie,</hi> of their Reſpective Juriſdictions) the Judges of the Eccleſiaſtical Courts continuing the Kings Judges, as they are now by Law; to manage the Intereſt of the Crown, (in all the Rights thereof, reſumed into the Crown, by the Acts of Supremacy) according to the Roman
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:54672:63"/> Laws, in thoſe Ages of Chriſtendom, which paſſed before the Uſurpation of the See of <hi>Rome</hi> had taken place. If it be ſaid; That it is not Viſible, when thoſe Uſurpations took place; I ſhall allow all the time, which that Code of the Canons contains, that Pope <hi>Adrian</hi> ſent to <hi>Charles</hi> the Great; In whoſe time, there can be no pretenſe of Uſurpation, upon the Temporalties of Princes, by the See of <hi>Rome.</hi> This Code is yet read, under the Name of <hi>Codex Canonum Eccleſiae Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manae.</hi> I have commended the Juſtice and Wiſdom of that Commiſſion, which was deſigned under <hi>Henry</hi> the VIII, and <hi>Edward</hi> the VI, for the <hi>qualities of Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons</hi> limited by it. But I do not think it poſſible for any Commiſſion, to <hi>Reform the Alterations</hi> introduced by the Popes Canon Law, after that time, in one Kings Raign, with that circumſpection which is requiſite. The Juriſdiction which the Church challenges, by Gods Law, can not be diſtinctly ſtated, with more ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction to all Intereſts, preſerving that of Religion, then by a Commiſſion ſo qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lified. The Intereſt of the Kingdom, in preſerving the ſtudy of the Roman Laws, hath always been thought conſiderable.
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:54672:64"/> But how ſhall the ſtudy of them be main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained, if the <hi>Authority</hi> of them be not maintained? Or how ſhall that Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity be maintained, but by <hi>adopting</hi> them into the Law of the Kingdom, in matters neceſſary to be provided for by Law, but not provided for, by the native Law of the Kingdom? Or what proviſion can there he, by the native Law of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, for thoſe Cauſes, which, for ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny hundred years before the Reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, the Popes Canon Law had ſenten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced, by the Authority of the Kingdom? There is an <hi>Intereſt of Religion in Matri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monial Cauſes,</hi> in <hi>Teſtamentary Cauſes,</hi> in Cauſes ariſing upon <hi>Elections of Corporate Clergie,</hi> in Cauſes of <hi>Diſpenſation in Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nons,</hi> in Cauſes of <hi>Tithes,</hi> in divers ſorts of Cauſes, beſides thoſe which the Power of the Keys, in the Diſcipline of the People, and the Correction of Inferior Clergy occaſioneth. Let me not ſay, that it were <hi>Barbarous,</hi> for a flouriſhing Kingdom, in a flouriſhing Age, for all other Learning, to reduce the Tryal of them, to the <hi>Arbitrary Verdicts of Juries;</hi> (Who can never underſtand the Grounds, upon which the matter of Fact is to be ſtated) when I can ſo clearly ſay, that
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:54672:64" rendition="simple:additions"/> there can be nothing more like to meer Tyranny, then <hi>Arbitrary Juſtice;</hi> nor Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice more Arbitrary, then, where it is manifeſt, that there can have been no other Law provided, becauſe the Canon Law hath been hitherto uſed. As for thoſe <hi>Cauſes,</hi> which are <hi>proper to the Church,</hi> as riſing from the <hi>Conſtitution</hi> of it; how can it ſtand with Religion, and Reformation in Religion, which we pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend, to try them otherwiſe, then by thoſe, which, the Kingdom ſhall be ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied, by ſuch a Commiſſion, that they are by Gods Law capable of Authority to do it? And the Intereſt of the Crown, and of the Subjects, which it is bound to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tect, ſhall be ſecured, when proviſion is made, by adopting the Roman Laws, for managing the Rights of the Crown, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumed by the Act of Supremacy, within thoſe Bounds, which the Roman Laws maintained, before the Uſurpation of the See of <hi>Rome.</hi> It cannot be denied, that <hi>the Popes Canon Law</hi> (which the Law of the Land hath already adopted, ſo far as it contradicteth not the Law of the Land) provideth for many things, not provided for by the <hi>Primitive Canons,</hi> within the Compaſs of the Roman Laws. And it
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:54672:65"/> would be too much raſhneſs, <hi>to recal that Adoption,</hi> and to leave ſo much matter to arbitrary Juſtice, rather then retain a Proviſion, which the Law and Religion profeſſed by the Kingdom owns not the Original of, though it owne the matter it hath adopted. For, whatſoever ſhall prove, by time and tryal, to hinder the <hi>Reformation,</hi> which we pretend thus to ground, and thus to bound, the faults that ſhall be found by experience muſt open the way of mending it, becauſe the Cure muſt be as particular, as the diſeaſe is. And upon theſe Terms, it can be no diſhonour to the Kingdom, and to the Reformation which it profeſſeth, to uſe the Canon Law which it adopteth, till time ſhew the way of amending thoſe par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulars, which, time ſhall ſhew, that the Reformation pretended requires to be changed. For inſtance, we know, that ſince <hi>Henry</hi> VIII. it is not the cuſtom to take any degree in Canon Law; Not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding the Law of the Land ado<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pteth the Canon Law. And, according<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly we all know, that Graduates in the Civil Law of the Romans are privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged, by the Eccleſiaſtical Law of the Kingdom. I would fain have any of
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:54672:65"/> them, that would wear the Face, and the Conſcience of a good Chriſtian, and a good Engliſh man both; Give me a rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable Account of theſe their Tenures, waving that which I here ſet forth for them; whom they will think too bold with their Freehold for it. For my part, who am no mans foe, but my own, in publiſhing my Opinion thus freely, upon this Exigent; I think I do good ſervice to them, with my Country, to ſet forth this Account, why and how the Roman Laws deſerve to be adopted into the Laws of the Kingdom; Namely, that the Popes Canon Law, which is already adopted, may be limited within thoſe Bounds, with the Roman Laws; (And <hi>by conſequence, the Primitive Canons of the Church,</hi> which the Roman Laws acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge and inforce) do either preſcribe or allow. I would make a further Offer, of introducing the Roman Laws, both into the <hi>Study</hi> of the Law of the Land, and into <hi>Authority</hi> in our Courts of <hi>Equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty;</hi> And of reconciling, thereby, the Croſs-Intereſts of the Profeſſions, upon competence of Juriſdictions. But, though I muſt needs have that Opinion my ſelf, which, I can ſee nothing againſt, ſeeing
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:54672:66"/> much for it; yet I will trouble no man with an Opinion, which neither my Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion obliges me, nor my ſkill inables me to make out. It ſhall be enough for me to obſerve, that they ſhall deſerve to be counted <hi>Profeſſors of the Roman Laws,</hi> that are truſted to miniſter the Canon Laws, by thoſe Bounds, which the Roman Laws allow. As for the Concurrence of that Juriſdiction which is proper to the Clergy, by Gods Law, and that which is reſumed by the Crown, to be <hi>miniſtred by the Profeſſors of the Roman Laws;</hi> I do acknowledge it cannot be ended, but by Appeals; The iſſue whereof, whither it ought to reſort, when it is time to ſay, it will be then time to ſay alſo, how theſe Intereſts are reconcileable. In the mean time, Epiſcopacy being owned by the Law of the Kingdom, and the Law of God both, to be that which the whole Church, from the beginning acknowledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth; I think I do my Country, and the Church of God in it no diſſervice, to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe a plaiſter large enough for the Sore of it, that ſhall come within the bounds which I have propoſed. For, the Chapters of Cathedral Churches are, by their <hi>Birth-right, Counſellors</hi> to the Biſhops,
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:54672:66"/> and <hi>Aſſiſtants,</hi> in his whole Office; The <hi>Archdeacon his Miniſter,</hi> and principal Commiſſary. Thoſe, by the Rule firſt ſet on foot by the Apoſtles, and obſerved always by the Church, of planting Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thedral Churches in Cities, and making the Churches planted in Cities Cathedral Churches, for the Government of all Chriſtendom within the Territories of thoſe Cities. This being, by his <hi>Order, Miniſterial</hi> to them, as well as to the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop, when both have part in the ſame Office. And here I place the hinge, up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on which I hang the Reconcilement of <hi>the preſumed Intereſt of the Presbyterians,</hi> with the true Intereſt of the Clergy; Suppoſing the Conference propoſed to have taken effect, and produced a <hi>Requeſt</hi> of both Parties, to the <hi>Legiſlative Power of the Kingdom,</hi> to make a Law of thoſe particulars, upon which they are <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> come to agreement, to be received, and to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe their Miniſtry. For, the Office of the Clergy being ſeparated from the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt of the Crown, by an Act of the Kingdom; And the Profeſſors of the Roman Laws truſted to manage this In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt, in behalf of the Subject; (Only aſſiſting the Clergy, in that part of the
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:54672:67"/> Juriſdiction proper to the Church, which will concern the Intereſt of Subjects, as Members of the Church, as well as the Office of the Clergy) What ſhall hinder them, the Preſbyterians, as well as the reſt of the Clergy, to exerciſe the Zeal, which they have always profeſſed, to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the Reforming of the converſation of the People, in aſſiſting that Diſcipline, as well over the <hi>Inſerior Clergie as the People,</hi> which the <hi>Chapters of Cathedral Churches,</hi> and the <hi>Archdeacons</hi> ſhall, by the Biſhop and under the Biſhop, be truſted with? For what need all this hinder the <hi>Preroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive</hi> of the Biſhops <hi>Negative</hi> Vote; when as there will be more to do under him, then hands will be found for, reſerving to him thoſe cauſes, which he would chuſe to reſerve? For, that will be found no more then requiſite, to preſerve his <hi>Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogative, that nothing be done without him;</hi> when nothing is done without him, but that which he ſhall chuſe to be eaſed in. He that knows what the <hi>Hierarchy</hi> ſignifies, muſt needs underſtand, that the ſame means, which preſerved the <hi>Whole Church in <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity,</hi> ſo far and wide for place, ſo long for time, as Unity prevailed in the Church, and Chriſtianity with it and by
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:54672:67"/> it, knows that the ſame muſt be uſed, to preſerve Unity in the <hi>Church of this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>om;</hi> The Queſtion being, how to Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form it ſo, that it may continue a Member of the Whole.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="24" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. XXIV. Some Principal Canons to be reſtored, in our preſent State.</head>
               <p>FOr, let no man think, that any Law can be effectual to this purpoſe, till the Caſe be ſtated, which the Law is pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided for. We are in the State of Schiſm, in ſpite of our teeth: Though we are to clear our ſelves of the crime of Schiſm, upon the Terms ſetled; which cannot clear us, if it be poſſible, that any other ſhould clear us. King <hi>Henry</hi> the VIII. had reaſon to declare, that he and his Kingdom ſhould have nothing to do with the Pope, that Excommunicated him for his Divorce; So many Popes having diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charged the Subjects of Princes Excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municate, of their Allegiance. But, to make good the Proteſtation, that he in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended no further change in Religion; I
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:54672:68"/> need not ſay what he did, to give ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding Popes occaſion to recal the folly of that Pope, which Excommunicated him, by a timely Reconcilement. In the mean time, the way to preſerve the Kingdom in Peace was, to have nothing to do with the See of <hi>Rome.</hi> But, had he been ſo well adviſed, as to have main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained his Divorce upon the terms which I plead for; What could the Pope have ſaid to that Code of Canons, which Pope <hi>Adrian</hi> the I. ſent to <hi>Charles</hi> the Great; which I would have this Church to owne? For it concludes, with a Synod of the Province of <hi>Rome,</hi> under Pope <hi>Gregory</hi> the II. which pronounces <hi>Anathema,</hi> to whoſoever ſhall marry his deceaſed Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers Wife. Let <hi>Julius</hi> II. Pope, that diſpenſed with <hi>Henry</hi> the VIII. and his Marriage with the Lady <hi>Katherine</hi> of <hi>Spain,</hi> have bethought himſelf, how to come clear of this <hi>Anathema;</hi> the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority of the See of <hi>Rome</hi> being intire. For K. <hi>Henry</hi> the VIII. or at leaſt for his Kingdom, it was and is enough, that, ſo long as he owned the Authority of that See, he muſt needs be troubled in conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence at that Marriage, by which he muſt needs incur it, preferring the former Act
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:54672:68"/> of a Council under <hi>Gregory</hi> the II. Pope, before a Bull of <hi>Julius</hi> the II. Pope, diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſing in an <hi>Anathema</hi> of the ſaid Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil. For, as the Primitive Canons are to be preferred, in Church-Law, before the looſneſs of ſucceeding Ages, being ſtill further from the Apoſtles; So the Act of the Council, under the Regular Power of the Pope, is to be preferred before a Bull; which now paſſeth without the Conſiſtory, as the Popes perſonal Act, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the unlimited abſolute Power of the Pope hath taken place. As for King <hi>Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward</hi> the VI. profeſſing the Reformation, and proteſting it as he did; ſo that the See of <hi>Rome</hi> could have no pretenſe of correſpendence, without owning it them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves; there ſucceeds the neceſſity of a State of Schiſm, upon the Excommunica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion following; The Crime of Schiſm re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maining on that ſide that Excommuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cates, for vindicating and reſtoring the Faith and the Laws of the Whole Church. This being the ſtate of our Caſe: and the Laws of the Whole Church, and the Faith thereof, neceſſary to the Title, that muſt juſtifie Reformation without the Conſent of the Whole; Is it not manifeſt, to all Underſtandings, that the Law, by which
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:54672:69"/> this State is to be Governed, muſt be ſuch a Proviſion, as the Laws of the Whole Church inable a part of it to make for it ſelf, in the Caſe? And therefore, we muſt affirm, as many of us as would have no ſhare in the Schiſm, as to God; being thus ſecured, that, to the Church, we are not chargeable with it; That there is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to hinder ſuch a Proviſion, but the miſunderſtanding of them: And that we ſee not, what the Conſequence of our own Profeſſion requires. A reaſon that preſſes me ſo hard, that I do willingly expoſe my ſelf to the diſpleaſure of all, that ſhall find themſelves diſguſted, with this freedom; Only to give my ſelf the ſatisfaction of publiſhing it, whatſoever diſpleaſure it procure me; As being ſatisfied, that there is no other cure for our preſent diſtempers. For in the firſt place, it muſt be ſaid, that it is in vain to talk of Regular Government, by the Canons of the Church, without reſtoring the liberty of Synods, to the reſpective Provinces. Not as if the Church needed any abatement, in the Act of <hi>Henry</hi> the VIII., which for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biddeth making, and perhaps adviſing of Canons to be made, without the Aſſent of the Crown. But becauſe the World
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:54672:69"/> knows, it was the Uſurped Legatine Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, that had brought Synods to nothing, by Uſurping upon the Ordinary. And therefore, it is but Juſtice in the Crown, finding the Right of Synods, the Subjects thereof, Uſurped by the See of <hi>Rome;</hi> to reſtore it to the Subjects, upon whom the Uſurpation had been made; The Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>premacy of the Crown being ſufficiently provided for, by the ſaid Act: And, the force of all Acts of Synods depending up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Legiſlative Power of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom. In the next place, it is to no pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, to talk of Reformation in the Church, unto Regular Government, without reſtoring the Liberty of chuſing Biſhops, and the Priviledge of injoying them, to the Synods, Clergy and People of each Dioceſe. I ſay not, depriving the Crown of the due Intereſt of a Nega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive, to any Perſon to be promoted a Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop, in any inſtance of his Promotion. God forbid it ſhould come into my thought. But, the Supremacy being ſo provided for, ſo evident is the Right of the Synods, Clergy and People, in the making of thoſe, of whom they conſiſt, and by whom they are to be governed, that I need mark no other Reaſon, for
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:54672:70"/> the neglect of Epiſcopacy, but the neglect of it; For the neglect of Cathedral Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, but the neglect, &amp; alienation of their Office, under and with their Biſhops. This for certain, had not the See of <hi>Rome</hi> intro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced ſo much diſorder, in the creating of Biſhops, that we have not yet cured it, we ſhould have heard of it with both ears, from their Advocates. And, if I may cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit a perſon of unqueſtionable credit, his late Majeſty was ſo convinced hereof, when he was at <hi>Oxford,</hi> that he offered to part with it, if a way were ſhewed how to do it. As for the tranſlating of Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops; which done, as it is, of courſe, muſt needs render the Office unfruitful to their People; As no man can deny, that there ought to be a courſe, for diſpenſing in the Canon, for publick good; So can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not this pretenſe of publick good come to effect, unleſs it be maintained by the Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice of Synods, to whom the State of the Church vindicates the Right of it. That which I ſaid afore, of Appeals, belongs to this place. For, what Law can provide, that, in Cauſes reſerved to the Biſhop, parties ſhall reſt content always with his ſentence? Or whether can Eccleſiaſtical Cauſes reſort, from him, but to the Synod
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:54672:70"/> of the Province? Again, what Chriſtian Kingdom could ever prevent a mixture of Cauſes; That is, a concurrence of In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt, between the Soveraign Power, and the Office of the Church? Or what danger can be imaginable, to this Crown, in doing Right to the Church; Having only its own Subjects to deal with? Or what can be more ready, to receive Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peals of this Nature, then a Commiſſion of Judges, delegate, as well by the Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nods as by the Crown, for the expedition of ſuch Cauſes, in which, the pretenſe of the Subject, as well as the Intereſt of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, may be concerned? As for matter of Faith; Having admitted all that hath been decreed within the time of the ſix truly General Councils; I dare ſay, that there is nothing, that the See of <hi>Rome</hi> can charge upon the Socinians, or Anaba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptiſts, or any Sect of our Fanaticks, that is not condemned, in the Arians, Pelagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, or other Sects, which the Whole Church hath condemned, during that time. So that there can be no cauſe, why Chriſtianity ſhould not be maintained, by the Reformation, during this State of Schiſm, but neglecting the true conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence of that which we our ſelves pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="25" type="chapter">
               <pb n="134" facs="tcp:54672:71"/>
               <head>CHAP. XXV. Two Laws more, neceſſary to the Reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Church.</head>
               <p>THeſe are the principal points, in the Canons of the Whole Church, which the Profeſſion of Reforming the Church obliges us to reſtore. There are two points more, the one concerning the People, the other the Inferior Clergy; which, till they be reſtored, our Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation cannot be that which it pretend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth. That all, who ſhall be convicted in Law, of capital or infamous Crimes, ſtand Excommunicate <hi>ipſo facto,</hi> and if Execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion paſs, be deprived of Chriſtian Burial, unleſs they reconcile themſelves to the Church; Unleſs the Law make this good, how ſhould the Kingdom be counted a Chriſtian Kingdom? For, if ſcandalous Crimes, that are notorious, be allowed Communion with the Church, how can it be a Church? Conviction, which is the Act of the Law, making the Crime notorious, how can Chriſtianity be protected, and the Church not able to renounce them
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:54672:71"/> that renounce it by their deeds? The in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe of ſin ſo flagrant in this Nation, ſince the War began, makes the neceſſity of this Law flagrant. I was ſpeaking of the Leviathan, that Monſter of a Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an, that with one Book, (allowed by the Act of Oblivion, becauſe the Doctrine was not damned, when the Perſon was pardoned) hath introduced that Deluge of Atheiſm and Prophaneneſs, which we are ready to be drowned with. Let Publick Juſtice have the convicting of the Blaſphemies which he hath taught, if the Church be not in Caſe to bear the envy of ſuch a truſt. But to account for ſuch a crime, by a pecuniary mulct, is to ſell our Chriſtianity, at the price, at which it is defied. Unleſs Infamy follow, and Excommunication, to bring it on, fare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wel Chriſtianity, which compoundeth with Apoſtaſie. The Father of the Sect thinks, I believe, that he hath as good Right to the Communion, as the reſt of His Majeſties Subjects; Who, though he ſhould profeſs Penitence for his crime, could not be believed; having given the World warning, that he may be bound to ſay, and to ſwear, that which he doth not believe. What courſe but this,
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:54672:72"/> to ſuppreſs the Vanity of committing Mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, under the name of a Duel? For, in all Common-wealths, where mens memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry is not liable to Infamy, ſin is not out of countenance. In that which is Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian, what can be infamous, if to forfeit Communion with the Church be not? As for Adultery, what puniſhment hath this Kingdom left for it? Or how ſhall it be counted a Chriſtian Kingdom, having none? Be the tryal of it, as Civil Intereſt ſhall require. If it paſs without Excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munication, though the Law of the Land lay no hold on it, what can clear the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of the expectation of Gods ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance? By conſequence hereof, they that are convicted of Simony in Civil Juſtice, muſt remain <hi>Irregular,</hi> to the Church; That is, though their Ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion can never be void, yet their perſons muſt remain incapable of any truſt, which their Clergy ſhould make them capable of. And why ſhould not the Priviledge of their Clergy ceaſe, and they remain Excommunicate for ſuch a Crime? The other Law, concerning the Clergy, is the confining of every one to one Dioceſe; Which is but the Reſtoring of that Order, which the See of <hi>Rome</hi> had diſordered,
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:54672:72"/> on purpoſe to ingage in the diſorders of it, all that they obliged by ſuch Privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges. For, the Priviledges reſerved to the Crown, Nobility, and Biſhops, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by the abuſe is but diſplaced, will not be conſiderable, in compariſon with the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation which it hindreth. It ſeems ſtrange to thoſe, that find themſelves In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſted, that two Benefices with Cure ſhould be allowed in one Dioceſe, not in ſeveral Dioceſes, though at leſs diſtance. But the Law cannot be underſtood to allow all that it forbids not; Becauſe there may be Reaſon, why the Publick good will not allow the forbidding of that, which is left to the Conſcience of particular perſons. Were all Benefices reſtored to that Proviſion, which the Cures might require, perhaps Priviledges of Pluralities might be extinguiſhed. In the mean time, is it not enough, that, whatſoever the Quality be, the Office of Prieſt and Deacon is relative to their Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpective Biſhops? that no man can be an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwerable to one Biſhop for a Charge, in which he is anſwerable to another for the ſame? Which if it hold not in one and the ſame Dioceſe, the Reaſon of the dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference is both ſufficient and evident.
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:54672:73"/> Always, the Ground being laid, that the Reformation of the Church is to be Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led by the Canons of the Primitive Church; there can be no more queſtion in this, then is in any thing, where the Primitive Inſtitution, is as Viſible, as the decay and abuſe. But this will princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pally concern Archdeacons, and the Dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nified Clergy, which are to bear a part in the Biſhops Office. For how ſhould they be charged with that, which they are not charged to execute?</p>
            </div>
            <div n="26" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. XXVI. Of Forbearance, due or not due, in two Inſtances.</head>
               <p>I Have propoſed a Conference, I have determined, that all is to be tryed by the agreement of the Catholick Church; But if we ſtay till the Parties agree to that, there muſt be no Conference. What have we to overcome this difficulty with? Conſidering, how the neceſſity of loſing all Religion preſſes all Parties, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidering how ſlight the pretenſes of diſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction at the Act of Uniformity are;
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:54672:73"/> though I cannot depart from my claim, that the Reformation cannot duely be made, but by and to that Pattern; yet I ſee it may be laid aſide in the Tryal, not ſuppoſing that the Will of God is declared by it. But, if the advantage be not allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, which the conſent of Chriſtendom from the beginning hath, in the judgment of common Reaſon, above any Opinion of this time, or any Party pretending Reformation; what courſe can they hold, that have not reaſonable Creatures to deal with? For how can they be count<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed reaſonable, that prefer their own Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, before the Reaſon of Chriſtendom? Or how ſhall they diſtinguiſh their <hi>pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate Spirits,</hi> from the Enthuſiaſms of Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naticks, that inſiſt upon thoſe Interpreta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and Conſequences of Scripture, which, had any man ſeen before them, the Church had never been as it hath been? In fine, the Caſe being ſtated, I ſee no cauſe, to apprehend any obſtinacy in the Parties, to prefer any faction, or partiality, before Reaſon ſo manifeſted, and ſo concerning the common Chriſtia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity. I will inſiſt upon two Inſtances. All the World knows, that one of the abuſes, which made the neceſſity of Reformation
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:54672:74"/> moſt appear, was that of private Maſſes; where the Euchariſt was celebrated, and the people did not communicate. It is as well known, that the Reformation ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to <hi>Calvin</hi> contents it ſelf with four Communions a year; but no Aſſembly without Preaching. The Church of <hi>England</hi> hath aimed at the Communion every Lords-day and Holy-day; at Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons, as frequent as can be had, ſo as to maintain the reverence due to Religion, to Preaching, and to the Church. What queſtion can there be in Religion, that the Euchariſt is the principal Office of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious Aſſemblies? What pretenſe of Reformation, in reſtoring Preaching, by ſilencing the Euchariſt? It will be ſaid, that there is fear of prophaning ſo Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious an Office. But where is Reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, if it make not the people fit for it? The Papiſts ſay; Private Maſſes are not commanded; they would have the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple communicate, and incourage them to it. But what do they do to bring them to it? Surely more then they do, that ſilence the Euchariſt for the Sermon; That are not contented, till ſo much Preaching be commanded, that they know the Euchariſt muſt be ſilenced.
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:54672:74"/> Let them think what abilities are requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſite, to maintain ſo frequent Preaching, that there ſhall be no time for the Eucha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſt; Let them think of the Scandals, that muſt needs fall out, for want of due abilities; and they will find cauſe, I doubt not, to prefer the Whole Church, before a late Party: and abate the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon, to reſtore the Euchariſt. Eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally, ſeeing the Law of this Land muſt be changed, to bear out what others have done; though it is manifeſt, they never gave any reaſon for it. They will ſee cauſe to think, that the beſt Preaching is that which may fit the people for the Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chariſt; by underſtanding the Covenant of Baptiſm, and the importance of daily renewing and reſtoring it, by Communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in the Euchariſt. The other Inſtance ſhall be the Pſalms; that are ſung in Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thedral Churches, but allowed to be read where there is not company to ſing them. For it is plain enough, what excuſes are made, and what indeavours uſed, to ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence this part of Gods Service: and to turn the Pſalms; which this Church, with the Whole Church, appointeth for devo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; into Leſſons of Inſtruction only. Hence all the Plea againſt the Old Tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:54672:75"/> with points; all the indeavors to crowd in the Pſalms in Rhime, inſtead of the Pſalter, and all uſe which the Church hath always made of it. But, did not partiality and faction prevail over that Reaſon, which all Chriſtendom be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Reformation hath always owned, there could be no queſtion of uſing the Pſalter of <hi>David,</hi> for an Inſtrument to tune the devotion of Chriſtian people, by; transforming the expreſſions of <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid</hi> unto our Lord Chriſt, in the firſt place; and, according to the Figure of Chriſt, to the Whole Church firſt, and then to every particular member of it. He that hath learnt this from the Whole Church, will never think it reaſon, to put this part of Gods Service to ſilence, who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever they be, that deſire or deſing it. He will rather indeavour, to reduce the ſinging of them into Pariſh Churches; being evidently ſo much eaſier, then the ſinging of the Pſalms in Rhime. But how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever, retain the reading of them by Antiphones, and not <hi>quench the Spirit</hi> of God, which breatheth forth that transfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation whereof I ſpake. Having thus inſtanced, I will not propoſe the Ground, upon which I maintain, that all Reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:54672:75"/> is to proceed, for the condition of the Conference which I propoſe. I will think it a point of that <hi>Forbearance,</hi> which S. <hi>Paul</hi> commandeth the Romans, not to inſiſt upon thoſe terms, which the Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of the Apoſtles doth inforce. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe I ſee him, not inſiſt upon the Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of an Apoſtle, with them; but, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving infallibly proved his ground, of Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtification by Faith alone, forbear the conſequence of it; charging the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans, to hold that indifferent, whatſoever his Authority, ſo grounded, declareth ſuch; yet charging them to forbear thoſe, that, for all his Authority and Reaſons, underſtood it not. For, I believe verily, that his reaſon and mine is the very ſame; Namely, to keep both Parties in the Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of one Church, a Member of the Whole; Hoping that, by Gods bleſſing, upon the advantages, which the commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nication of the Faithful one with another, and with their Clergy affordeth, thoſe that are now moſt keenly ſet againſt theſe little things, that are excepted at in the Act of Uniformity, may, by that condeſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, which the Intereſt of Chriſtianity obliges all Parties to, come to underſtand the only Principle of Reformation and
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:54672:76"/> Unity both; The Authority of the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholick Church, in all things not determi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by Gods Law, which is only the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel under this time of Chriſtianity. And I ſet before them, to that purpoſe, the example of the Jews; Who, for all the Forbearance commanded by S. <hi>Paul,</hi> ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving ſtopped their ears, at all his charms; with the Unity of the Church, have for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feited the Faith, hitherto irrecoverably. For, being fully perſwaded, that with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out this Principle, it is not poſſible, either for this Church, or for any part of the Reformation, long to ſubſiſt; Can I fear any leſs, then the utter loſs of Religion, for my deareſt Country, and for the dearer Church of God in it?</p>
            </div>
            <div n="27" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. XXVII. How Recuſants may, or may not be puniſhed as Idolaters.</head>
               <p>IT remains that I ſay, what Penalties this Poſition makes competent to thoſe, that refuſe the Reformation thus limited. A thing eaſie for me to do, having decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red the Ground, upon which the refuſing
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:54672:76"/> of Chriſtianity is puniſhable; Which the Reformation, hitherto, hath not been able to do. The Poſition of puniſhing Hereticks capitally is generally decryed by them; And yet we ſee <hi>Servetus</hi> and <hi>Gentilis</hi> put to death, at <hi>Geneva</hi> and <hi>Bern;</hi> and others elſewhere. If, becauſe ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenced for Hereticks by them that put them to death; Why ſhould not the Powers that adhere to the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> execute the Sentence thereof, upon thoſe whom they pronounce Hereticks? If, becauſe ſo ſentenced by the Primitive Church, in which we both agree; Why owne we not the Primitive Church in the reſt, as well as in that? If, becauſe they that gave the Sentence are compe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent Judges in Religion; What remains, but that contrary Sentences be executed by the Sword, and Religion be no other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe judged? But, ſuppoſing Religion, and the Church, and the ſenſe of the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture Viſible, ſo far as the preſerving of Unity requires; Chriſtian Powers muſt both protect Subjects in their Civil, as well as natural being, though not true Chriſtians; and yet puniſh them for not being true Chriſtians. Only, if they pretend freedom from Allegiance, by
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:54672:77"/> Chriſtianity, (and we know it is falſe Chriſtianity that ſo pretends) there will be alſo fit time to declare, why they may be capitally puniſhed. But thoſe who declare the Pope Antichriſt, and the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts Idolaters in the exerciſe of their Religion, have not declared, what Penal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty is competent to their Idolatry. And yet, till that be cleared, we are in the clouds. This difficulty, I find my ſelf able to look in the face, without ever diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puting, whether the Papiſts, by their Religion, are bound to commit Idolatry, or not. The Law of <hi>Moſes,</hi> indeed, ſeems to ſhew, that, by the Law of Nature, Idolaters may be put to death, for their Idolatry. For, there is no appearance, that the Law of God would have injoyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed that, which the Law of Nature allows not. But the Caſe is otherwiſe under Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianity, then under the Law of <hi>Moſes.</hi> The people of <hi>Iſrael</hi> held the Land of Promiſe, upon Condition, not to ſuffer any other God to be worſhipped within the Bounds of it, but the true God, that gave it them upon thoſe terms. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they committed a forfeit, whenſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever they ſuffered Idolatry in it. But the Goſpel was preached to the Roman
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:54672:77"/> Empire, conſiſting of two Religions, of Jews and Gentiles; Maintaining the State of the World upon the ſame terms which it found; ſaving that, which, if they imbraced the Faith, they muſt voluntari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly change. When therefore the Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raign Power of the Empire came to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs the Faith; (and thereupon, an obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation to maintain and propagate it, by all means, which the Right of Soveraign Power furniſhes) they could not anſwer God, for the right uſe of their Power, uſing any other means, then the Intereſt of Chriſtianity allows. They might have confiſcated Eſtates, where they might have taken away lives; But that would have made the meekneſs, which Chriſtianity pretendeth, to appear that Hypocriſie of our Sects; Who are always humble, always for Toleration, till they get the Power into their own hands. To ſhut up the Temples of Idols, and to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bid Sacrifices, was no more then to ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs that Sacriledge, which the light and Law of Nature diſcovereth. If any of the Imperial Laws make it death to ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice; it is to be underſtood, upon preſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ption, that thoſe Sacrifices were Inquiries into the life of the Prince, or of their
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:54672:78"/> enemies. To conſtrain them to be Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians by Penalties, had been to make them counterfeit Chriſtians. Beſides, the Nations that bordered upon the Empire were all Idolaters; And Chriſtianity pretended to convert them, as well as the Empire. If the Emperors had puniſhed their Subjects, being Gentiles, for being Idolaters, muſt not the Neighbour Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions have perſecuted the Chriſtians, their Subjects, for being Chriſtians? The reaſon of the difference between the Law and the Goſpel, in this behalf, is that which S. <hi>Auſtin</hi> giveth, why the Law of <hi>Moſes</hi> voids the Marriages of Jews with Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles; Whereas S. <hi>Paul</hi> adviſes thoſe that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ned Chriſtians, being married to Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laters, to continue in Wedlock with them, deſiring it. S. <hi>Auſtins</hi> reaſon is this; That the Law, tendring only temporal promiſes expreſly, (which Gentiles as well as Jews, might &amp; did injoy in this world) thought it too hard a temptation, to truſt a Jew in Wedlock with a Gentile; by wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>, he might be in danger to be ſedu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced, to proſperous Idolatry. Whereas Chriſtianity, upon the advantage of the world to come, aſſured by the Preaching of our Lord and his Apoſtles, challengeth
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:54672:78"/> all other Religions, as unable to reſiſt it, when it is performed as well as profeſſed. So that to ſuffer Idolaters, in converſing with Chriſtians, was but the allowing of opportunity, for the converting of Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters. I think I have cauſe to make this an argument <hi>ad hominem,</hi> that our Secta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries themſelves cannot, nor do require the Penalty of Idolatry, by <hi>Moſes</hi> Law, upon Papiſts. They that remember the time, when the late Q. Mother of Royal memory came over, do know, what infuſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons the Pulpits then made, into the minds of the people, of the curſe of God hang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing upon the Nation, for His Majeſties Marriage. The pretenſe was wholly, upon the Law of <hi>Moſes;</hi> Which, as I have ſhewed, is not to the purpoſe among Chriſtians. But indeed, thoſe prognoſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cations were no other, then the Prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies of the Devils Oracles, among the Gentiles; Foretelling the miſchiefs, which they intended or deſired to do themſelves. This being a ſufficient rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, why the ſame pretenſe is not now on foot, becauſe it cannot be plauſible, after ſo dear experience of the miſchief it tends to; I think I am to take advantage of it, in behalf of Truth and Juſtice; That
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:54672:79"/> no Party can pretend, the Penalty of <hi>Moſes</hi> Law to lye, in our Caſe; Suppoſing, not granting the Papiſts to be Idolaters, according to <hi>Moſes</hi> Law. And is not the Caſe the ſame, between the Reformation and the See of <hi>Rome?</hi> At leaſt it is ſo, if the Reformation be that which it pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendeth. For then, the advantage muſt needs be ſo Viſible, that to allow conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation between the Profeſſions that are at ſuch diſtance, is but to allow the means of bringing all Popiſh Recuſants to Church; when the Reformation is that, which it pretendeth. I grant that it falls out to be otherwiſe, in our experience. For, they that are converted to the See of <hi>Rome,</hi> at this time, are converted by this miſcarri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age, that they venture themſelves into diſpute with thoſe, which they are not able to deal with. But the miſcarriage is accidental; Becauſe of the Diviſions within our ſelves; ariſing from hence, that our Reformation owneth not the Bounds which it requireth. For, by this means, the Clergy of this Church is in contempt with their Flock; and private Chriſtians venture themſelves into diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pute with Recuſants, (that is, with their Prieſts) without truſting their Paſtors,
<pb n="151" facs="tcp:54672:79" rendition="simple:additions"/> or acquainting them with what they do. Which if they did do, in due time, ſuch occaſions would be opportunities of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducing Recuſants to Church. Beſides, to purſue the Idolatry of the See of <hi>Rome,</hi> (ſuppoſing, not granting that ſo it is) what would it be, but to draw the Sword on both ſides, to try the quarrel of Religion with? And therefore Soveraign Powers cannot give God account, that they uſe the Right he gives them over Papiſts their Subjects, purſuing them to the Penalty of <hi>Moſes</hi> Law, as Idolaters. There is ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther reaſon for the ſame, that appears now and then, in the diſputes of them, that maintain the Religion of the See of <hi>Rome</hi> to be Idolaters. For, they have many times found themſelves obliged to grant, that their Idolatry is another kind of Idolatry, then that which is prohibited, and puniſhed with death, by the Law of <hi>Moſes.</hi> And if ſo, it muſt be another kind of Penalty, that belongs to it. Now I ſuppoſe S. <hi>Paul</hi> ſays true, that <hi>Covetouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs is Idolatry,</hi> and that, there be thoſe that make their <hi>Belly their God.</hi> And whoſoever underſtands the difference between the Old and the New Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, will allow, that S. <hi>Hierom</hi> under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood
<pb n="152" facs="tcp:54672:80"/> it; Who, in his Commentaries upon the Prophets, makes all that they, the Prophets ſay, againſt the Idolatry of the ten Tribes, to belong to the Hereſies and Schiſms of Chriſtians; and, all Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks and Schiſmaticks to be Idolaters, in the myſtical ſenſe of the Old Teſtament, under the New. Which is no more, then our Lord ſays of the Samaritans; <hi>That they worſhipped they knew not what;</hi> At ſuch time when it was well enough known, that the Samaritans were no Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laters; worſhipping the only true God of <hi>Iſrael.</hi> For certainly, though all Super<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtition be not Idolatry, yet all Idolatry is Superſtition; Becauſe the chief of Super<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitions is Idolatry. All Superſtitions ſtand upon the ſame ground as Idolatry, and aim at the ſame mark. Man is ſenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, by that Conſcience, which the light of Nature creates, that one true God is to be worſhipped; And that as himſelf ſhall require, not as his Creature is willing to allow. And being therefore ſenſible, that Concupiſcence allows him not that Service, which Conſcience requires, they are willing to pay him in Coin of their own ſtamping; Uſurping the Prero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gative of his Soveraignty, even in that,
<pb n="153" facs="tcp:54672:80"/> whereby they pretend to pay their Alle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giance. Is there any other ſourſe of Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latry but this? For, is it not reaſonable to think, that men can ſatisfie themſelves, and put off the Gods they have made themſelves, with that, which the jealous God, the true God will not be ſerved with? And therefore, Religion teaches, that Idolatry is the Worſhip of the Devil. Not only, becauſe he teaches it; But be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he holds the Opinion of a God, by correſponding with Idolaters in their Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latries. And what is all Superſtition, but redeeming the Service of God in Spirit and Truth, by the ſervice of our Bodies or Eſtates; which may be done, when the inward man is not ſubject to God? Such are the Invocations of Saints, the Worſhipping of their Reliques and Images, the Pilgrimages and Indulgences commended or commanded by the See of <hi>Rome;</hi> And ſuch they may be owned to be, by him that dare not undertake them to be that Idolatry, that was puniſhable with death by the Law of <hi>Moſes.</hi> And being ſuch, it will be puniſhable in all, who, for an undue reſpect to the See of <hi>Rome,</hi> will not have their fellow-ſubjects freed from ſuperſtitious cuſtoms; Nor
<pb n="154" facs="tcp:54672:81"/> obey the Laws of their Country, that give them this freedom. But if this be the due Reaſon, for which it is puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able; the ſame Reaſon will render them puniſhable, who think they ſerve God, by running into Conventicles, in deſpite of the Laws of God and their Country. For, what is that, but a pretenſe of pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the debt of Religion, which Chriſtia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity makes due to God, by worſhipping an Idol of their own ſetting up? That is, as I ſaid afore, by worſhipping God ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to an Imagination of their own erecting; and not according to that, which the common Chriſtianity requires. And thus I am come to the Concluſion, which I intended, without diſputing, whether or no, the Papiſts, by their Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, do exerciſe that Idolatry, which is puniſhable by death in <hi>Moſes</hi> Law. For if capital Penalty lye not in our Caſe; If it be agreed upon, that they are puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able upon the ſame Ground, for which the other ſort of Recuſants are puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able; then is the way clear before me, to proceed to declare, what Penalties, both ſorts of Recuſants are to be, or may be puniſhed with: Suppoſing our Reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion confined within thoſe Bounds, which
<pb n="155" facs="tcp:54672:81"/> the Faith and the Laws of the Catholick Church either determine or allow.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="28" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. XXVIII. All that take Arms againſt the Soveraign, to Reform Religion, may be liable to Capital Puniſhment.</head>
               <p>BUt if the Papiſts cannot be liable to capital puniſhment, as Idolaters, neither can they be liable to it, as limbs of Antichriſt. The name of Antichriſt is a challenge of Soveraign Power; Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the name of Chriſt is ſo; Signifying a Prince and a Prophet, raiſed and ſetled by Gods immediate Word, which is the Soveraign Title. For <hi>Antichriſt</hi> can ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifie nothing, but a counterfeit Chriſt; One that pretends to be Chriſt, and is not; Our Lord Chriſt being the Meſſias, which the Fathers and Prophets from the beginning expected. But the Soveraign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of Chriſt is declared by himſelf, to be a meer Spiritual Soveraignty; which all the Jews, even the Apoſtles before our Lords death, expected to be a tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Kingdom. And therefore, whoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever
<pb n="156" facs="tcp:54672:82"/> it is, that groundeth Soveraignty upon Chriſtianity, though he be not Antichriſt for that, yet is he the enemy of all Chriſtian States, for it. And ſo are the Subjects of all Chriſtian States, that think themſelves free of their Allegiance to Princes, or States, Excommunicated by the Pope. And upon this account, I deny not, that Papiſts may become liable to capital puniſhment, or to baniſhment with confiſcation; Which ſeems to be, of the two, the greater puniſhment. But this, neither common to all Papiſts, nor proper to Papiſts alone. For, that this is not the Faith of all Papiſts, I need no more, then the diſtance between the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular Prieſts and the Jeſuits here, to prove. And that it is not proper to Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts alone, I need no more, then the Scottiſh Covenant, and the troubles of the three Kingdoms upon it, to prove. And therefore, it is a thing abſolutely neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, to make thoſe Penalties juſt, which the Laws inflict upon the Papiſts; that they diſtinguiſh between the Cauſe of Religion, common to all, and the Cauſe of them, that make it a point of Religion, to violate their Allegiance to a Soveraign depoſed by the Pope. Nay it will be
<pb n="157" facs="tcp:54672:82"/> neceſſary, in point of Juſtice, to impoſe the ſame Penalties, upon all of all Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gions, that may think themſelves diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charged of their Allegiance, upon any account of Religion whatſoever. It is manifeſt, that they who take Arms againſt their Soveraign, to reform Religion, do ground themſelves upon the Title of Religion, and think themſelves tyed by their Chriſtianity to do it; As they who take Arms againſt their Prince, depoſed by the Pope, think themſelves tyed in Chriſtianity, to execute his Sentence. Thoſe whom the people follow, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forming Religion againſt the will of their Soveraign; Thoſe they make as much Judges, in reforming Religion, as the other do the Pope. And all that refuſe to ſecure their Soveraign by Oath, that they will neither lead nor follow any man, in reforming Religion, without his Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, deſerve to be out of the protecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of that <hi>Sword,</hi> which he <hi>weareth not in vain.</hi> They fall into the Caſe of the Jews, expecting the Meſſias; For, when they imagine, that he is come, they will think themſelves diſpenſed with, by their Religion, for any Bond of Allegiance. But Chriſtian Princes and States are not wont,
<pb n="158" facs="tcp:54672:83"/> ſo far as I know, to think themſelves ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cured by the Oath of Jews. Let this be a difference, which they make between Jews and Chriſtians, to take the Oath of their Chriſtian Subjects, for ſecurity of their Allegiance; Becauſe true Chriſtia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity obliges all good Chriſtians, to bear Allegiance to their Soveraigns, not to be diſpenſed with, upon any account of Chriſtianity; Notwithſtanding we ſee, that there are thoſe, that count them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves the beſt Chriſtians, that do think themſelves diſpenſed with in their Alle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giance, upon divers and ſeveral accounts of their Chriſtianity. But let this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, having had tryal of contrary pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenſes, think it ſelf bound, to declare the ſame Penalties, againſt the ſame Crimes; And able to impoſe the utmoſt Penalties, upon all that ſhall refuſe, to ſecure their Soveraign by Oath, of their Allegiance. And ſince the allowance, which the Law makes, in underſtanding the Oath of Supremacy, evidences, that it may be underſtood, in a ſenſe offenſive, in point of Religion; let it be thought time, to antiquate the old, and to inact a new form, that may tye all Subjects as Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects, without pretenſe of offending any
<pb n="159" facs="tcp:54672:83"/> Religion; by condemning all Religions, that make difficulty to undertake it, for irreligious.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="29" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. XXIX. What Penalties the Protection of Religion requires.</head>
               <p>NOw I am to ſay, how far Chriſtian Powers are to puniſh Hereticks and Schiſmaticks. For, it is too late for me to ſay, that they may puniſh their Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venticles, having declared the reaſon, why they may do it; And being now only to draw the conſequence of that reaſon, how far they are to do, or may do it. Here, I muſt firſt marvel at our Independents; ſome of whom have diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted, in very good earneſt, that it is not lawful, for Civil Powers, to impoſe Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nalties upon Religion. Whereas the World knows, that there never was any ſuch Religion in the World, as that of Independents, before the planting of <hi>New England.</hi> And that ſince, thoſe that framed Independent Congregations there, upon a Covenant, whereby they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce
<pb n="160" facs="tcp:54672:84"/> 
                  <hi>One Catholick Church,</hi> and <hi>One Baptiſm for Remiſſion of Sins;</hi> have not only baniſhed Antinomians, and put Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers to death; But have impoſed a Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nalty of five ſhillings a Lords-day, upon all that come not to hear their Sermons. For, though this Penalty is not ſtrictly exacted at preſent, yet it lyes at preſent. Whereby, the greater part of His Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſties Subjects in that Plantation, are not only hindred, from exerciſing the Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion injoyned by the Laws of this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom; But alſo their Children dye un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baptized, themſelves live and dye with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the Communion of the Euchariſt, and, in fine, their Souls are murthered, by this Tyranny of their miſbelieving fellow-Subjects. Whether all this by their <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent,</hi> or by <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſurpation,</hi> I leave to thoſe that may redreſs it, to judge. But, if the Protection of Religion, and of the Church lye, in maintaining thoſe Rights, which the Soveraign Power finds the Church poſſeſt of, when it undertakes the Profeſſion of Chriſtianity; And all the Right of the Church, (which it hath, by the meer conſent of thoſe that voluntarily undertake Chriſtianity) reſolves into Excommunication; Then is not the
<pb n="161" facs="tcp:54672:84"/> Church protected in the Rights of it, by Chriſtian Powers, unleſs their Laws in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able the Excommunication of the Church to lay hold on all their Subjects. Nor can any inconvenience follow hereupon; Becauſe the Excommunication of the Church, when it is protected by the Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil Power, can never proceed, but upon Cauſes which the Law allows. Now, ther are two ſorts of Excommunicate perſons, according to the Premiſes; One are they that <hi>Excommunicate themſelves;</hi> the other, they that are Excommunica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by the Church. For, though they Excommunicate themſelves, yet, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they are to be <hi>avoided</hi> by the Flock, from whence they depart, when they Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communicate themſelves, they are to be held, as if they were Excommunicate by the Church. Now, if they who thus Excommunicate themſelves ſhould be under no Penalty of Civil Power, for ſo doing, I would fain know, what that Protection, which Chriſtian Powers muſt needs owne, to the Chriſtianity which themſelves profeſs, can avail it. For, if the Church Excommunicate thoſe that perform not the Chriſtianity which they profeſs, and the Excommunicate be free
<pb n="162" facs="tcp:54672:85"/> to run into the Conventicles of thoſe that Excommunicate themſelves, whowill care for performing the Chriſtianity which he profeſſeth? Or how ſhall the Church and Religion ſubſiſt, when no man need to care for performing the Chriſtianity which he profeſſeth? This is the danger which is come ſo near, to bring this Church to nothing, at this time. On the one ſide, all Papiſts Excommunicate themſelves, on the other ſide, all that run into Conventicles. The Papiſts, we all know, are under Penalties grievous enough; If we ſpeak of that part, which doth not decline their Allegiance. As for thoſe that do, I have already ſet the conſideration of them aſide. And yet there is this Apology, for the ſeverity of thoſe Laws; That they do take off the Penalty of perpetual impriſonment, which by the Ancient Laws of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, introduced under the Papacy, lyes againſt all that are Excommunicate; And therefore is to lye, againſt all that Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communicate themſelves. If there be a reaſon, why ſuch ſevere Laws ſhould be in force againſt them, can any, that wears the face of a man, ſay, why <hi>the other ſort of Recuſants</hi> ſhould be free from all
<pb n="163" facs="tcp:54672:85"/> Penalties? I think the World is ſenſible hereof, in the ſuſpenſion of the Penal Laws againſt the Recuſants; Which, under his late Majeſty, was charged with ſuch violent jealouſies: and now paſſes without diſcontent, becauſe there is nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther conſcience nor ſhame, to levy thoſe Penalties upon them, and none upon the Conventicles. In the mean time, <hi>Atheiſm, Prophaneneſs, Blaſphemy, Apoſtaſie, Hereſie</hi> ſhelter themſelves under the Communion of the Church, which the Laws protect; and will needs be of that Religion, which they may profeſs, and need not perform. And, how long this Church can continue this Church, upon thoſe terms, let thoſe judge, whom it concerns. My buſineſs is only this; That, if thoſe that Excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municate themſelves be under no Penal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, thoſe that are Excommunicate by the Church need not care, that they are Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communicate. And ſo the Church is not protected, becauſe the Excommunication of the Church is not in force; That is, it is no Penalty to be Excommunicate, to all that can <hi>think it is none.</hi> And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, unleſs it draw a <hi>Penalty of this World</hi> after it; that all may have occaſion to avoid the Penalty of the World to come,
<pb n="164" facs="tcp:54672:86"/> by avoiding the Penalty of this World; the Church is not protected. It may be thought, that the Church is protected nevertheleſs, by the <hi>Priviledge</hi> of recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving the Tyths, of thoſe that decline it, and of the Truſt it manages, of diſpenſing Church-goods. And this is, indeed, part of the Penalty, by which they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deem their Recuſancy; In as much, as they are put to maintain the Religion which they invent; Church-goods, though they be <hi>Publick goods,</hi> yet, being originally affected to the maintenance of that Church, which the Law protecteth. But that, being a Penalty of their own choice, ſatisfies not the Protection of the Religion which the Kingdom profeſſeth; until the Law make it a <hi>diſgrace,</hi> and a degree of <hi>Infamy,</hi> to ſtand Excommuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate, whether by themſelves, or by the Church. And, ſeeing all Diſcipline, even that of the Clergy, ends in Excommuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation; To maintain the Revenue, and let go Diſcipline, would be, <hi>to ſell Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion</hi> for the Revenue of the Church. For what would this be, but a tempting of the debauched, into the Service of the Church, when there is no Diſcipline, to reſtrain their debauches? The complaints
<pb n="165" facs="tcp:54672:86"/> of this time ſhew this to be a Perſecution, which the <hi>Sects</hi> of the time <hi>bring upon the Church.</hi> For, Diſcipline is releaſed, for fear to ſtir, and for hope to gain Sectaries; and the fault is laid upon the Clergy, that ſuffer in the releaſing of Diſcipline. But Chriſtian Powers are bound, not only not to perſecute the Church themſelves, but not to ſuffer Sects to perſecute it. And to avoid trouble, by releaſing Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipline, may be the way to find it, in the means of avoiding it. Certainly, till Excommunication (which is the <hi>utmoſt reſort</hi> of all Diſcipline) be in force, we can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not ſay we have a Church; but only, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe we have Laws, by which it ought to be in force; And becauſe we hope to have Laws, by which it will be in force. Men may amuſe themſelves, with the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nited Provinces;</hi> which, they ſay, flouriſh in trade and riches, by maintaining all Religions. But the que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion is of Religion, not of Trade, nor Riches. If it could be ſaid, that their Religion is improved, with their Trade, the example were conſiderable. But, they that would reſtore and improve the Religion, that flouriſhed in <hi>England</hi> thirty years ago, muſt not take up with
<pb n="166" facs="tcp:54672:87"/> the <hi>baſe Alloy</hi> of that which is ſeen in the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nited Provinces.</hi> Nor is this a reproach to them, but a truth of Gods Word; that Religion and Trade cannot be both at once at the height. Beſides, there is a <hi>Religion of the State</hi> in the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nited Provin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces:</hi> and other Religions are tolerated there, becauſe they were in being before the State was ſetled, or contributed to the ſetling of it, upon expectation of being tolerated in their Religions, when it ſhould be ſetled. But when the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nited Provin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces</hi> were in danger to break in pieces, upon a Diſpute in Religion, in the year 1618. and when the point of Religion was decided by the point of that Sword, which decided by the point of that Sword, which inabled the <hi>States General</hi> to give Law to the States of <hi>Holland;</hi> Let him, that now may ſee more Aprons then Clokes come from their Arminian Gon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregations, tell me, whether the point were decided by a Penalty, or not. But let him tell me alſo, whether it had not been better, to have decided it no fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, then the Catholick Church had de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cided it; then to indanger the Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation, (as now it is in danger, by admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the Socinians into Communion with the Arminians) in caſe the Penalty ſhould
<pb n="167" facs="tcp:54672:87"/> prove inſufficient. As for the Diſcourſes, that threaten the tranſporting of Eſtates, upon Penalties for Religion; and, that would incourage ſtrangers to plant and improve Trade here; Who knows not, that the Conventicles now Uſurped were firſt erected by the late War? And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore muſt be preſumed to cheriſh the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenſe of it. And how eaſie is it, for thoſe that inact Penalties for Religion, to provide, that it be for no mans eaſe, to declare himſelf an <hi>enemy to his Country?</hi> Nor let any man think, that ſtrangers are affected in Religion, as thoſe at home are; who pretend, by Religion, <hi>to give Law to their Country.</hi> The diſſenſions on foot among us may well diſcourage them from planting among us, to improve Trade with us. The improving of the Reformation, and the ſetling of it, would be but an incouragement to them, to paſs by thoſe frivolous pretenſes, which carry us to theſe frantick diſtances. In the mean time, be it conſidered, that Inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendency, which was not <hi>in rerum natura</hi> at the planting of <hi>New England,</hi> being once ſetled there, by the pretenſe which their Patent or Patents gave, became ſo fruitful, that within twenty years, they
<pb n="168" facs="tcp:54672:88"/> were able to cut off their Prince. For., all that love truth muſt acknowledge, that they were Independents that did that horrible Act. And then conſider, how you would hope to have it re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrained, if S. <hi>Pauls</hi> precept of avoiding Sectaries that Excommunicate themſelves be not in force, by Canonical Penalties, upon them that are to <hi>avoid;</hi> And by temporal Penalties, upon them that are to be <hi>avoided.</hi> For, converſing together, otherwiſe then for Trade and Commerce, experience ſhews, that infection is un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>avoidable. And therefore the Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, which the Kingdom owes the Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion which it profeſſeth, neceſſarily re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires, not only, that it be maintain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, <hi>at the Charge of the Schiſmaticks</hi> in it. For, as that is the proper Penalty, for them to redeem their Recuſancy with; So is it the Juſtice, which they owe their fellow-Subjects, whom they have hither<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to kept in that Aegyptian Bondage. And this Reaſon will extend the ſame obliga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, to all other Plantations and Reſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dences of Engliſh; To wit, that, if they be ſuffered to live in another Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on there, account may be taken of them
<pb n="169" facs="tcp:54672:88"/> here, that they be not <hi>admitted to Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion</hi> here, without renouncing that which they lived in there. That they be not ſuffered there, without maintaining the Religion profeſſed here. It extends alſo to French and Dutch, and all Forreign Churches, that, for Trade, or otherwiſe, may be allowed to plant here. For, either they hold Communion with this Church, or not. If not, it muſt be Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal, both for thoſe of this Church, to Communicate with them, and for them, to admit thoſe of this Church. If ſo, yet, ſo long as there is cauſe of jealouſie, there muſt be proviſion, that neither Church be declined, upon any pretenſe of ſuch jealouſie. I will here add one thing, before I make an end; Becauſe it may be demanded, how the Law of the Land may make Excommunication turn to <hi>diſgrace,</hi> and to ſome degree of <hi>Infa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my.</hi> The anſwer is; Let the Law of the Land provide, that no man may have <hi>Chriſtian Burial,</hi> (that is, be buried in <hi>Conſecrate ground,</hi> and <hi>with the Office of the Church)</hi> but he whom his Curate knows to have received the Communion within the year; And, I believe, the moſt part of them that Excommunicate
<pb n="170" facs="tcp:54672:89"/> themſelves will return of themſelves. But then it muſt be provided, and the Biſhop muſt be inabled by Law, to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge that Curate of <hi>Office</hi> and <hi>Benefice,</hi> that ſhall falſifie his truſt in that point. Now give me leave to demand, whether the Church be under <hi>Protection,</hi> or under <hi>Perſecution;</hi> If the Curate be not inabled by Law, to refuſe Chriſtian Burial to thoſe, of whoſe Salvation he can give no account, becauſe they withdraw them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves from his Cure.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="30" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. XXX. The Condition of reconciling Recuſants.</head>
               <p>BUt this not all; There is one point yet behind. For, whenſoever the Church Excommunicates for notorious and ſcandalous ſin, to reſtore him that is ſo Excommunicate to Communion would be to murther his Soul, and Chriſtianity both at once; not ſuppoſing ſome pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portionable preſumption of amendment, in him that is reſtored. This therefore <hi>muſt hold, as the Reaſon of it holds,</hi> in thoſe that Excommunicate themſelves; In the
<pb n="171" facs="tcp:54672:89"/> reconciling of Hereticks and Schiſma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks to the Church. And this, the pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice of the Whole Church of God from the beginning ſhews them, that are wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to underſtand the reaſon of it, before they tread that Authority under foot, which the common Chriſtianity obliges all to follow. Shew me any Hereſie or Schiſm ever reſtored to the Church, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out renouncing the ſame, and I will con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs, that the <hi>Church it ſelf turned Heretick or Schiſmatick</hi> from the ſame date. Only there is a difference to be put, between Hereſie and Schiſm, and other <hi>Perſonal Crimes.</hi> For, I ſee no reaſon, why we ſhould not call other Crimes Perſonal, in oppoſition to Hereſie and Schiſm; Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe we call it not Hereſie or Schiſm, till <hi>Scparation</hi> be made. A falſe Belief in Fundamentals is Hereſie before God, a Reſolution to divide the Church is Schiſm before God, both deſtructive to Salvation, before Separation be made. But Separation is the diſeaſe we pretend to cure, without prejudicing the health of Gods Church. And therefore, ſhould Separation be made to maintain a Profeſſion, that <hi>Simony,</hi> for example, or <hi>Sacriledge,</hi> or any other deadly Crime is
<pb n="172" facs="tcp:54672:90"/> no ſin, the Party ſo formed would be, <hi>ipſo facto,</hi> an Hereſie. Perſonal Crimes, then, muſt be reſtored to Communion, upon preſumption of Perſonal Conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion from the ſame. But Hereſies and Schiſms becoming <hi>Bodies,</hi> by profeſſing an <hi>Ingagement,</hi> may be re-united to the Church in <hi>Body,</hi> renouncing the Separa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in which they ſtood ingaged. For, there is reaſonable preſumption, that the <hi>Leaders</hi> would not renounce, if they did not repent them of it. As for the <hi>People,</hi> that only follows and leads not, it is moſt true and juſt to maintain, that Hereſie and Schiſm is a Bar to Salvation; though we allow hope of Salvation to the ſimple, that follow malicious Leaders, out of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vincible ignorance. It is therefore no blemiſh to the Church, to receive them, as they departed, in company of their Leaders. For their Salvation is provided for, when the Bar is removed. The ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience of our Caſe makes this conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable. At His Majeſties Return, it was inacted, that ſuch Uſurpers, as were poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed of <hi>dead Places,</hi> ſhould hold, without inquiring, whether <hi>Ordained</hi> or not. Whereby it might ſeem to them, that found no fault with their own Title,
<pb n="173" facs="tcp:54672:90"/> that the Law of the Kingdom owned their Ordinations to be good. But with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out cauſe. For, the Kingdom being then under that <hi>Force,</hi> which was not as yet removed, (a thing manifeſt enough; The Church not being yet reſtored) the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining of them, (which I am neither to juſtifie nor to blame) was nothing but the induring of that Force upon Part, rather then call in queſtion the <hi>Whole.</hi> But hereupon, they that had got this colour for their Poſſeſſion, were not like to diſowne that Ordination, which the Law of the Land had ſeemed thus far to owne. So, the way was paved for the Schiſm on foot, by refuſing the Act of Uniformity, when they were imployed, without recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciling themſelves to the Church, by fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>going their Schiſm. Some may think, that I abate more then this, for their ſakes, when I allow them <hi>Satisfaction by Conference;</hi> yea and Laws to be changed for their ſatisfaction, if juſt cauſe may ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear. But it is no more then I would allow <hi>Popiſh Recuſants,</hi> to juſtifie the Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nalties, that will be always neceſſary, becauſe they prefer the Authority of the See of <hi>Rome,</hi> (forbidding all Treaty of Religion without it) before the common
<pb n="174" facs="tcp:54672:91"/> Chriſtianity, requiring Reformation in the Chriſtianity of the Kingdom. For, do not they deſerve thoſe Penalties, who refuſe to aſſiſt their Country, in a work ſo concerning the common Salvation, upon juſt terms? This I am ſure, ſuppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing ſatisfaction, there can be no difficulty in departing from <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſurped Ordinations,</hi> and from the Schiſm grounded upon the ſame. And therefore, it is only the <hi>ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemnity of Renouncing</hi> that is abated, and the <hi>Irregularity</hi> that is pardoned; And that, by the example of the firſt Great Council, in the Caſe of the Meletians. And that, becauſe they renounce not the Catholick Church, but acknowledge a <hi>National Church;</hi> Which they cannot ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge, upon due grounds, but they muſt acknowledge the Catholick Church. And therefore, I ſay not the ſame of the Independents; Who are <hi>Banded</hi> into a Profeſſion deſtructive to it, upon a <hi>Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant.</hi> For that Covenant is it, that muſt be expreſly and formally renounced, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they can be capable of <hi>Communion</hi> with the Church; And much more of <hi>Orders.</hi> To grant them Communion otherwiſe, is to make the Church guilty of their Schiſm, which it alloweth. And
<pb n="175" facs="tcp:54672:91"/> ſo, to give Popiſh Recuſants a juſt cauſe to refuſe Communion with it. As for other Sects of Antinomians, Anabaptiſts, and the like; When any man knows, up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on what Grounds they Excommunicate themſelves, and how far they are Banded into Sects, it will then be no difficult thing to ſay, how they are to be Recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciled, ſo as their Schiſms and Hereſies may be duely Renounced. A thing which muſt be conſidered, in thoſe that were Preſbyterians, before they broke into Conventicles. For, ſince that came to paſs, who ſhall warrant, that they have been guided by none but ſuch, as have Preſbyterian Orders? Or that they ſtand now to that Religion, which the Rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lion once made Law to the Kingdom? Which if they do not, who ſhall warrant, or how ſhall the Church be ſatisfied, that they do depart from their Schiſms, with their Leaders? And indeed, the Inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendents, though they be Banded into a Sect, by a Covenant; yet, if once they be diſbanded, who ſhall anſwer for them, that they will follow their Lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders? And all this by virtue of the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>criledge, whereby they all betray the <hi>Authority of the Church,</hi> and with it the
<pb n="176" facs="tcp:54672:92"/> Chriſtian Faith, to the <hi>Will of their People,</hi> to debauch them into the ſame Schiſm with themſelves. Which if it be conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered, perhaps it will appear, that the <hi>Forbearance</hi> which I have granted, can, for this reaſon, extend no further, then to the <hi>Perſons</hi> of thoſe that deſerted their Churches, rather then ſubmit to the Act of Uniformity. Nor ſhall it trouble me, if my Opinion be found to come to no more. For the Opinions of private per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons are to content themſelves, with de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claring <hi>what may be;</hi> Leaving them that are concerned, to judge what is. But, as for the way of Reconciling thoſe which ſhall be converted, to the Church; in that, the <hi>Apoſtolical Wiſdom of the Primi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Catholick Church</hi> is of neceſſity to take place. For, Schiſm or Hereſie be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Bar to the effect of Baptiſm, which is the <hi>Gift of the Holy Ghoſt;</hi> And the renouncing of it being the removing of that Bar; It follows, that all that ſhall return are to be reconciled by <hi>Confirma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> as always they were reconciled to the Primitive Catholick Church. This were eaſier done, could it be preſumed, that all would follow their Leaders. But if that cannot be preſumed, if they muſt
<pb n="177" facs="tcp:54672:92"/> be reconciled one by one, yet is that no more, than the work of an <hi>Epiſcopal Viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, from Pariſh to Pariſh:</hi> A thing practiſed and uſual in the Church, after the building of Pariſh-Churches, in the worſt of thoſe times, in which, the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nons which I have commended took place. But now, as for Quakers, we are no more to reckon them <hi>among Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, then the Gnoſticks and Manichees of Old, then the Mahumetans at preſent.</hi> For they do openly owne, the Dictate of their own Spirits to be as much <hi>the Word of God</hi> as the Scriptures. And that is as much, as ſerves to create all ſuch new Sects, as, acknowledging the Scriptures ſo far as they pleaſe, introduce the pretenſes of their own Revelations, where they think fit. For, when the <hi>private Spirit</hi> is equalled with <hi>Gods Word,</hi> the laſt Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctate, as in mens <hi>laſt Wills,</hi> muſt of neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity take place. Only this difference; That, whereas <hi>Gnoſticks, Manichees, Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>humetans,</hi> followed, or do follow their Leaders Spirit, Quakers follow every one their own. And therefore are the more contemptible, and the more reducible, whenſoever a courſe ſhall be eſtabliſhed. Certainly, did they ſee, that they cannot
<pb n="178" facs="tcp:54672:93"/> be reconciled but as ſo many <hi>Renegades,</hi> they would bethink themſelves, before they went on in their madneſs. Eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally, did the Law ſet before them, that this their Poſition is not reconcileable to <hi>Civil Truſt:</hi> Always obliging them, to the moſt deſperate Acts of Treaſon, and violence to their Country, that they can imagine <hi>their own Spirit</hi> to dictate. Up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on which account, it cannot be beyond the merit of their madneſs, that they are made <hi>ſervi poenae</hi> by Law, as the Roman Laws call it; That is, that they are tranſported to work in the Plantations. For, they that take upon them to impoſe upon their Country, that the <hi>Offices of common Civility</hi> are <hi>Acts of Idolatry;</hi> What is not to be expected from their madneſs, who, as the Caſe is, dare pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend, that it ought to be Law to all Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians? But, ſince the Law is to provide for ſuch People, it is manifeſt, that it is to provide, that they may not fail of the truſt which the Church and Kingdom en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters into, with thoſe whom they receive to Communion, but that they muſt fail of the Civil Truſt of Subjects; That is, that their <hi>Teſtimonies be not receivable in Law,</hi> that they be diſabled to <hi>ſue at Law,</hi>
                  <pb n="179" facs="tcp:54672:93"/> that they be diſabled to make <hi>Wills,</hi> or to get by Wills, or any thing elſe within the effect of Civil Truſt. And this muſt alſo be the Penalty of the <hi>Leviathan,</hi> and all that have or may follow him, either into <hi>Apoſtaſie</hi> or <hi>Atheiſm.</hi> For, they who declare themſelves at freedom, to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwear the Chriſtian Faith, can never be held by any bond of Civil Truſt. It muſt alſo be the Penalty of all Sects, that may <hi>relapſe,</hi> after they may have been recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciled; At leaſt in that Proportion, which, that part of the Faith, which their reſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctive Sect denieth, holds, to the whole Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of Chriſtianity; which <hi>Apoſtacy</hi> and <hi>Atheiſm</hi> deſtroy at once. For, it may be a Queſtion, why the Kingdom ſhould be counted a Chriſtian Kingdom, if the Laws of it ſet not ſome mark of <hi>Infamy</hi> or <hi>Diſgrace</hi> upon the enemies of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianity, according to the Rate of their Enmity; Which, only the inforcing of Excommunication, by the Laws, can do.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:54672:94"/>
            <head>Books Printed for and Sold by <hi>James Collins</hi> at the <hi>Kings-Head</hi> in <hi>Weſtminſter-Hall.</hi>
            </head>
            <list>
               <item>A Blow at <hi>Modern Sadduciſm,</hi> in ſome Philoſophical Conſiderations about <hi>Witchcraft.</hi> To which is added, The Relation of the <hi>Famed Diſturbance</hi> by the <hi>Drummer,</hi> in the Houſe of M. <hi>Mompeſſon.</hi> With ſome Reflections on <hi>Drollery</hi> and <hi>Atheiſm.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Plus ultra;</hi> or the Progreſs and Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vancement of Knowledge ſince the days of <hi>Ariſtotle. Octavo.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A <hi>Loyal Tear</hi> drop'd on the <hi>Vault</hi> of our late <hi>Martyr'd Soveraign,</hi> in an <hi>Anni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſary Sermon</hi> on the day of his <hi>Murther. Quarto.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>All three by <hi>Joſ. Glanvill,</hi> A. M. and Rector of <hi>Bath.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Triumphs of <hi>Rome</hi> over <hi>Deſpiſed Proteſtancy:</hi> Written by Biſhop <hi>Hall. Octavo.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A Sermon preached before the <hi>Peers, Octob.</hi> 10. 1666. being the Faſt-day for the late <hi>Fire:</hi> By <hi>Seth</hi> Lord Biſhop of <hi>Oxon. Quarto.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The <hi>Practice</hi> of <hi>Serious Godlineſs:</hi> Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectionately
<pb facs="tcp:54672:94"/> recommended and directed in ſome Religious Counſels of a Pious Mother to her dear Daughters. 12<hi rend="sup">o</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A Diſcourſe of <hi>Subterranean Treaſure:</hi> By a Member of the Royal Society. 12<hi rend="sup">o</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The General Aſſembly: A Sermon by <hi>Francis Fullwood.</hi> D. D. <hi>Quarto.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Forty Sermons by <hi>Anthony Farindon.</hi> B. B. <hi>Fol.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Rea's Flora, Ceres &amp; Pomona.</hi> Fol.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Epiſcopacy Apoſtolical;</hi> or a Conſent of the Forreign Churches to the Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline of the Church of <hi>England:</hi> Written by Biſhop <hi>Moreton,</hi> and publiſhed with a long Preface, by <hi>Henry Yelverton</hi> Baronet. <hi>Octavo.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A Diſcourſe of the Uſe of Reaſon in the Aſſairs of Religion againſt the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Opinions of the Sects of this Age. <hi>Quarto.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A <hi>Private Conference</hi> between a <hi>RICH ALDERMAN</hi> and a poor Country Vicar, made publick, wherein is diſcourſed the Obligation of Oaths which have been impoſed on the Subjects of <hi>England,</hi> with other matters relating to the preſent State of Affairs.</item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
